







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/did/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>DID</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/did/</link>
        
        
            <title>DID</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Everybody, regardless of if they have a dissociative disorder or not, has parts to their personality. For example, one may generally behave differently at work than they do at home&mdash;they have a &ldquo;work self&rdquo; and a &ldquo;home self&rdquo;.
In someone without a dissociative disorder,
when one transitions between their work self and their home self, they likely have a continuous internal sense of memory and identity&mdash;when they&rsquo;re at home, they still remember what happened while they were at work and relate to those experiences. Using graphs, we can represent the relationship between their work self and their home self with two nodes, each denoting a part of their personality, and one edge connecting the nodes, relating the shared sense of memory and identity between the two parts.



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div id="twoparts" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/twoparts.js"></script>


Here, in an individual without a dissociative disorder, their work self and their home self are aware of and relate to the thoughts, feelings, and actions of the other part.
But people have more than just a work self and a home self&mdash;they have a multitude of parts, representing many different facets of their personality. For simplicity&rsquo;s sake we will only look at 6 of these parts to represent their entire personality, but without loss of generality, this concept can be extrapolated to as many parts as needed to represent the whole personality.
In an individual without a dissociative disorder, their parts form a complete graph&mdash;all the nodes are connected with edges to all the other nodes, so all their parts remember and relate to the actions of other parts.</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div id="singlet" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/singlet.js"></script>


<p>The similar colors of the nodes, or parts, represents the small variations between parts of their whole personality.
Because their parts are familiar with and aware of one another, their personality changes would generally blend smoothly between their parts.</p>
<p>Things may be a bit different in an individual with a dissociative disorder. While they still may have similar types of parts to someone without a dissociative disorder, their graph may look something like this:</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div id="system1" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/system1.js"></script>


<p>Their parts do not form a complete graph&mdash;the lack of connection between their parts represents the lack of continuity of memory and identity between parts of self. The different colors represent that their personality variation is likely to be larger than that of a more integrated individual because their parts are more separated.
In an individual with DID, when one part of them is active, they may experience the world in an entirely different way than when a different part is active. They may have a different awareness of their life, different memories, and have an different felt sense of identity. Their life is compartmentalized into different pockets of awareness, identity, memory, and experience that they switch between to experience life. Not all of their parts are aware of the feelings and actions of other parts, and this is by design&mdash;from a young age, they learned to separate parts of self who hold difficult memories and experiences from other parts of self. This separation of parts of self is protective, as it allowed them to learn and grow as a child when some parts of them were active, while using different parts to compartmentalize traumatic experiences away from the more healthy parts of self.</p>
<p>It is important to note that just as everybody&rsquo;s personality structure is different from one anothers, people with DID are going to have a different system structures, which depends on their reactions to their individual life experiences.
For example, part of my system structure may look something like this:</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div id="mysystem" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/mysystem.js"></script>


<p>This is a far overly simplistic view, and only shows the parts of my system structure that I am aware of and am comfortable sharing here. Here, I use the weights of edges between nodes to represent how connected two parts are, I use squares to denote clusters of parts rather than individual parts, and I only show three parts in each cluster when there are actually many more. In reality, I believe my system is much more complex than can be shown on a simple graph<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<!--


The graph above is an overly simplistic view of an example system structure. In reality, it would be hard to capture an entire system structure with
Because of the lack of connection between parts, different parts of self 


However, this can cause problems in daily functioning as an adult as different parts of self may have different motivations and awareness of their current life

while separating the traumatic experiences to other parts when they are active. 

While it isn't necessarily important for individuals without a dissociative disorder to map out their parts[^1], since their parts are aware of the 

Because these parts of self are separated, they act as different compartments of experience, 
In order to map memory, awareness, and identity differences between the parts, it is vital that someone with a dissociative disorder learns more about their parts of their personality. 
[^1]: As far as I'm aware, this could be considered Internal Family Systems (IFS) therapy, which is a popular therapy modality for individuals without DID.

Different individuals with dissociative disorders are going 

-->
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>To be more accurate, I&rsquo;d also probably need to use a directed graph to show the one-way amnesia I sometimes experience&mdash;a part may be aware of the actions of another part, but that other part isn&rsquo;t aware of the first part. This is quite common in my system.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/visualgraphs/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/visualgraphs/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 17:56:15 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>A visual representation of DID using graphs</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>My relationship with my DID diagnoses&mdash;both with regards to accepting it as my diagnosis and understanding how it affects me&mdash;has evolved significantly since starting therapy.
Over the past approximately 1.5 years, I&rsquo;ve been through several distinct stages of recovery. In this post, I reflect back on how far I&rsquo;ve come on my recovery journey so far.</p>
<h4 id="stage-0-buildup-to-starting-therapy-october-2021--january-2022">Stage 0: Buildup to starting therapy (October 2021&ndash;January 2022)</h4>
<p>In October of 2021, I had what I thought were a series of panic attacks due to a highly specific trigger of trauma that I experienced as a child.
I eventually met with a psychiatrist at my school who, upon hearing of my symptoms and pediatric mental health history, likely immediately knew that I had a dissociative disorder and recommended therapy.
They connected me with a therapist who specializes in dissociative disorders, who I started working with in January 2022.</p>
<p>At this time, I genuinely did not know what DID was. I was aware I experienced depersonalization<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, and that I had some strange psychiatric symptoms in my childhood, but I thought I was mentally healthy other than that panic associated with a trigger. I started therapy with the hopes of stopping the inconvenient &ldquo;panic attacks&rdquo;, and came in with the intention that I&rsquo;d only be in therapy for a year or so. I truly had no idea what I was signing up for.</p>
<h4 id="stage-1-denial-january--april-2022">Stage 1: Denial (January&ndash;April 2022)</h4>
<p>Upon learning that DID was my working diagnosis, the first stage was denial.
Despite the fact that I had a prior pediatric dissociative disorder diagnosis and had been experiencing symptoms of DID my entire life, I genuinely did not think I had DID.
Several parts of me believed that I was faking to get out of my adult responsibilities<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, other parts thought that DID was fake as I was matching my symptoms to the disorder because I was reading so much academic literature about it<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, and one adamant part thought my therapist was inducing my symptoms<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
In fact, none of these excuses were correct, but the denial was protective&mdash;it prevented me, albeit momentarily, from the awareness that I had a disorder caused by childhood trauma, which I was not yet ready to to terms with.</p>
<p>During this stage, I didn&rsquo;t really even know that my symptoms were symptoms&mdash;they were normal to me, so I assumed everyone was experiencing what I did. I was switching between parts with full amnesia, but <a href="/posts/amnesia/">amnesia is tricky, and less obvious than it sounds</a>, so I genuinely didn&rsquo;t know I had any amnesia. I was emotionally numb, like I normally am, and life was a blur. During this stage, I was unaware that I was affected by a dissociative disorder because I refused to see it.</p>
<h4 id="stage-2-acceptance-april--august-2022">Stage 2: Acceptance (April&ndash;August 2022)</h4>
<p>The next stage was acceptance.
In April, I had several strange experiences that could only be explained by me having DID. I started noticing switches between parts, and became aware that my handwriting changed depending on which part of me was active. I began to accept that I actually did have a dissociative disorder, and that the mental health professionals I was working with were correct.
My symptoms starting becoming more obvious, with me realizing I experience full amnesia between parts by repeatedly finding evidence that I had done things that I had no memory of doing. I also began having more dissociative episodes, where traumatized parts would take over, but thankfully most of them occurred in therapy or while I was home alone. I began experiencing rapid switching, where I switch between parts in a quick succession in response to stress. This is a disorienting experience, which typically ends in me being very confused and having a headache.</p>
<p>However, while my symptoms starting coming to light, I could not tell apart my parts&mdash;I was sometimes able to tell when I switched, but I wouldn&rsquo;t know which part I switched to or from. This was a particularly scary stage, as I started seeing the chaos but I simultaneously had no idea what exactly was going on&mdash;how was my system structured? I had no idea&mdash;I hadn&rsquo;t had time to collect enough data yet.</p>
<h4 id="stage-3-seeing-my-parts-august-2022--april-2023">Stage 3: Seeing my parts (August 2022&ndash;April 2023)</h4>
<p>In the next stage, rather than simply seeing <em>symptoms</em>, I started seeing the <em>parts</em> underlying those symptoms.  This was a very gradual process, but over time I started being able to correlate my handwriting changes with changes in other attributes, like vocal tone and posture. I looked back at what I remembered of my life and started being able to see what roles different parts played. I began to learn more about my system structure, and realized that I was polyfragmented.
I started assigning labels to parts that would come up frequently, and started mapping out my amnesia between parts. I sought out reasons for why my parts split in the way that they did, and why my system was so chaotic. During this time, my system was very unstable, but I internally felt fine&mdash;I was used to the chaos. I had significant lapses in memory and was trying my hardest to advance in my PhD program despite this, although I was having difficulties with memory and <a href="/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/">fluctuating intelligence</a><sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.
I was still internally numb with a low dynamic range of emotions, just as I always was.</p>
<p>I was <em>seeing</em> my parts&mdash;as in, I was tracking my symptoms and assigning meaning to them&mdash;but I wasn&rsquo;t <em>connected</em> to them. I couldn&rsquo;t internally differentiate between parts, as I was solely relying on external differences between parts rather than a felt internal sense of difference. I was adamant that I was not able to internally differentiate between the parts, but in reality, I never even tried to look inside to see if I could.
I didn&rsquo;t want to feel the parts, who often come with difficult emotions, as I was used to being emotionally numb and enjoyed the internal stability.
But in order to heal, I needed to truly connect with my parts, rather than only observing them, and that, too, came with time.</p>
<h4 id="stage-4-connecting-with-my-parts-april-2023--now">Stage 4: Connecting with my parts (April 2023&ndash;now)</h4>
<p>Finally, I believe I am in a new stage of recovery&mdash;I am beginning to truly connect with my parts internally.
Since coming to terms with the fact that I need to actually allow myself to feel emotions in order to heal, my relationship with my parts has changed significantly. Rather than solely <em>observing</em> my parts like I was before, I&rsquo;m beginning to <em>feel</em> my parts and their emotions. With this, I&rsquo;m beginning to have a felt internal sense of which parts are active, rather than my previous method of telling apart my parts by solely relying on externally observable differences between the parts.
I&rsquo;m beginning to be able to observe things like internal bodily sensations, thought patterns, how I hold my body, general views about life, and a vague internal sense of &ldquo;who I am&rdquo; in order to tell which parts are active, which has greatly helped with the mapping of my system.
But connecting with my parts has also been tough&mdash;I&rsquo;m connecting with thoughts, feelings, and emotions I&rsquo;m not used to feeling, like <a href="/posts/anxiety/">anxiety</a> and <a href="/posts/anger">anger</a>. Because I&rsquo;ve been so disconnected from emotions my entire life, I&rsquo;m genuinely not used to feeling <em>anything</em>, let alone the negative emotions that I had previously dissociated away. Most of the time, I&rsquo;m not even sure what emotions I&rsquo;m feeling&mdash;I&rsquo;m having to map sensations in my body and a general awareness that the emotion is &ldquo;bad&rdquo; and infer what I should be feeling in the situation.
I&rsquo;m often overwhelmed my negative emotions that I&rsquo;m unfamiliar with and don&rsquo;t enjoy feeling.</p>
<p>So while I&rsquo;m in a difficult stage of recovery now, this is progress, so should be framed as good. I believe my amnesia is lessening as I&rsquo;m becoming more accepting of my parts, and I&rsquo;m also starting to connect with positive emotions. One younger part, in particular, has felt more comfortable to come out more, bringing excitement, joy, and happy memories with them. Many of my parts, however, hold a lot of fear, pain, sorrow, shame, and anger. I can feel that my dynamic range of emotions is increasing as I&rsquo;m connecting with more of my parts.</p>
<p>The more I look back on how far I come, the more insight about myself I seem to be gaining.
I don&rsquo;t know what my healing journey will look like in the future, but I&rsquo;m happy with the progress I&rsquo;ve made thus far.
Coming to terms with having DID has been
a difficult journey and I have a long, complex healing path ahead, but I&rsquo;m hopeful that the future will bring a me a more full, complete life.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>To me, when I experience depersonalization I do not feel real&mdash;I feel floaty in my body, my limbs feel heavy, and it feels like I&rsquo;m a puppet being moved around by another being. My mom reports that I told her about this for the first time when I was four years old. I&rsquo;ve experienced depersonalization off and on with varying severity for as long as I can remember.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I started &ldquo;failing&rdquo; at my adult responsibilities when my symptoms became worse. Instead of seeing my difficulties increasing as a result of my becoming more symptomatic, I saw it as the other way around&mdash;I believed I started faking symptoms as an excuse for my failings. I now see this as being unequivocally untrue&mdash;there is no way I could be faking these symptoms. Feelings of faking are apparently very common in early stages of treatment of DID.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Upon learning that I likely had DID, I began reading as much as I possibly could about the disorder. Understanding DID became a &ldquo;special interest&rdquo; of mine, as I wanted to understand what I was apparently going through. I absorbed the information from a very theoretical perspective and couldn&rsquo;t yet see how it applied to me. Some parts took this as a sign I was reading about DID in order to fake it. This is also untrue.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>They definitely were not as I&rsquo;ve had symptoms of DID since before I started therapy, but a common argument of DID deniers is that it&rsquo;s therapist induced, which, in my case, is not true.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Because different parts of me were created at different times of my life and are essentially a snapshot of who I was at that time, my intelligence, and ability to grasp onto complex ideas, fluctuates depending on which part of me is active. This has been extremely difficult as a PhD student who needs to hold onto complex concepts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/stagesofrecovery/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/stagesofrecovery/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 06:03:21 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>My stages of recovery</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>While I do experience what one could call &ldquo;dissociative episodes&rdquo; where a trauma-holding part takes full control of our body for a period of time, most of the time I experience momentary episodes of dissociation, where a part only takes control of our body for a few seconds at the maximum. However, these can still be difficult and disrupting to my daily life.</p>
<p>These types of episodes are quite common for me&mdash;they occur several times a day, often clustered together in time.
For that brief moment, my concentration is entirely focused internally, and I have no little to no awareness of the external world around me.
Simultaneously, my face and/or body may be moving in ways that I have no control over or awareness of. I may make noises, or mumble things, that are indicative of what&rsquo;s going on internally.
Internally, I am flooded by difficult emotions, such as fear or shame, along with an associated thought or memory. I perceive what I am experiencing internally as if it&rsquo;s happing in reality.
My heart rate may spike, and I may break into a sweat.
And then, all of a sudden, it&rsquo;s over, and I&rsquo;m back to doing what I was doing before, unphased by what just occurred.
These episodes can last from fractions of a second to several seconds, and occur several times a day.
After they&rsquo;re over, I can easily forget what went on during the episode or what triggered it. I describe one of these episodes in <em><a href="/posts/partscontrol/">The parts I don’t know about still have control</a></em>.
Within DID language, I could describe such an event by saying that a trauma-holding part that I do not have full memory sharing with was triggered and briefly took over.
These events seem to be triggered by either queues in my external environment or internal happenings that I, for the most part, seem to be unaware of.</p>
<p>From the outside, all of this happens so fast that if you blink you might miss it. Or, you may think it a tic, or a flinch. Personally, I try to hide them so they&rsquo;re as undetectable as possible to the outside observer&mdash;I don&rsquo;t want to inadvertently let others know what I&rsquo;m experiencing.</p>
<p>From a therapeutic perspective, I&rsquo;m supposed to try and connect with these parts, or take a moment to reflect inwards, when they come up. However, I&rsquo;m so used to just moving on with my life after they occur, as I&rsquo;ve been doing my whole life, that it has become habitual. I typically don&rsquo;t even realize that I&rsquo;ve had one of these dissociative intrusions because they occur so frequently for me that I perceive them as being normal, and I rapidly forget that they even occurred and move on with life. I have too many of these a day to stop and reflect internally after every episode. I still see these episodes as a nuisance, rather than parts that are surfacing into my consciousness because they need help, as I should if I want to encourage integration between my parts. Healing is difficult work.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/intrusions/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/intrusions/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 19:07:13 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative intrusions</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>One impactful but not immediately obvious symptom of DID for me is that I do not seem to have a continuous internal sense of time&mdash;my awareness of my life is shuffled.
Because of this, I may have a hard time differentiating what happened yesterday versus what happened last week or last month,
or struggle with remembering if, for example, I have leftovers in my fridge now or if that was from weeks ago.
This has made things like tracking changes in my environment difficult.
For example, I have had spring-time allergies for much of my life, but I was unable to realize that until recently&mdash;every day in the spring, I&rsquo;d wake up with allergies, but to me that was just accepted as fact. I didn&rsquo;t remember that I had allergies yesterday or every day last week, or that I didn&rsquo;t have allergies last fall, or that I&rsquo;ve had allergies every spring since childhood. All I am aware of is that I have allergies in that moment. Only since concretely tracking my symptoms this year was I able to determine that I do have springtime allergies, despite having them for years.
Life really feels like a blur to me.</p>
<p>I believe these experiences can be explained by my system structure, which is heavily impacted by the fact that I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented">polyfragmented</a>.
I seem to shift and switch between compartments a significant amount on a daily basis, and many of these compartments, or parts, only seem to come out every few days or weeks. Since what is at the forefront of my awareness depends on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, and many of these parts only come out once in a while, the end result seems to be that my understanding of my life is very shuffled.</p>
<p>Right now, I have a hard time differentiating between these parts, which makes it difficult to map how my understanding of my life is shuffled. I can vaguely tell when the last time I was in an active compartment was because I remember those memories most prominently, but I don&rsquo;t know <em>who</em> the part is. Many of them feel the same except for mild memory differences, seemingly because I have low identity alteration.
I have been told that differentiating between parts takes time, so I am hopeful that I&rsquo;ll soon be able to identify my parts.
I&rsquo;ve been operating like this for my entire life without awareness that most others do not have such a shuffled awareness.
I&rsquo;m glad that I finally understand that I have DID and that I operate in this way, as it provides me language to contextualize my experiences. With time, I hope to gain a more broad view of my life and form a more continuous relationship with time.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/shuffledawareness/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/shuffledawareness/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 21:19:32 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Shuffled sense of time</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Have you thought about how you conceptualize your internal experience, or the language you use to describe it? I personally hadn&rsquo;t given either much thought until I learned I had DID. Since then, I&rsquo;ve had a long journey of learning to understand how I operate, which has required me to think deeply about how to convey my experiences to others who likely do not operate in the same way that I do.</p>
<p>How one chooses to explain how they operate is complex and deeply personal.
As such, different people with DID may choose to convey their experiences in many different ways.
While some people are extremely creative in their portrayals of how they operate, I am someone who is more reluctant to portray myself in a way that others may deem as being too imaginative.
Because of this, I&rsquo;m still trying to find the language that feels most appropriate to describe my experiences.</p>
<p>The language one chooses is influenced by the underlying model that they use to understand what they are experiencing.
My experiences with DID seem to vary greatly, and range in severity depending on if I&rsquo;m experiencing a trauma trigger or not.
On the severe end, when parts take over my body, it can feel like I&rsquo;m being possessed and another being is controlling me.
On the other end, most often switching and shifting between parts feels so natural to me that I wonder if my experiences are even different than the norm.
To me, it seems that both these mundane and extraordinary experiences can be explained by the model of me switching, shifting, and being influenced by different compartments of memory and experience, which I call parts.</p>
<p>With time, I have realized that I see the world with multiple different perspectives&mdash;while I have the perspective of me as a whole person, I also see the perspectives of me as my individual parts.
The perspective of me as a whole person is something I was acquainted with before my DID discovery journey began, as it is what most people experience and is thus the societal norm.
On this blog, and when I discuss with others about my experiences, I typically portray the perspective of myself as a singular unified person as it&rsquo;s likely how the vast majority of people see themselves, but this language can be limiting to describe my experiences.
Writing from the perspective of me as a whole, these &ldquo;parts&rdquo; seem to be compartments of many different aspects of my life, such as memory and  identity, that I switch between to navigate through life.
For the most part, I only have the perspective of one part at any given time<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, and due to my degree of compartmentalization between parts, including amnesia and severely changing understandings of the world, depending on which compartment I am in I may have very different perspectives and things to say.
If I only portray myself as one singular unified person, I am misrepresenting aspects of my experience.
Thinking and writing as if I am a system of parts can enable me to explain experiences that simply don&rsquo;t make sense from the more restrictive whole-self perspective, like changing views about a topic, lapses in memory, possession-like experiences, losing time, and even quirks like handwriting and gait changes between parts.</p>
<p>Since starting therapy, I&rsquo;ve gradually learned to internally reference myself as a system of parts, yet I still translate that to a singular-self language when talking with others as I am hesitant to externally display my internal perspective with others.
I like portraying having a unified, singular-self view of life, even though it doesn&rsquo;t fully reflect how I&rsquo;ve learned to perceive myself.
This is probably due to the fact that it makes me uncomfortable realizing others know that the way I internally refer to myself is different than the norm.
When I was young, I was more in-touch with my individual parts&rsquo; perspectives&mdash;I would often refer to myself in third person in conversation with others<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I eventually learned that others did not experience themselves in this way, as I was occasionally ridiculed for it. I learned to hide using this language, even though it was the most accurate language for my experiences, since it was not well received by others.
Perhaps because of this, I feel the same way about using other unconventional language to describe my experiences&mdash;speaking from the perspective of individual parts, like I naturally did when I was younger, is tainted with shame due to my past experiences, and something I&rsquo;m working towards getting more comfortable with when appropriate in order to become more authentically me.</p>
<p>While I am used to thinking in third person<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, thinking about myself as multiple is new<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>, and I&rsquo;m still getting used to this conceptualization and the language used to describe it.
On this blog, I have decided to use whatever language is most appropriate for describing the particular experiences that I&rsquo;m trying to convey&mdash;I don&rsquo;t want to limit myself to a particular conceptualization or vocabulary set. So while I have mostly written from the perspective of a unified self thus far, this may change as I learn what language and conceptualization feels most comfortable for me.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Although, as I&rsquo;m creating connections between parts, this is thankfully changing!&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>This is because I have many parts who perceive my life in third person, and when those compartments are active, I naturally refer to myself in third person.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>This is useful for trauma survivors since it allows a detached view of self&mdash;one can perceive themselves as the observer of a situation rather than a participant in it.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>I didn&rsquo;t know this was an option, and it didn&rsquo;t come organically to me like the third-person perspective did. Now that I am more aware this is how I operate, I see that it aligns very well with my experiences.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/language/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/language/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 12:22:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Finding my language</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>DID is very much internal disorder. That is, unless I tell you that I have it, you wouldn&rsquo;t know<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. One of the ways DID affects my internal experience is that I have significant gaps in my memory, both of my past childhood, and of my present adulthood.
But amnesia is tricky&mdash;I don&rsquo;t know what I don&rsquo;t remember, so most of the time I don&rsquo;t realize I&rsquo;ve forgotten anything.</p>
<p>I believe I experience amnesia in a few ways.
The most innocuous type that I experience seems due to me having constricted awareness&mdash;each of my parts seems to act as a compartment of memory, so when I&rsquo;m in one compartment it may be difficult for me to index memories that occurred when I was in a different compartment of memory.
For example, if my partner talks about a hike we went on a few months ago when I&rsquo;m in a task-based compartment for cleaning, I may not remember the hike, but I may eventually get a very vague memory of it if they prompt me about it further. If I see a picture of us on the hike, it may help queue my memory of it more, but it still isn&rsquo;t a complete memory like it would be if I were in the compartment that was actually there on that hike.
I believe this is because hiking and cleaning occupy two entirely different compartments of my life; there&rsquo;s little in common between the two, and my constricted awareness makes it so that these memories aren&rsquo;t shared well between the two parts. This seems to be a version of state-dependent memory.</p>
<p>I also experience full amnesia between parts. That is, I will not have access to any of the memories of one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This typically seems to occur between compartments that hold trauma memories and ones that do not, but I also seem to experience this between non-trauma holding parts, and I&rsquo;m not yet sure why.</p>
<p>Within full amnesia, I seem to exhibit two types. The first is when I experience a discrete jump in my awareness when I switch between compartments where I have no idea what was happening just before the switch. This causes an obvious jump in my awareness, and may make it more noticeable that I have amnesia. I might find myself, all of a sudden, in a different room than I remember being in just a second ago, when in reality another part had moved me to that room outside of my awareness<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I experienced this when I was younger<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, but not as much as I&rsquo;ve gotten older. Now, I more so seem to have a sliding-window type memory&mdash;rather than a discrete jump in awareness, my memory of what happened gradually disappears over several minutes after a switch. This leads to a perceived smoother transition between parts, making my memory loss less obvious to me.</p>
<p>Regardless of the type of amnesia I have, I experience shuffling of memories and time jumps&mdash;I do not have a continuous, linear understanding of my life. For example, it may be hard for me to differentiate what occurred last week vs what occurred years ago, and sometimes things that occurred months ago feel more current to me than things that occurred even yesterday. As always, this seems to be justified by my understanding of how I operate&mdash;if I&rsquo;m in a compartment of memory that was last active a few months ago, those memories are more at the forefront of my awareness than memories formed in a different compartment yesterday.
This leads to a lot of confusing experiences, like looking out of my window and expecting it to be winter but seeing that it&rsquo;s actually summer, or all of a sudden noticing that the furniture in my apartment has moved from what I last remember, or looking at my plants and being amazed by how much they had grown because I remembered them being much smaller.
These sorts of experiences occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still early on in my DID discovery journey, so my understanding of my amnesia will likely change over time as I learn more about how I operate.
I hope this post serves as a snapshot in time of my awareness of how I operate a little over one year after starting therapy.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Unless you really know what to look for or you catch me in a dissociative episode, neither of which are likely.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Thankfully, I have never had a full dissociative fugue where I end up in an entirely different location than I was before. Most of my dissociative episodes occur at home when I&rsquo;m alone or in when I&rsquo;m in threapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>This, along with other symptoms, led to me receiving a dissociative disorder diagnosis as a pre-teen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/amnesia/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/amnesia/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 12:10:19 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative amnesia</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Imagine if, without your awareness, your deepest, most repressed thoughts and feelings were displayed for the world to see. With how my DID presents, this is something that occurs quite frequently for me. Because much of my most difficult emotions are separated from the core me, I am usually unaware of them until they surface and they&rsquo;re in the forefront of my awareness. Then, after they are over, I may forget that these dissociative episodes ever happened. This has led to me into many scary and sometimes dangerous situations, which typically leave me puzzled by what is happening in the world around me.</p>
<p>As an example, I like to go on evening walks for exercise. I typically walk one of a few routes in the densely populated city I live in. One day this past summer, I walked by a person who had some of the same characteristics as someone who caused me harm in the past. I walked by this individual without awareness that I was at all triggered. Then, in a split second, they started yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&rsquo;re scared of me, huh? What do you have to be scared about?&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>What?</em> It was so out of context for me; I had no idea why they were yelling at me. I wasn&rsquo;t scared of them&mdash;up until they started yelling at me, I hadn&rsquo;t even noticed them. I ignored them and calmly kept walking in the direction I was going. Then, they started moving towards me<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, continually yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why are you scared of me? You think I&rsquo;m threatening? There&rsquo;s nothing to be scared about!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I sped up walking and continued ignoring them. I felt very calm while this was happening, although I was confused by what going on. I eventually made it to the next block over and lost sight of them. I calmly walked home, and went out of my way to reassure myself that I had done nothing wrong, and that the person was at fault, not me. But <em>why</em> did this person think I was scared of them? Was I scared of them?</p>
<p>As it turns out, a part of me <em>was</em> scared of them. When I saw that person, that part became so scared, that they momentarily took control of our face and made a scared microexpression, directed at that person. However, I had no awareness that I was scared of them or that I had made any facial expression. This is because the parts of me who were on my evening walk were not connected with the part of me that was scared of the person, so from the perspective of the part of me that was going on a walk, I had no idea that anything abnormal was happening, while the scared part was simultaneously terrified.</p>
<p>Over the next few days, I intentionally went on my evening walk, purposefully walking past the location of the event to ensure I didn&rsquo;t associate anything negative with it. The parts of me walking felt perfectly fine, and I didn&rsquo;t realize anything was off.
Then, within a week, without realizing it, I stopped going on my evening walks. A month went by, and I still avoided walking, but it didn&rsquo;t even occur to me that I stopped.
I went from walking every day for months to only leaving my apartment when absolutely necessary. I didn&rsquo;t feel any fear associated with walking or leaving my apartment, but it was clearly there, dictating my behavior. It took over a month for me to realize anything was wrong, and once I pondered why I was no longer walking the reason became obvious&mdash;a part of me was still clearly scared of what had happened on that walk.
In order to get back to my walking routine, I gradually had to show that part that we were safe, and that that wasn&rsquo;t going to happen again, and even if it did, there were other parts who could take care of the situation like we had done last time. With this awareness in mind, over time, I managed to get back to going on my evening walks.</p>
<p>This is one example of how having DID affects my life and functioning. Before I became aware that I have DID, I was unaware of how much influence my parts had over my life. My behaviors are influenced by fear I cannot even grasp onto or feel. Other people may be more aware of my own internal state than even I am, since my body language may be contradictory to how I feel on the inside.
Getting to know my parts is helping me to become more aware of my internal state, and, in turn, will allow me to live a more complete life.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Thankfully, they used a walker, so I was in little danger.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/partscontrol/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/partscontrol/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:30:21 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>The parts I don’t know about still have control</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was initially hesitant to write about anger, as it&rsquo;s an emotion I am not used to feeling<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
How could I write about something I know nothing about?
But I now realize that the absence of anger in my life is significant in itself, and is indicative of how I operate.</p>
<p>Anger is an emotion that I am simultaneously very sensitive to, yet not at all familar with&mdash;I am incredibly sensitive to the external display of anger in others, yet not at all familiar with how it feels internally.
I believe this is because when I was small, I grew up in an environment where my primary caregiver frequently displayed anger.
This is because they had unprocessed trauma of their own, which came out as fits of rage.
These bouts of anger were extremely terrifying for me as a young child, and ended in emotional and sometimes physical harm done to me.
Because of the repeated association of anger with terror, pain, and instability, I believe I learned to internally separate anger as a &ldquo;bad&rdquo; emotion, and shoved it away as an emotion that I did not want to experience.
My relationship with anger was tainted by my early childhood experiences, making a powerful emotion that should be utilized as part of an emotionally healthy life inaccessible to me as an adult.</p>
<p>I once naively believed that not feeling anger was an asset of mine&mdash;that anger was a disruptive emotion, and it was safer for me not to feel it. While it is beneficial to those around me for me to not ever display anger, I now believe that anger is an important emotion that should be part of my emotional repertoire.
Anger enables people to enact change. By my not being able to experience anger, I&rsquo;m more likely to stay involved in situations and environments which are not good for me, making me to be more likely to be repeatedly victimized.
Due to my upbringing, I learned to value other peoples&rsquo; comfort over my own, and use dissociation to subconsciously withhold my sometimes justified anger.</p>
<p>I believe that because I have DID<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, my dynamic range of emotions is very shallow&mdash;most of the time, I feel mild contentment. I grew up in an environment where I didn&rsquo;t feel like I could take up any emotional space, as the emotional landscape in my family of origin was dominated by others&rsquo; strong emotional displays. I enjoy my internal stability&mdash;I do not want to feel strong emotions. I am scared of the loss of control I was so used to seeing in others while growing up.
However, this separation of anger and other emotions leads to a less full life, including amnesia, behavior that feels out of my control when I&rsquo;m triggered, along with stunted &ldquo;good&rdquo; emotions, like happiness and excitement. By using dissociation, I&rsquo;ve traded experiencing a full range of emotions for internal stability. This served me well in the past, but in the future I&rsquo;d like to live a more full, complete life&mdash;one that does not rely on maladaptive dissociative coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>While I now see anger as a valuable emotion, my learned patterns of removing it from my awareness continue, so still I have difficulty accessing it.
My understanding of anger comes from a theoretical view&mdash;I can intellectually understand it, but I do not believe I have felt genuine anger before. With time, I hope that will change.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>And maybe I was right to be hesitant, as I don&rsquo;t have much to say since I&rsquo;m early in my awareness journey, but I want to document my understanding of things at various stages of healing.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I believe I am this way due to how I responded to experiences in my childhood, which resulted in me forming maladaptive coping mechanisms which can be labeled DID.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/anger/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/anger/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 11:05:58 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anger</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from minutes to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
Additionally, <a href="/posts/shuffledawareness/">my internal awareness of my life is shuffled</a>, so I do not have a linear narrative history of my life or day-to-day activities.
This can affect my daily functioning significantly.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>I use <em>switch</em> to denote a hard, discrete change between parts, which usually occurs when I&rsquo;m triggered and can be disorienting. I use <em>shift</em> to denote a smooth change between parts, which occurs more often than switching for me and can internally feel like a gear shifting in my brain.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12, I stopped feeling anxiety. Prior to that, I was a child ravished by anxiety. Then, one day, it stopped<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. And I have never experienced anxiety in the same way since.</p>
<p>I now understand that anxiety is one of the experiences that I dissociated away&mdash;it&rsquo;s a state that I did not enjoy experiencing, so I learned how to compartmentalize it and push it out of my awareness.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean I do not <em>experience</em> anxiety; rather, it means that when I do, I am so detached from it that I do not experience all aspects of it.</p>
<p>My body trembles, lower lip quivers, and heart races, yet I don&rsquo;t know why I am experiencing these physical symptoms.
My mind races with irrational thought loops, yet I can&rsquo;t quite grasp onto them so they feel like meaningless noise to me.
I am disconnected and emotionally numb. Except for when I am not.</p>
<p>When I am able to connect with the feeling of anxiety, it is all-encompassing and feels everlasting. When something triggers anxiety to the forefront of my awareness, it is all I can concentrate on, and I will do whatever I need to do to alleviate the feeling. Then, all of a sudden, it goes away as quickly as it came, and after it&rsquo;s over I gradually forget that it ever happened.</p>
<p>Right now, as I write this, I do not know what anxiety feels like. Parts of me do, but I am not connected with those parts. For the most part, I feel like an emotionless machine, going through the motions of life. Despite the fact that I&rsquo;m unable to connect with anxiety, that doesn&rsquo;t mean it doesn&rsquo;t affect me. My behaviors are controlled by fear and anxiety that I cannot feel&mdash;I can only intellectually infer that I am being affected by anxiety by examining my behaviors. I avoid leaving my apartment, interacting with others, and doing things that may eventually lead to stressful situations. Yet I do not experience the associated emotions with these behaviors&mdash;I am numb.</p>
<p>When I was 12, I didn&rsquo;t become a less anxious person&mdash;I just became more detached from my anxiety. My crippling anxiety wasn&rsquo;t miraculously cured. Instead, it was like fixing a wound that needed stitches with a band-aid&mdash;an easy, temporary solution that left me worse-off in the long term.</p>
<p>In order to decrease my amnesia and regain control of my life, I need to connect back with my anxiety.
Although it allows me to avoid difficult feelings in the moment, my current method of dealing with anxiety&mdash;compartmentalizing it and shoving it from my awareness&mdash;leads to uncontrollable fear-based behavior, a lack of internal awareness, and amnesia. I need to connect with this destabilizing experience once again, this time working though it instead of shoving it from my awareness. Then, I can address its root causes and gain control of my life again.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>My mom reports me having a discrete personality change when this occurred.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/anxiety/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/anxiety/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 19:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anxiety</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have always been nerdy. From a young age, I immersed myself in academic work, as I enjoyed learning and the strict routine that school provided for me. I also had an intense need to perform well&mdash;my perfectionistic tendencies dominated my life as a child. While I often did perform well academically, there were times where I performed markedly poorly on assessments, so far outside the norm of what would have ordinarily be expected of me, despite preparing and knowing the material. For example, on one occasion in high school, I was so prepared for an exam that I helped tutor my friends about the material leading up to it, only for me to fail while they performed well. I wasn&rsquo;t ordinarily a bad test taker&mdash;I genuinely didn&rsquo;t understand the material when exam time came. To put it simply, there were times when I was smart, and times when I was&hellip; not. I  now understand this to be as a result of having DID.</p>
<p>Some of my parts were formed when I was a small child. When I am in these compartments, although I may be aware that I am an adult, I typically have the mental ability of around the age in which those parts developed. These compartments are essentially snapshots of my mindset at the time they were created, with varying levels of awareness of the present day. One major implication of this is that my ability to understand information varies depending on which compartment of awareness I am in. For example, I have a younger, very timid part that sometimes comes out that has the mental ability of a 7-year-old. When this part is active, I am unable to grasp onto the complex topics required of me for my PhD that I can normally do with relative ease when the right part of me is active. I am not aware of what I do not know, believing what I know in that moment is all that I do know. This part of me often comes out around others while I&rsquo;m supposed to be having intellectual discussions. The results are humiliating&mdash;I am unable to discuss even my own research, which the right parts of me are very familiar with. Many a time I have left a meeting feeling absolutely defeated and frustrated that I was unable to discuss my research properly. However, there were other times, when the correct parts were out, that I was very much able to hold an academic discussion about my work. My fluctuating knowledge of my work has detrimentally impacted my academic career thus far.</p>
<p>Before I knew I had DID, I never questioned my fluctuating levels of intelligence. However, I did come up with a justification for my poor performance&mdash;when I was in compartments that weren&rsquo;t aware of my more academic parts, I truly believed that I was dumber than all of my peers. I believed that any time I had performed well I had cheated, and I had faked my way to where I am today as a PhD student. There are times where I&rsquo;d look at my academic papers, ones that I had written, and not only did I not understand what the material was about, but I didn&rsquo;t fully remember writing them. I developed extreme imposter syndrome as a result of this&mdash;I truly didn&rsquo;t feel like I belonged in my institution, and I believed that I had genuine reasons as to why.</p>
<p>It has only been within the last several months that I&rsquo;ve been able to identify when I&rsquo;m in a compartment of awareness that is not necessarily able to understand the material required of me in order to complete my degree, and I now see that the difference in ability is pronounced. When one of these parts of me are active, I now stop working and try to understand why it is out. What is preventing me from accessing the compartments of me that do work? Sometimes the answer is obvious; other times, I&rsquo;m not so sure. Most frequently, however, I don&rsquo;t realize that a non-academic part has been out until after it has already gone, when I relook at a problem that I was previously agonizing over and it becomes obvious. I&rsquo;m still trying to understand these parts of myself, but just knowing that my having DID explains much of my academic distress really helps me understand why I am the way that I am.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 21:52:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Fluctuating intelligence</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Pretty early on in my DID discovery journey, I realized that my handwriting was different depending on which part of me was writing. This was very useful information, as I had taken well-catalogued academic notes for years prior to starting therapy, so I had a solid bank of data of which I could look back on and see which parts of me were active at different times of my life.</p>
<p>One thing I quickly noticed was that any time I traveled to a conference, my handwriting changed. And then when I got back, my handwriting changed back to whatever was normal at that time of my life<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
Internally, this also made sense&mdash;I tend to index my life by location rather than time. In fact, in all of my notebooks&rsquo; index sections, I had added a column for location, in addition to the standard page number and date. My mind likes segmenting my life based on location.</p>
<p>Why could this be the case? Why do I create parts when I travel? Looking back at my life story, it actually makes a lot of sense.
My first several years of life involved a lot of traveling. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad&rsquo;s job.
As a perk of being an expat, my dad&rsquo;s job paid for two vacations a year&mdash;one for rest and relaxation, and another to visit family.
Because of this, by my 5th birthday, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips.</p>
<p>This sounds like an incredibly fortunate childhood, and while it was, it was also very stressful for me.
As an autistic person, I regulate myself by following a strict routine. As an adult, changes in plans are very dysregulating, and usually leave me in a detached dissociated state with difficulty picking up the newly created plans.
I can only imagine how dysregulating it was for me as a small child to have my routine entirely upended every several months to travel to a new environment with an unknown routine.
I had no option&mdash;my family chose to travel, and since within my family structure the emotional landscape was already dominated by others, I had to be an easy child and submit to whatever they wanted. This led to me dissociating and creating parts to handle the traveling for me.</p>
<p>This past summer, I went to my first conference while aware that I create parts this way.
The night leading up to the event, I remember absolutely dreading the trip, wishing I could back out but knowing that I couldn&rsquo;t. Then, when the time came, I genuinely enjoyed the conference&mdash;the right part showed up for the job. I did seem to create a part for this trip, and this was the first part that I was self-aware I was creating. I had no control over it; instead, I observed its creation as I walked into the hotel lobby to check in. A new persona emerged, and was ready to take on whatever routine was required of me for my week-long conference that was just getting started. With that part as the dominant part, other parts came out periodically to do what was required of me, like networking, socializing, and presenting. But this newly created part was the star of the show, helping me create a solid routine I could stick to throughout the week to help keep me regulated. Then, on the last day, once again the dread came&mdash;this time, I, as the newly created part, didn&rsquo;t want to change my routine back again as I was only familiar with the one I had created. However, when I arrived in my apartment after a long journey back, a different part switched in and I was so glad to be home and back again in my standard routine.</p>
<p>We traveled to many beautiful locations in my early childhood, and I truly appreciate all the culturally enriching experiences I acquired, which I believe to this day have helped shaped my worldview. I do, however, wish that my parents were more aware of how stressful this was for me as a child. I did not understand the significance of the locations we would visit, and felt as though I was being dragged from place to place without understanding what was going on around me. In pictures of our family vacations, it&rsquo;s clear that I am dissociating&mdash;many of them show me with a blank expression with my eyes glazed over. I learned to regulate myself by dissociating, detaching from the world around me. And these repeated experiences of traveling = part creation have continued throughout my life, increasingly fragmenting my awareness when I take trips.</p>
<p>I believe this is a good example of how trauma, but not necessarily abuse, can lead to the formation of DID.
I would not consider traveling as much as we did abuse, but it was traumatic because it was too much for me to handle at the developmental stages it occurred in.
One could argue that this was neglect or negligence&mdash;that my parents weren&rsquo;t attuned to my emotional needs at the time.
However, it does not fit into the category of extreme abuse that is often attributed to the creation of DID.
While I do not believe this was the only trauma that caused me to form DID, and some of those traumas would be considered abuse,
traveling in the way that we did when I was small had a major impact on how I create parts, and is perhaps the most influential mechanism of part creation in my adult life.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>My handwriting isn&rsquo;t usually discretely clear, and is often a blend of many different parts&rsquo; handwritings. However, on several trips my handwriting made a clear enough change for me to notice this pattern.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/traveling/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/traveling/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 22:14:57 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Parts are created from trauma, not necessarily abuse</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&hellip; it&rsquo;s about childhood trauma.</p>
<p>Dissociative Identity Disorder (DID) can be thought of as a coping mechanism one may develop when they experience repeated trauma in early childhood. It is arguably one of the most misunderstood and controversial mental health conditions, perhaps because it&rsquo;s been repeatedly sensationalized in the media. Or, maybe because the name and clinical description of the disorder implies that it&rsquo;s about having multiple identities or personality states. However, these personality states are often incredibly subtle and are instead indicative of a post-traumatic reaction involving severe internal compartmentalization.</p>
<p>DID is a highly individualized disorder which forms based off of one&rsquo;s reaction to their life experiences. As such, I can only speak for myself and how I personally experience this disorder. While DID can be difficult to understand<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, it can be thought of as being fundamentally about two psychological phenomena&mdash;<em>detachment</em> and <em>compartmentalization</em>. Using myself as an example, when I was small, there were times where I experienced severe repeated abuse<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, but at other times had a happy childhood. While I was being abused, I mentally <em>detached</em> myself from the situation&mdash;I disconnected from my body and the external world, choosing instead to escape into my mind to distract myself from a situation I knew no other way to get out of. Perhaps more importantly, I also internally <em>compartmentalized</em> the experience and shoved it from my awareness, effectively allowing me to forget that it even occurred after it was over as I lived an otherwise happy childhood<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. Because this abuse occurred repeatedly, I continually used this strategy of switching to the compartment that held the abuse when I experienced triggers that the abuse was going to happen again. Then, when the abuse was over, I would switch back to the compartment that had a happy childhood and was blissfully unaware of the abuse that was taking place. This repeated pattern of switching between compartments further increased my compartmentalization of memory, awareness, experience, and identity. However, this was incredibly protective, as it allowed some parts of me to learn and grow as a child while other parts of me held the difficult memories and feelings of being abused out of awareness. All of this was done on a subconscious level.</p>
<p>This strategy of compartmentalization can only develop when trauma occurs in early childhood, while the brain still is rapidly developing and has the capacity to use such defenses. And because I learned to use these defenses when I was very young and my brain wired based on my experiences of the world around me, I learned that this was a very effective strategy for minimizing psychological discomfort.
Because of this, over time my threshold for what constituted compartment creation lowered as I relied more and more on this coping mechanism.
Because I was able to compartmentalize my experience, I subconsciously learned to separate the good aspects of my life&mdash;like emotions of happiness, contentment, and good memories&mdash;from the bad aspects of my life&mdash;like anger, grief, and memories of trauma.
Additionally, I learned to use compartmentalization in areas of my life that weren&rsquo;t inherently traumatic.
While this started as a very effective coping mechanism in response to childhood trauma, it has rapidly turned maladaptive as I have continually created compartments to respond to adult stressors.</p>
<p>Rather than fluidly being able to access all aspects of my personality like a more integrated individual, I have to switch between discrete personality states as I move throughout life.
While many of these compartments share memory (i.e., when I am in one compartment of memory, I will likely remember at least most of what happened when I was in a different compartment of memory), when I switch between compartments it can feel like my working memory, or what I was actively thinking about, gets wiped&mdash;like a blip in my conscious awareness.
I also have compartments of memory with varying degrees of amnesia between them, so I genuinely may not remember what happened when I was in one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This lack of memory sharing typically happens between compartments who hold traumatic memories and emotions and ones who do not.
Additionally, depending on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, I will have different motivations and awareness of my current life. So while I may be an enthusiastic PhD student in several compartments, I also have compartments where I have no idea what my research is, or even that I am a student working towards my degree.
Sometimes, instead of fully taking over, these compartments intrude on my awareness, so I may have unexplained feelings of, say, fear that I have no idea where is coming from or what is triggering it.</p>
<p>For a long time, I was adamant that I did not experience identity alteration. I&rsquo;m now realizing that while I do have many compartments that all seem to identify as &ldquo;me&rdquo;, some compartments are so far removed from present time and context that, when I am in them, I do not perceive myself as being the adult me I actually am.
The identity alteration I do experience is incredibly subtle, and is much more an internal phenomena than an external one&mdash;an external observer will most likely not be able to tell apart my parts<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. These parts are just different versions of me, so even with the identity alteration I do have, I see these parts as all being <em>me</em>.</p>
<p>So DID is really not <em>about</em> identity, even if that&rsquo;s the most sensationalized part of the disorder. I personally see the identity alteration and switching/influence of multiple personality states as merely a side effect of a brilliant psychological defense mechanism in response to early childhood trauma. But while it&rsquo;s not about identity explicitly, the fact that one has several distinct identities<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> as opposed to a single unified one can be a major component to the disorder that may severely affect, both positively and negatively, how one experiences life with DID.</p>
<!--
While many of these compartments share memory (i.e., when I am in one compartment of memory, I will likely remember at least most of what happened when I was in a different compartment of memory), when I switch between compartments it can feel like a RAM drop---my working memory, or what I was actively thinking about, gets wiped. 
-->
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>There are many different theories about how DID forms and works, but this is one of the ways that I like to think about it.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>This example is an oversimplification, and this severe abuse occurred outside the home. However, I did experience less severe abuse and other traumas within my family which shaped my development of this disorder as well.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>This was not fully the case, but I wanted to emphasize the differential between the good and bad parts of my childhood to provide a more concrete example of how parts in DID may split.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>For the most part, I still can&rsquo;t even tell apart my parts. This is something that I&rsquo;m sure I will get better at with time, as I get more acquainted with how I operate.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>These distinct indentities are not whole on their own. Rather, they represent different parts of my whole personality. Rather than having one unified identity, I have several fragmented identities/personality states that I switch between.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/notaboutidentity/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/notaboutidentity/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 21:43:08 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>It’s not about identity</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
