







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="https://example.com/tags/did/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>DID</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>https://example.com/tags/did/</link>
        
        
            <title>DID</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have always been been nerdy. From a young age, I immersed myself in academic work, as I enjoyed learning and the strict routine that school provided for me. I also had an intense need to perform well&mdash;my perfectionistic tendencies dominated my life as a child. While I often did perform well academically, there were times where I performed markedly poorly on assessments, so far outside the norm of what would have ordinarily be expected of me, despite preparing and knowing the material. For example, one one occasion in high school, I was so prepared for an exam that I helped tutor my friends about the material leading up to it, only for me to fail while they performed well. I wasn&rsquo;t ordinarily a bad test taker&mdash;I genuinely didn&rsquo;t understand the material when exam time came. To put it simply, there were times when I was smart, and times when I was&hellip; not. I  now understand this to be as a result of having DID.</p>
<p>Some of my parts were formed when I was a small child. When I am in these compartments, although I may be aware that I am an adult, I typically have the mental ability of around the age in which those parts developed. These compartments are essentially snapshots of my mindset at the time, with varying levels of awareness of the present day. One major implication of this is that my ability to understand information varies depending on which compartment of awareness I am in. For example, I have a younger, very timid part that sometimes comes out that has the math ability of a middle schooler. When this part is active, I am unable to grasp onto the complex topics required of me for my PhD that I can normally do with relative ease when the right part of me is active. I am not aware of what I do not know, believing what I know in that moment is all that I do know. This part of me often comes out around others while I&rsquo;m supposed to be having intellectual discussions. The results are humiliating&mdash;I am unable to discuss even my own research, which the right parts of me are very familiar with. Many a time I have left a meeting feeling absolutely defeated and frustrated that I was unable to discuss my research properly. However, there were other times, when the correct parts were out, that I was very much able to hold an academic discussion about my work. Becoming aware that I have DID has offered a much-needed explanation for why my brain works in this way.</p>
<p>Before I knew I had DID, I never questioned my fluctuating levels of intelligence. However, I did come up with a justification for my poor performance&mdash;when I was in compartments that weren&rsquo;t aware of my more academic parts, I truly believed that I was dumber than all of my peers. That, somehow, any time I had performed well I had cheated, and I faked my way to where I am today as a PhD student. There are times where I&rsquo;d look at my academic papers, ones that I had written, and not only did I not understand what the material was about, but I genuinely didn&rsquo;t even remember writing them. I developed extreme imposter syndrome as a result of this&mdash;I truly didn&rsquo;t feel like I belonged in my institution, and I believed that I had genuine reasons as to why.</p>
<p>It has only been within the last several months that I&rsquo;ve been able to identify when I&rsquo;m in a compartment of awareness that is not necessarily able to understand the material required of me in order to complete my degree, and I now see that the difference in ability is pronounced. When this part of me is active, I now stop working and try to understand why it is out. What is preventing me from accessing the compartments of me that do work? Sometimes the answer is obvious; other times, I&rsquo;m not so sure. I&rsquo;m still trying to understand these parts of myself, but just knowing that my having DID explains much of my academic distress really helps me understand why I am the way that I am.</p>
<!--


In a PhD program[^1], other than one's thesis defense that is the capstone of their degree, the qualifying exam is the most important test of one's degree. The qualifying exam typically occurs a year or two into the degree, and is meant to assess if one is qualified to continue in the PhD program. What exactly a qualifying exam consists of differs from school to school, and department to department. In my program, my qualifying exam was a "chalk talk"---you choose three topics of concentration, and three experts on those fields will ask you questions which you answer on the chalk board. They assess your responses and determine if you're qualified to continue in the degree.

[^1]: Ones I am familiar with in the USA.


In high school. I wasn't aware I had DID. But looking back with the awareness I now have, there are many instances of fluctuating intelligence that can be perfectly explained by having DID. My freshman year, I had a turbulent home environment


For example, in high school, there were times where I'd teach my friends material that would be on the exam, and then I'd do poorly on the exam while they would do well.

My qualifying exam


I do not have access to my full set of knowledge and skills, and 
When this part of me is active

I can feel the intelligence differential between myself and others around me. Over time, when I was in that compartment 



There are some things in life that just made so much more sense after I realized I had DID. Probably the most frustrating one was my fluctuating intelligence. This explained how I could teach my friends the material for a math exam and subsequently fail it while my friends did well. 

I have a complicated relationship with academics.
As a PhD student, 

One of the most frustrating symptoms that falls under the category of _symptoms I've had my entire life but didn't realize_ is flucutating intelligence.

My intelligence, 

This is, perhaps, one of the most frustrating parts of having DID.
-->
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 21:52:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Fluctuating intelligence</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Pretty early on in my DID discovery journey, I realized that my handwriting was different depending on which part of me was writing. This was very useful information, as I had taken well-catalogued academic notes for years prior to starting therapy, so I had a solid bank of data of which I could look back on and see which parts of me were active at different times of my life.</p>
<p>One thing I quickly noticed was that any time I traveled to a conference, my handwriting changed. And then when I got back, my handwriting changed back to whatever was normal at that time of my life <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
Internally, this also made sense&mdash;I tend to index my life by location rather than time. In fact, in all of my notebooks' index sections, I had added a column for location, in addition to the standard page number and date. My mind likes segmenting my life based on location.</p>
<p>Why could this be the case? Why do I create parts when I travel? Looking back at my life story, it actually makes a lot of sense.
My first several years of life involved a lot of traveling. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad&rsquo;s job.
As a perk of being an expat, my dad&rsquo;s job paid for two vacations a year&mdash;one for rest and relaxation, and another to visit family.
Because of this, by my 5th birthday, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips.</p>
<p>This sounds like an incredibly fortunate childhood, and while it was, it was also very stressful for me.
As an autistic person, I regulate myself by following a strict routine. As an adult, changes in plans are very dysregulating, and usually leave me in a detached dissociated state with difficulty picking up the newly created plans.
I can only imagine how dysregulating it was for me as a small child to have my routine entirely upended every several months to travel to a new environment with an unknown routine.
I had no option&mdash;my family chose to travel, and since within my family structure the emotional landscape was already dominated by others, I had to be an easy child and submit to whatever they wanted. This led to me dissociating and creating parts to handle the traveling for me.</p>
<p>This past summer, I went to my first conference while aware that I create parts this way.
The night leading up to the event, I remember absolutely dreading the trip, wishing I could back out but knowing that I couldn&rsquo;t. Then, when the time came, I genuinely enjoyed the conference&mdash;the right part showed up for the job. I did, in fact, create a part for this trip, and this was the first part that I was self-aware I was creating. I had no control over it; instead, I observed its creation as I walked into the hotel lobby to check in. A new persona emerged, and was ready to take on whatever routine was required of me for my week-long conference that was just getting started. With that part as the dominant part, other parts came out periodically to do what was required of me, like networking, socializing, and presenting. But this newly created part was the star of the show, helping me create a solid routine I could stick to throughout the week to help keep me regulated. Then, on the last day, once again the dread came&mdash;this time, I, as the newly created part, didn&rsquo;t want to change my routine back again as I was only familiar with the one I had created. However, when I arrived in my apartment after a long journey back, a different part switched in and I was so glad to be home and back again in my standard routine.</p>
<p>We traveled to many beautiful locations in my early childhood, and I truly appreciate all the culturally enriching experiences I acquired, which I believe to this day have helped shaped my worldview. I do, however, wish that my parents were more aware of how stressful this was for me as a child. I did not understand the significance of the locations we would visit, and felt as though I was being dragged from place to place without understanding what was going on around me. In pictures of our family vacations, it&rsquo;s clear that I am dissociating&mdash;many of them show me with a blank expression with my eyes glazed over. I learned to regulate myself by dissociating, detaching from the world around me. And these repeated experiences of traveling = part creation have continued throughout my life, increasingly fragmenting my awareness when I take trips.</p>
<p>I believe this is a good example of how trauma, but not necessarily abuse, can lead to the formation of DID.
I would not consider traveling as much as we did abuse, but it was traumatic because it was too much for me to handle at the developmental stages it occurred in.
One could argue that this was neglect or negligence&mdash;that my parents weren&rsquo;t attuned to my emotional needs at the time.
However, it does not fit into the category of extreme abuse that is often attributed to the creation of DID.
While I do not believe this was the only trauma that caused me to form DID, and some of those traumas would be considered abuse,
traveling in the way that we did when I was small had a major impact on how I create parts, and is perhaps the most influential mechanism of part creation in my adult life.</p>
<!--

One part of me is very grateful that I had traveled so much in my childhood because that meant that I had already seen everything I would ever to in life and would never have to travel again. That part of me sees vacations a check box to complete, rather than an experience to enjoy. This line of thinking was influenced by the stress I 


 I, as the newly created part, did not want to change my routine back again.

I was a very well traveled child, and while I used to think of this as an amazing opportunity 
I even in my adult life, and is perhaps the most influential 


One could argue that this was neglect, not abuse.


With that being said, in my adult life at least, I do enjoy vacations---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.

One part of me was very happy that I had traveled so much as a child because that would mean that I wouldn't 
My understanding of vacations was that they were a check box to complete, rather than an experience to enjoy.
With that being said, I did enjoy them---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.
With that being said, I did enjoy them---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.

I did not understand the significance of the locations I was being 


My system is very chaotic---I seem to split parts in complex 

As I understand it, one can create parts to respond to stressors in their environment.

To me, traveling is stressful. And incredibly unpredictable. When I was young, I didn't know what was going on in the environment around me as my parents moved me from landmark to landmark that I didn't understand the significance of. 

By the time I was 5 years old, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips. I did not understand the significance of the locations I was being 

One of the first mechanisms of creating parts 

I have kept detailed work journals for 
Something I've always done 

At first, it didn't make sense to me 
Over time, it became obvious why.


As a polyfragmented system, I seem to split parts
Early into my discovery journey, something puzzled me. I learned pretty quicky 

My first several years of life were very chaotic. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad's job. 
For my whole life up to that point, while my handwriting was floridly changing, I never had questioned it or honestly really noticed it. Now, I am very thankful that I have a solid visual indicator for which parts of me were active at different times of my life.
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My handwriting isn&rsquo;t usually discretely clear, and is often a blend of many different parts' handwritings. However, on several trips my handwriting made a clear enough change for me to notice this pattern.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/traveling/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/traveling/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 22:14:57 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Parts are created from trauma, not necessarily abuse</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>DID can be difficult to understand.
One of my favorite analogies for DID is from Janina Fisher&rsquo;s <em>Healing the Fragmented Selves of Trauma Survivors</em>, pgs 149-150:</p>





<div class="paige-quote">
    <blockquote class="blockquote">Your parts developed a relay race system for surviving your childhood: one would grab the baton and run the next leg of the &lsquo;race,&rsquo; while others were shielded from what was happening, and then another would grab the baton and run the next leg. It was automatic: the best &lsquo;runner&rsquo; for a particular situation would be instinctivly activated to run that leg, then the best runner for the next leg of the race would be triggered, and so on. No one was distracted by how the others were running because each was separate and had little to no awareness of the others.</blockquote>

    
</div>

<p>I relate a lot to this analogy. Before I became more self-aware, I was only able to hold the perspective of the part I currently was, and didn&rsquo;t realize that my understanding and perception of the world changed depending on which part of me was active. When I would analyze my past memories, I would only be aware of the feelings and actions of the part I currently was, for the most part not taking into account my experiences that didn&rsquo;t align with the currently active part. I had multiple separate threads of experience that I would switch between without awareness.</p>
<p>Now that I am more aware of how I operate, my goal is to be able to take a step back from the compartment that I currently am in to be able to have a broader picture of my life.
In the year and two months I&rsquo;ve been in therapy, my awareness has increased dramatically, but I still have a long way to go.
One of the hardest parts has been accepting that I am a team rather than the solo runner I always thought I was.</p>
<!--

I would switch from part to part without awareness, and, although I didn't know it at the time, I was living life moment-to-moment, without much awareness of what had happened in the past or what I wanted to do in the future. 

As I understand it now, 
when one part of me is active, memories formed when different parts were active feel different---they distinctly feel like _not me_. How much they feel like _not me_ seems to vary depending on how connected two parts are. For example, a part of me that works may not remember traumatic memory at all, and may have a vague awareness of my memories formed while I was on vacation, and would be much more connected with memories that different work parts formed. In fact, if one were to ask me about my vacation from a month ago while a work part is active, I will likely only have a general awareness of what occurred during that trip and would have to switch to a part more familiar with the vacation in order to converse more.

This is an incredibly subtle feeling, 
Moment-to-moment, I generally have a continuous sense of "I"; that is, I don't generally have discrete jumps in 



if I remember what I did when a different part of me was active, the memory feels different from memories that belong to the current version of me. It feels distinctly like memories of other parts do not belong to _me_; they're someone else's. This is an incredibly subtile distinction, and one of the main ways I use to tell apart me parts. Moment-to-moment, I always feel like _me_; I don't really experience discrete jumps in 

---I don't perceive a differential. The main way I'm able to tell that I'm a different part is looking at the past rather than 

Whatever version of me is currently active feels like me, and the only version of me. It took me a long time to realize this, because it's an incredibly subtle distinction. 


One of the ways I like to think about how I experience life is to think that I'm made up of a team of parts working together to live life. 
Now, I understand that who I am right now isn't who I always am---things like my views, interests, mannerisms, and, perhaps most obviously, handwriting change depending on which part of me in the relay race of life is holding the baton. 
It's been difficult trying to conceptualize my experience with DID. The analogy of "multiple people living in the same body" that many people use doesn't seem to make sense for me. In fact, because of this, I actively denied that having DID for several months after starting therapy with the justification that I do not relate to others' experiences I learn about online. 
With this analogy, people with DID seem to feel as though they are the current part that is out, and that parts they could be at other times are "other" to them. 
--!>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/relayrace/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/relayrace/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 14:56:01 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Life is a relay race</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&hellip; it&rsquo;s about childhood trauma.</p>
<p>Dissociative Identity Disorder (DID) can be thought of as a coping mechanism one may develop when they experience repeated trauma in early childhood. It is arguably one of the most misunderstood and controversial mental health conditions, perhaps because it&rsquo;s been repeatedly sensationalized in the media. Or, maybe because the name and clinical description of the disorder implies that it&rsquo;s about having multiple identities or personality states. However, these personality states are often incredibly subtle and are instead indicative of a post-traumatic reaction involving severe compartmentalization of experience.</p>
<p>DID is a highly individualized disorder which forms based off of one&rsquo;s reaction to their life experiences. As such, I can only speak for myself and how I personally experience this disorder. While DID can be difficult to understand, it&rsquo;s fundamentally about two psychological phenomena&mdash;<em>detachment</em> and <em>compartmentalization</em>. Using myself as an example, when I was small, there were times where I experienced extreme repeated abuse<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, but at other times had a happy childhood. While I was being abused, I mentally <em>detached</em> myself from the situation&mdash;I disconnected from my body and the external world, choosing instead to escape into my mind to distract myself from a situation I knew no other way to get out of. Perhaps more importantly, I also internally <em>compartmentalized</em> the experience and shoved it from my awareness, effectively allowing me to forget that it even occurred after it was over as I lived an otherwise happy childhood<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. Because this abuse occurred repeatedly, I continually used this strategy of switching to the compartment that held the abuse when I experienced triggers that the abuse was going to happen again. Then, when the abuse was over, I would switch back to the compartment that had a happy childhood and was blissfully unaware of the abuse that was taking place. This repeated pattern of switching between compartments further increased my compartmentalization of memory, awareness, experience, and identity. However, this was incredibly protective, as it allowed some parts of me to learn and grow as a child while other parts of me held the difficult memories and feelings of being abused out of awareness. All of this was done on a subconscious level.</p>
<p>This strategy of compartmentalization can only develop when trauma occurs in early childhood, while the brain still is rapidly developing and has the capacity to use such defenses. And because I learned to use these defenses when I was very young and my brain wired based on my experiences of the world around me, I learned that this was a very effective strategy for minimizing psychological discomfort.
Because of this, over time my threshold for what constituted compartment creation lowered as I relied more and more on this coping mechanism.
Because I was able to compartmentalize my experience, I subconsciously learned to separate the good aspects of my life&mdash;like emotions of happiness, contentment, and good memories&mdash;from the bad aspects of my life&mdash;like anger, grief, and memories of trauma.
Additionally, I learned to use compartmentalization in areas of my life that weren&rsquo;t inherently traumatic.
While this started as a very effective coping mechanism in response to childhood trauma, it has rapidly turned maladaptive as I have continually created compartments to respond to adult stressors.</p>
<p>Rather than fluidly being able to access all aspects of my personality like a more integrated individual, I have to switch between discrete personality states as I move throughout life.
While many of these compartments share memory (i.e., when I am in one compartment of memory, I will likely remember at least most of what happened when I was in a different compartment of memory), when I switch between compartments it can feel like a RAM drop&mdash;my working memory, or what I was actively thinking about, gets wiped.
I also have compartments of memory with varying degrees of amnesia between them, so I genuinely may not remember what happened when I was in one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This lack of memory sharing typically happens between compartments who hold traumatic memories and emotions and ones who do not.
Additionally, depending on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, I will have different motivations and awareness of my current life. So while I may be an enthusiastic PhD student in several compartments, I also have compartments where I have no idea what my research is, or even that I am a student working towards my degree.
Sometimes, instead of fully taking over, these compartments intrude on my awareness, so I may have unexplained feelings of, say, fear that I have no idea where is coming from or what is triggering it.</p>
<p>For a long time, I was adament that I did not experience identity alteration. I&rsquo;m now realizing that while I do have many compartments that all seem to identify as &ldquo;me&rdquo;, some compartments are so far removed from present time and context that, when I am in them, I do not perceive myself as being the adult me I actually am.
I now see my initial attempts to deny my identity alteration as a way of denying that I do, in fact, have DID, and once again used my coping mechanisms to shove that knowledge out of my awareness. This is because coming to terms with having DID means coming to terms with having childhood trauma, and while that was once too hard for me to accept, I am beginning to accept it now.</p>
<p>So DID is really not <em>about</em> identity, even if that&rsquo;s the most sensationalized part of the disorder. I personally see the identity alteration and switching/influence of multiple personality states as merely a side effect of a brilliant psychological defense mechanism in response to early childhood trauma. But while it&rsquo;s not about identity explicitly, the fact that one has several distinct identities as opposed to a single unified one can be a major component to the disorder that may severely affect, both positively and negatively, how one experiences life with DID.</p>
<!---
Denial is a major part of this disorder, and one year and two months into therapy, I'm still coming to terms with this.

So DID is really not about identity---it's about childhood trauma and the extreme compartmentalization that may form because of it. 
This only scratches the surface of what I experience as a results of having DID.
There are many occasions that I have been shocked to hear how I behaved when more vulnerable parts of my personality have been out,.

For example, I have parts that clean for me, because at one time I likely decided that although I really didn't want to clean, I needed to, so I created a part to do so for me. 

While this was an incredibly effective coping strategy for me when I was actively experiencing trauma, it 

This has been an incredibly effective strategy in emotional regulation for me. In fact, my dynamic range of emotions is so low, that my main emotional state exists solely of mild contentment, which I seemingly experience most of the time.



On this blog, I hope to document my experiences as a system of memory compartments, which I like to call parts, working together in the relay race of life in an attempt to live it to the fullest.



Because this compartment creation strategy has been my primary coping mechanism, as time went on, I created more and more compartments as a response to small life stressors, which has been unsustainable. 
 an unsustainable 

Detaching from the world around me allowed me to regulate how much of my surroundings I experienced, which has been particularly helpful as an autistic person with sound and light sensitivities.
Over time, rather than the standard development of a fluid personality with a singular sense of "me", I developed several discretely separated personality states that I need to switch between to experience life.

Because of the internal compartmentalization, the parts of me who lived a normal childhood did not remember the events that occurred to the parts of me who experienced trauma. This allowed my compartments that experienced life to grow and thrive as a child, while my other compartments held the hurt and pain of the abuse. 
This led to 

While many individuals with this disorder may only experience a split in traumatized vs untraumatized parts of their personality, 

As I became older and was no longer actively encountering abuse, because it was so deeply engrained in how I operate, I still used this part creation strategy to aid in every day life.

Detaching from the world around me was a way I learned to regulate myself. For example, because I am autistic, I have sound and light sensitivities. 

, which has been particularly helpful as an autistic person with sound and light sensitivities.

This became a highly effective strategy---I learned to dedicate parts of me to handling abuse, and other parts of me to learning and growing as a child. 
---I was oblivious to the fact that this abuse caused me to form a severe mental disorder that would impact me for the rest of my life.

Because this abuse occurred at a time in which my brain was rapidly developing, this strategy of detachment and compartmentalization became engrained as an effective 
I learned how

which was damaging to my develping brain. 





extreme repeated abuse outside of the home (along with less severe abuse and traumas within my family). Because this abuse was so severe, 


To put it simply, how I understand 



And while that may be true about

Truthfully, as much as I want to generalize, I understand how personal

Yet, perhaps because of the name, or the media representation, 

When I started therapy almost 14 months ago, I genuinely believed that dissociative identity disorder (DID) was a fake disorder that people feigned to get out of trouble or for attention. My understanding of DID was influenced by the social and traditional media representation of the disorder, which generally portrayed people experiencing drastic personality shifts, or seemingly role-playing characters. I never thought this disorder could apply to me---for the most part, I was soft spoken, reclusive, and tried my hardest to blend into society. However, as I know now, I am a typical, but not stereotypical, example of how DID presents.

DID is caused by repetitive trauma in early childhood, while the brain is rapidly developing. To put it simply, one way a child can cope with trauma 

if a young child experiences trauma, one way they can cope with 

At an early age, if one 




So it's not about identity. Having multiple identities is a side effect of the extreme internal compartmentalization caused by trauma. But because it's the most sensational part of the disorder, that's what it's known as.
but somehow it's been made 

Alternative title: How I conceptualize my experience 1 year and 2 months into therapy.--->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This example is an oversimplification, and this extreme abuse occurred outside the home. However, I did experience less severe abuse and other traumas within my family which shaped my development of this disorder as well.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This was not fully the case, but I wanted to emphasize the differential between the good and bad parts of my childhood to provide a more concrete example of how parts in DID may split.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/notaboutidentity/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/notaboutidentity/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 21:43:08 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>It’s not about identity</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
