







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="https://example.com/tags/did/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>DID</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>https://example.com/tags/did/</link>
        
        
            <title>DID</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes, it feels like I have so many parts out at any given time. There are times where it feels like there are so many things that I want to be doing in that moment. I&rsquo;m being pulled in so many different directions that I do not know what to do&mdash;I have decision paralysis. Then, if I do manage to pick something to do, it&rsquo;s inevitable that some other part does not want to do what I have chosen to do, so</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/internaldivision/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/internaldivision/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 17:07:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Internal division</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was initially hesitant to write about anger, as it&rsquo;s an emotion I am not acquainted with<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
How could I write about something I know nothing about?
But I now realize that the absence of anger in my life is significant in itself, and is indicative of how my underlying dissociative defense system operates.
Anger is an emotion that I am simultaneously very familiar with, yet not at all acquainted with&mdash;I am incredibly sensitive to the external display of anger in others, yet not at all familiar with how it feels internally.
I believe this is because when I was small, I grew up in an environment where my primary caregiver frequently displayed anger.
This is because they had unprocessed trauma of their own, which came out as fits of rage.
These bouts of anger were extremely terrifying for me as a young child, and ended in emotional and sometimes physical harm done to me.
Because of the repeated association of anger with terror, pain, and instability, I believe I learned to internally separate anger as a &ldquo;bad&rdquo; emotion, and shoved it away as an emotion that I did not want to experience.
My relationship with anger was tainted by my early childhood experiences, making a powerful emotion that should be utilized as part of an emotionally healthy life inaccessible to me as an adult.</p>
<p>I once naively believed that not feeling anger was an asset of mine&mdash;that anger was a disruptive emotion, and it was safer for me not to feel it. While it is beneficial to those around me for me to not ever display anger, I now believe that anger is an important emotion that should be part of my emotional repertoire.
Anger enables people to enact change. It can be the driving force required to get one out of bad situations. By my not being able to experience anger, I&rsquo;m more likely to stay involved in situations and environments which are not good for me. I value other peoples&rsquo; comfort over my own, and use dissociation to subconsciously withhold my sometimes justified anger.</p>
<p>Because I have DID, my dynamic range of emotions is very shallow&mdash;most of the time, I feel mild contentment. I grew up in an environment where I didn&rsquo;t feel like I could take up any emotional space, as the emotional landscape in my family of origin was dominated by others&rsquo; strong emotional displays. I enjoy my internal stability&mdash;I do not want to feel strong emotions. I am scared of the loss of control I was so used to seeing in others while growing up.
However, this separation of anger and other emotions leads to a less full life, including amnesia, behavior that feels out of control when I&rsquo;m triggered, along with stunted &ldquo;good&rdquo; emotions, like happiness and excitement. By using dissociation, I&rsquo;ve traded experiencing a full range of emotions for internal stability. This served me in the past, but in the future I&rsquo;d like to live a more full, complete life&mdash;one that does not rely on dissociative coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>While I now see anger as a valuable emotion, my learned patterns of removing it from my awareness continue, so still I have difficulty accessing it.
My understanding of anger comes from a theoretical view&mdash;I can intellectually understand it, but I do not believe I have ever felt anger before. With time, I hope that will change.</p>
<!--
Anger is an emotion I learned to dissociate away from a very young age. 



Because of this, I learned to associate anger with terror and instability, and internally decided that anger was an emotion I did not want to experience.






I do not believe I have ever experienced anger before.

 Like anxiety, anger is an emotion I have dissociated away. However, unlike anxiety, which I do experience, I do not believe I have ever experienced true anger before.


Anger is an emotion I am not acquainted with. 

My mom tells me she's only seen me angry twice in my life---both involved her doing things to my cat without getting permission. In these cases, I'm sure I was acting to protect my cat, but I do not fully remember either incident. It would be too destabilizing for me to realize that 

I have been trained to be very sensitive to the signs of anger in others---


I am very familiar with anger as expressed by others. 



My understanding of anger comes from a theoretical view---I can intellectually understand it, but I do not believe I have ever felt anger before. 

I have a rudimentary understanding of anger. 


I understand why anger is important
It can be the driving force one needs to fight against harm or injustice done to them.

change one's situation

Anger is a powerful emotion. It can help one to enact change in their life, 
The absense of anger in my life 

Rather than feeling angry about something

I do not feel anger, because it was modeled to me as an unstable 

My mother could not control her anger. It was an emotion she turned to frequently, and her emotions 

I am very unfamiliar with anger

I do not believe I have ever felt anger before. I believe this is common 
It may be hypocritical for me to write a post on an emotion that I am so unfamiliar with. 


My dynamic range of emotions is very shallow---most of the time, I feel mild contentment. 
I grew up in an environment where I didn't feel like I could take up any emotional space, as the emotional landscape in my family of origin was dominated by others' strong emotional displays. 

I enjoy my internal stability---I do not want to feel strong emotions. I am scared of the loss of control I was so used to seeing while growing up. 

those around me dominated the emotional landscape. 
I do not have much experience with strong emotions, 


I have never experienced strong emotions
-->
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>And maybe I was right to be hesitant, as I don&rsquo;t have much to say since I&rsquo;m early in my awarness journey, but I want to document my understanding of things as I learn.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/anger/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/anger/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 11:05:58 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anger</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from days to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<!--

I'm only at the beginning of my journey to discovering how I operate, and I'm learning more about my system every day. 

At the very begining of my journey to discovering how I operate, I never could have imagined that I had this chaotic of a system. 

I am not a singular part, with other parts being "other" to me, which is how some people seem to conceptualize having DID.
Rather, I am all of my parts, and all of my parts are me. These parts seem to represent pieces of the whole me. My life is fragmented into many different compartments that I switch between. Depending on which compartment I am in, I will have a different internal experience. For the most part, externally, there is not much differentiation between my parts. You will likely not be able to tell when one part is out vs a different part is out.



Many of my parts share memory and are cooperative with one another.
Right now, as I write this, 
up until recently, I was just as dysfunctional, but I didn't know I was because I didn't know I had DID and daily amnesia. Now that I am much more aware of what is going on in my life, I have full confidence that I will become more functional again soon. I have been very functional living with this disorder in the recent past, so I have full faith I'll get there again, this time with much more awareness of how I operate.






I seem to use parts differently than the most-shared representations of DID portray. Because of this, it took me an incredibly long time to see in myself that I had DID. 






I'd like to note that while I use the word "dysfunctional" to describe myself, I'm actually very high-functioning in most areas of my life. 
I use the word dysfunctional to describe the fact that this disorder is impacting my day-to-day functioning, making it hard to do the things I want to do. This is because my internal awareness is so fragmented that I do not have continuity of memory, and I have clusters of parts with different interests trying to live life in different ways, causing internal division. However, in many aspects of life, I am living functionally.



I'm using my dissociative coping mecahanisms to protect me from what could be objectively considered a difficult time, just as I have in the past. For the most part, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview. Dissociation is an amazing coping mechanism. 


For what it's worth, the labels I use to describe how I function make it seem like my life is a lot worse than it actually is. Despite the internal chaos and amnesia, I, for the most part, enjoy how I operate. I realize 

Thus, when I am triggered in the present day, I have to switch between a series of parts in rapid succession before switching back to an untraumatized part.
I am also able to take care of myself well, but 


This is the most descriptive word I've found used in the literature and online communities that represents how I experience having DID.
Most of my parts share memory between them, so switching/shifting can almost be undetectable to me. However, I do experience amnesia between some parts that come out nearly daily.
I seem to split parts easily and in a complex manner. 

With these splitting patterns, this means I have a lot of parts.

When I was young, I likely would not qualify as polyframented---my rate of part creation has increased as I aged 

I seem to have parts created to do jobs for me. For example, I have a few different parts dedicated to cleaning, a part for brushing my showering, and even a sequence of parts dedicated to getting me from putting my VR headset on to in my VR game as quickly/without my awareness as possible. My definition of what constitutes part creation is so low that a game loading screen made me create parts.

[^1]: _[The phenomenology and treatment of extremely complex multiple personality disorder](https://scholarsbank.uoregon.edu/xmlui/bitstream/handle/1794/1396/Diss_1_4_8_OCR_rev.pdf)_. Richard Kluft, 1998. 

This is not a word I've seen in the academic literature, although Richard Kluft seems to describe similar phenomena in one of his papers[^1], so it's not concretely defined. To me, the word polyfragmented means a person who has many parts and/or splits them in a complex fashion. I believe I fall under the category of both. 
Because my understanding of DID was that of a more traditional presentation, I initially did not believe I had this disorder, despite having clear cases of amnesia. However, over time, I found that my presentation was simply different to the traditional presentation. It seems as though I 


rather than having a relatively few number of well-defined parts, 


Reading about experiences of people who self-identify as polyfragmented helped me to see that this label makes the most sense to me.

Because I switch so much, my relationship with time 

Rather than a few clearly defined parts, it seems as though my entire personality is split into multiple parts

My internal experience is extremely compartmentalized. When my symptoms are bad, I'm often living day-to-day, or even moment-to-moment, unaware of what I had previously been doing or what my next plans are. I feel like I'm in a state of survival---I just need to get through this moment onto the next day. This was a mindset I used as a child when I had to get through my current situation, but trusted there were good times ahead. I'd do whatever I could to pass time, to distract myself of the present moment so once the good times came, I could 

When times are good, 

However, in my adult life, this is a 
When I began graduate school, everything was stressful, and I was nearly constantly in this living moment-to-moment mindset, unable to take a step back and examine that 


I relied upon as a child to get me through times that were extremely stressful---I perceived the present moment as being bad, but I had faith that in the future. I used this when I had to get through a situation that took a long time

---the present moment is bad, but maybe the future will be better. I just need to get through this present moment to getas long as I could make it through the present moment, maybe the next. 

It took me several months of therapy with a dissociative disorders specialist in order for me to even consider that I had DID, despite having a pediatric dissociative disorder diagnosis. Like many others would in my generation, as soon as I realized I was being assessed for DID, I immediately went to sites like Reddit and YouTube to see how other people with this disorder conceptualize their experiences. Needless to say, I did not relate to others' experiences that I found online. Most people I had encountered seemed to have a relatively small number clearly defined parts with clear roles. I genuinely did not believe that I had DID, despite the fact that I was frequently dissociating in therapy sessions without realizing I was doing so. 

Why do I have so many parts? The threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals---things that would be considered traumatic to me may not have affected another child as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, along with the fact that I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there's a high correlation of those who are polyfragmented and have autism.

What does this mean? It is my understanding that typically, individuals with DID split a few to several well defined parts---they don't have too many different compartments they switch between.


used colloquially to mean a system with many parts, typically with complex splitting patterns. 

I do not seem to experience this. Instead, 

I've also learned that I have many different types of parts and mechanisms for part creation.
I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch[^6] between parts on a very regular basis.
Additionally, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to create many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event. 
I also do not only split parts due to trauma---I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged[^7]. 
-->
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12, I stopped feeling anxiety. Prior to that, I was a child ravished by anxiety. Then, one day, it stopped <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. And I have never experienced anxiety in the same way since.</p>
<p>I now understand that anxiety is one of the experiences that I dissociated away&mdash;it&rsquo;s a state that I did not enjoy experiencing, so I learned how to compartmentalize it and push it out of my awareness.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean I do not <em>experience</em> anxiety; rather, it means that when I do, I am so detached from it that I do not experience all aspects of it.</p>
<p>My body trembles, lower lip quivers, and heart races, yet I don&rsquo;t know why I am experiencing these physical symptoms.
My mind races with irrational thought loops, yet I can&rsquo;t quite grasp onto them so they feel like meaningless noise to me.
I am disconnected and emotionally numb. Except for when I am not.</p>
<p>When I am able to connect with the feeling of anxiety, it is all-encompassing and feels everlasting. When something triggers anxiety to the forefront of my awareness, it is all I can concentrate on, and I will do whatever I need to do to alleviate the feeling. Then, all of a sudden, it goes away as quickly as it came, and after it&rsquo;s over I gradually forget that it ever happened.</p>
<p>Right now, as I write this, I do not know what anxiety feels like. Parts of me do, but I am not connected with those parts. For the most part, I feel like an emotionless machine, going through the motions of life. Despite the fact that I&rsquo;m unable to connect with anxiety, that doesn&rsquo;t mean it doesn&rsquo;t affect me. My behaviors are controlled by fear and anxiety that I cannot feel&mdash;I can only intellectually infer that I am being affected by anxiety by examining my behaviors. I avoid leaving my apartment, interacting with others, and doing things that may eventually lead to stressful situations. Yet I do not experience the associated emotions with these behaviors&mdash;I am numb.</p>
<p>When I was 12, I didn&rsquo;t become a less anxious person&mdash;I just became more detached from my anxiety. My crippling anxiety wasn&rsquo;t miraculously cured. Instead, it was like fixing a wound that needed stitches with a band-aid&mdash;an easy, temporary solution that left me worse-off in the long term.</p>
<p>In order to decrease my amnesia and regain control of my life, I need to connect back with my anxiety.
Although it allows me to avoid difficult feelings in the moment, my current method of dealing with anxiety&mdash;compartmentalizing it and shoving it from my awareness&mdash;leads to uncontrollable fear-based behavior, a lack of internal awareness, and amnesia. I need to connect with this destabilizing experience once again, this time working though it instead of shoving it from my awareness. Then, I can address its root causes and gain control of my life again.</p>
<!--

I have a very curated internal experience---emotionally, I feel 

The irrational thought loops 
At least not in a normal way anymore. 

DID shapes the way I experience emotions.

Different aspects of my life are compartmentalized 

When I was a child, I was filled with worry. 
-->
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>My mom reports me having a discrete personality change when this occurred.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/anxiety/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/anxiety/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 19:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anxiety</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Pretty early on in my DID discovery journey, I realized that my handwriting was different depending on which part of me was writing. This was very useful information, as I had taken well-catalogued academic notes for years prior to starting therapy, so I had a solid bank of data of which I could look back on and see which parts of me were active at different times of my life.</p>
<p>One thing I quickly noticed was that any time I traveled to a conference, my handwriting changed. And then when I got back, my handwriting changed back to whatever was normal at that time of my life <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
Internally, this also made sense&mdash;I tend to index my life by location rather than time. In fact, in all of my notebooks&rsquo; index sections, I had added a column for location, in addition to the standard page number and date. My mind likes segmenting my life based on location.</p>
<p>Why could this be the case? Why do I create parts when I travel? Looking back at my life story, it actually makes a lot of sense.
My first several years of life involved a lot of traveling. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad&rsquo;s job.
As a perk of being an expat, my dad&rsquo;s job paid for two vacations a year&mdash;one for rest and relaxation, and another to visit family.
Because of this, by my 5th birthday, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips.</p>
<p>This sounds like an incredibly fortunate childhood, and while it was, it was also very stressful for me.
As an autistic person, I regulate myself by following a strict routine. As an adult, changes in plans are very dysregulating, and usually leave me in a detached dissociated state with difficulty picking up the newly created plans.
I can only imagine how dysregulating it was for me as a small child to have my routine entirely upended every several months to travel to a new environment with an unknown routine.
I had no option&mdash;my family chose to travel, and since within my family structure the emotional landscape was already dominated by others, I had to be an easy child and submit to whatever they wanted. This led to me dissociating and creating parts to handle the traveling for me.</p>
<p>This past summer, I went to my first conference while aware that I create parts this way.
The night leading up to the event, I remember absolutely dreading the trip, wishing I could back out but knowing that I couldn&rsquo;t. Then, when the time came, I genuinely enjoyed the conference&mdash;the right part showed up for the job. I did, in fact, create a part for this trip, and this was the first part that I was self-aware I was creating. I had no control over it; instead, I observed its creation as I walked into the hotel lobby to check in. A new persona emerged, and was ready to take on whatever routine was required of me for my week-long conference that was just getting started. With that part as the dominant part, other parts came out periodically to do what was required of me, like networking, socializing, and presenting. But this newly created part was the star of the show, helping me create a solid routine I could stick to throughout the week to help keep me regulated. Then, on the last day, once again the dread came&mdash;this time, I, as the newly created part, didn&rsquo;t want to change my routine back again as I was only familiar with the one I had created. However, when I arrived in my apartment after a long journey back, a different part switched in and I was so glad to be home and back again in my standard routine.</p>
<p>We traveled to many beautiful locations in my early childhood, and I truly appreciate all the culturally enriching experiences I acquired, which I believe to this day have helped shaped my worldview. I do, however, wish that my parents were more aware of how stressful this was for me as a child. I did not understand the significance of the locations we would visit, and felt as though I was being dragged from place to place without understanding what was going on around me. In pictures of our family vacations, it&rsquo;s clear that I am dissociating&mdash;many of them show me with a blank expression with my eyes glazed over. I learned to regulate myself by dissociating, detaching from the world around me. And these repeated experiences of traveling = part creation have continued throughout my life, increasingly fragmenting my awareness when I take trips.</p>
<p>I believe this is a good example of how trauma, but not necessarily abuse, can lead to the formation of DID.
I would not consider traveling as much as we did abuse, but it was traumatic because it was too much for me to handle at the developmental stages it occurred in.
One could argue that this was neglect or negligence&mdash;that my parents weren&rsquo;t attuned to my emotional needs at the time.
However, it does not fit into the category of extreme abuse that is often attributed to the creation of DID.
While I do not believe this was the only trauma that caused me to form DID, and some of those traumas would be considered abuse,
traveling in the way that we did when I was small had a major impact on how I create parts, and is perhaps the most influential mechanism of part creation in my adult life.</p>
<!--

One part of me is very grateful that I had traveled so much in my childhood because that meant that I had already seen everything I would ever to in life and would never have to travel again. That part of me sees vacations a check box to complete, rather than an experience to enjoy. This line of thinking was influenced by the stress I 


 I, as the newly created part, did not want to change my routine back again.

I was a very well traveled child, and while I used to think of this as an amazing opportunity 
I even in my adult life, and is perhaps the most influential 


One could argue that this was neglect, not abuse.


With that being said, in my adult life at least, I do enjoy vacations---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.

One part of me was very happy that I had traveled so much as a child because that would mean that I wouldn't 
My understanding of vacations was that they were a check box to complete, rather than an experience to enjoy.
With that being said, I did enjoy them---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.
With that being said, I did enjoy them---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.

I did not understand the significance of the locations I was being 


My system is very chaotic---I seem to split parts in complex 

As I understand it, one can create parts to respond to stressors in their environment.

To me, traveling is stressful. And incredibly unpredictable. When I was young, I didn't know what was going on in the environment around me as my parents moved me from landmark to landmark that I didn't understand the significance of. 

By the time I was 5 years old, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips. I did not understand the significance of the locations I was being 

One of the first mechanisms of creating parts 

I have kept detailed work journals for 
Something I've always done 

At first, it didn't make sense to me 
Over time, it became obvious why.


As a polyfragmented system, I seem to split parts
Early into my discovery journey, something puzzled me. I learned pretty quicky 

My first several years of life were very chaotic. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad's job. 
For my whole life up to that point, while my handwriting was floridly changing, I never had questioned it or honestly really noticed it. Now, I am very thankful that I have a solid visual indicator for which parts of me were active at different times of my life.
-->
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>My handwriting isn&rsquo;t usually discretely clear, and is often a blend of many different parts&rsquo; handwritings. However, on several trips my handwriting made a clear enough change for me to notice this pattern.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/traveling/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/traveling/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 22:14:57 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Parts are created from trauma, not necessarily abuse</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&hellip; it&rsquo;s about childhood trauma.</p>
<p>Dissociative Identity Disorder (DID) can be thought of as a coping mechanism one may develop when they experience repeated trauma in early childhood. It is arguably one of the most misunderstood and controversial mental health conditions, perhaps because it&rsquo;s been repeatedly sensationalized in the media. Or, maybe because the name and clinical description of the disorder implies that it&rsquo;s about having multiple identities or personality states. However, these personality states are often incredibly subtle and are instead indicative of a post-traumatic reaction involving severe compartmentalization of experience.</p>
<p>DID is a highly individualized disorder which forms based off of one&rsquo;s reaction to their life experiences. As such, I can only speak for myself and how I personally experience this disorder. While DID can be difficult to understand, it can be thought of as being fundamentally about two psychological phenomena&mdash;<em>detachment</em> and <em>compartmentalization</em>. Using myself as an example, when I was small, there were times where I experienced extreme repeated abuse<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, but at other times had a happy childhood. While I was being abused, I mentally <em>detached</em> myself from the situation&mdash;I disconnected from my body and the external world, choosing instead to escape into my mind to distract myself from a situation I knew no other way to get out of. Perhaps more importantly, I also internally <em>compartmentalized</em> the experience and shoved it from my awareness, effectively allowing me to forget that it even occurred after it was over as I lived an otherwise happy childhood<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. Because this abuse occurred repeatedly, I continually used this strategy of switching to the compartment that held the abuse when I experienced triggers that the abuse was going to happen again. Then, when the abuse was over, I would switch back to the compartment that had a happy childhood and was blissfully unaware of the abuse that was taking place. This repeated pattern of switching between compartments further increased my compartmentalization of memory, awareness, experience, and identity. However, this was incredibly protective, as it allowed some parts of me to learn and grow as a child while other parts of me held the difficult memories and feelings of being abused out of awareness. All of this was done on a subconscious level.</p>
<p>This strategy of compartmentalization can only develop when trauma occurs in early childhood, while the brain still is rapidly developing and has the capacity to use such defenses. And because I learned to use these defenses when I was very young and my brain wired based on my experiences of the world around me, I learned that this was a very effective strategy for minimizing psychological discomfort.
Because of this, over time my threshold for what constituted compartment creation lowered as I relied more and more on this coping mechanism.
Because I was able to compartmentalize my experience, I subconsciously learned to separate the good aspects of my life&mdash;like emotions of happiness, contentment, and good memories&mdash;from the bad aspects of my life&mdash;like anger, grief, and memories of trauma.
Additionally, I learned to use compartmentalization in areas of my life that weren&rsquo;t inherently traumatic.
While this started as a very effective coping mechanism in response to childhood trauma, it has rapidly turned maladaptive as I have continually created compartments to respond to adult stressors.</p>
<p>Rather than fluidly being able to access all aspects of my personality like a more integrated individual, I have to switch between discrete personality states as I move throughout life.
While many of these compartments share memory (i.e., when I am in one compartment of memory, I will likely remember at least most of what happened when I was in a different compartment of memory), when I switch between compartments it can feel like a RAM drop&mdash;my working memory, or what I was actively thinking about, gets wiped.
I also have compartments of memory with varying degrees of amnesia between them, so I genuinely may not remember what happened when I was in one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This lack of memory sharing typically happens between compartments who hold traumatic memories and emotions and ones who do not.
Additionally, depending on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, I will have different motivations and awareness of my current life. So while I may be an enthusiastic PhD student in several compartments, I also have compartments where I have no idea what my research is, or even that I am a student working towards my degree.
Sometimes, instead of fully taking over, these compartments intrude on my awareness, so I may have unexplained feelings of, say, fear that I have no idea where is coming from or what is triggering it.</p>
<p>For a long time, I was adamant that I did not experience identity alteration. I&rsquo;m now realizing that while I do have many compartments that all seem to identify as &ldquo;me&rdquo;, some compartments are so far removed from present time and context that, when I am in them, I do not perceive myself as being the adult me I actually am.
The identity alteration I do experience is incredibly subtle, and is much more an internal phenomena than an external one&mdash;an external observer will most likely not be able to tell apart my parts <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. These parts are just different versions of me, so even with the identity alteration I do have, I see these parts as all being <em>me</em>.</p>
<p>So DID is really not <em>about</em> identity, even if that&rsquo;s the most sensationalized part of the disorder. I personally see the identity alteration and switching/influence of multiple personality states as merely a side effect of a brilliant psychological defense mechanism in response to early childhood trauma. But while it&rsquo;s not about identity explicitly, the fact that one has several distinct identities<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> as opposed to a single unified one can be a major component to the disorder that may severely affect, both positively and negatively, how one experiences life with DID.</p>
<!---

For a long time, I was adament that I did not experience identity alteration. I'm now realizing that while I do have many compartments that all seem to identify as "me", some compartments are so far removed from present time and context that, when I am in them, I do not perceive myself as being the adult me I actually am. 
I now see my initial attempts to deny my identity alteration as a way of denying that I do, in fact, have DID, and once again used my coping mechanisms to shove that knowledge out of my awareness. This is because coming to terms with having DID means coming to terms with having childhood trauma, and while that was once too hard for me to accept, I am beginning to accept it now.



Denial is a major part of this disorder, and one year and two months into therapy, I'm still coming to terms with the fact that I utilized this effective coping strategy in response to childhood trauma, which is known as Dissociative Identity Disorder. d
Denial is a major part of this disorder, and one year and two months into therapy, I'm still coming to terms with this.

So DID is really not about identity---it's about childhood trauma and the extreme compartmentalization that may form because of it. 
This only scratches the surface of what I experience as a results of having DID.
There are many occasions that I have been shocked to hear how I behaved when more vulnerable parts of my personality have been out,.

For example, I have parts that clean for me, because at one time I likely decided that although I really didn't want to clean, I needed to, so I created a part to do so for me. 

While this was an incredibly effective coping strategy for me when I was actively experiencing trauma, it 

This has been an incredibly effective strategy in emotional regulation for me. In fact, my dynamic range of emotions is so low, that my main emotional state exists solely of mild contentment, which I seemingly experience most of the time.



On this blog, I hope to document my experiences as a system of memory compartments, which I like to call parts, working together in the relay race of life in an attempt to live it to the fullest.



Because this compartment creation strategy has been my primary coping mechanism, as time went on, I created more and more compartments as a response to small life stressors, which has been unsustainable. 
 an unsustainable 

Detaching from the world around me allowed me to regulate how much of my surroundings I experienced, which has been particularly helpful as an autistic person with sound and light sensitivities.
Over time, rather than the standard development of a fluid personality with a singular sense of "me", I developed several discretely separated personality states that I need to switch between to experience life.

Because of the internal compartmentalization, the parts of me who lived a normal childhood did not remember the events that occurred to the parts of me who experienced trauma. This allowed my compartments that experienced life to grow and thrive as a child, while my other compartments held the hurt and pain of the abuse. 
This led to 

While many individuals with this disorder may only experience a split in traumatized vs untraumatized parts of their personality, 

As I became older and was no longer actively encountering abuse, because it was so deeply engrained in how I operate, I still used this part creation strategy to aid in every day life.

Detaching from the world around me was a way I learned to regulate myself. For example, because I am autistic, I have sound and light sensitivities. 

, which has been particularly helpful as an autistic person with sound and light sensitivities.

This became a highly effective strategy---I learned to dedicate parts of me to handling abuse, and other parts of me to learning and growing as a child. 
---I was oblivious to the fact that this abuse caused me to form a severe mental disorder that would impact me for the rest of my life.

Because this abuse occurred at a time in which my brain was rapidly developing, this strategy of detachment and compartmentalization became engrained as an effective 
I learned how

which was damaging to my develping brain. 





extreme repeated abuse outside of the home (along with less severe abuse and traumas within my family). Because this abuse was so severe, 


To put it simply, how I understand 



And while that may be true about

Truthfully, as much as I want to generalize, I understand how personal

Yet, perhaps because of the name, or the media representation, 

When I started therapy almost 14 months ago, I genuinely believed that dissociative identity disorder (DID) was a fake disorder that people feigned to get out of trouble or for attention. My understanding of DID was influenced by the social and traditional media representation of the disorder, which generally portrayed people experiencing drastic personality shifts, or seemingly role-playing characters. I never thought this disorder could apply to me---for the most part, I was soft spoken, reclusive, and tried my hardest to blend into society. However, as I know now, I am a typical, but not stereotypical, example of how DID presents.

DID is caused by repetitive trauma in early childhood, while the brain is rapidly developing. To put it simply, one way a child can cope with trauma 

if a young child experiences trauma, one way they can cope with 

At an early age, if one 




So it's not about identity. Having multiple identities is a side effect of the extreme internal compartmentalization caused by trauma. But because it's the most sensational part of the disorder, that's what it's known as.
but somehow it's been made 

Alternative title: How I conceptualize my experience 1 year and 2 months into therapy.--->
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This example is an oversimplification, and this extreme abuse occurred outside the home. However, I did experience less severe abuse and other traumas within my family which shaped my development of this disorder as well.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>This was not fully the case, but I wanted to emphasize the differential between the good and bad parts of my childhood to provide a more concrete example of how parts in DID may split.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>For the most part, I still can&rsquo;t even tell apart my parts. This is something that I&rsquo;m sure I will get better at with time, as I get more acquainted with how I operate.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>These distinct indentities are not whole on their own. Rather, they represent different parts of my whole personality. Rather than having one unified identity, I have several fragmented identities/personality states that I switch between.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/notaboutidentity/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/notaboutidentity/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 21:43:08 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>It’s not about identity</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
