







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/symptoms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>symptoms</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/symptoms/</link>
        
        
            <title>symptoms</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Life is moving very rapidly right now. I wrote the previous post (<a href="/posts/wakingup/">Waking up to the present</a>) six weeks ago, shortly after I had split a new cluster of parts. Then, three weeks ago, I split a whole new cluster of parts. Both six weeks ago and three weeks ago I had very distinct changes in my behavioral patterns and how I operate. I have two very distinct &ldquo;jumps&rdquo; in my continuity of memory both three and six weeks ago.</p>
<p>I have been creating new clusters of parts due to stressors for my whole life, but up until recently I wasn&rsquo;t aware I was doing it&mdash;it was &ldquo;normal&rdquo; to me, so I didn&rsquo;t know anything was off. Until I learned that I had DID, I didn&rsquo;t have a framework from which to understand my experiences. Since starting for therapy for DID, I have become much more aware of my internal states and, with lots of practice and observation, I am now generally able to tell when I have switched between or created new compartments of memory.</p>
<p>While cultivating my internal qualitative awareness of my system is important, I am a very quantitative-minded person&mdash;I want hard, solid evidence that what I am going through is actually happening. And now I finally do.</p>
<p>A few years ago, I started tracking information about my life and logging it in a database. I started small, tracking simple things like medications taken, my weight, and when I showered. Over time, I started tracking more and more complex things as I became more aware of patterns in my life. For example, there are times when I have a distinctly different gait than normal, and other times where I chew my tongue habitually in a distinct way, along with many other factors. I also automatically log certain things such as the activity on my computer and phone, along with steps taken and when I fall asleep/wake up every day. I generally log the activities of what I do in a day, in broad categories such as work, eating, and walking, over time.
I now have tens of thousands of data points about myself, spread over a few years, from which I can draw conclusions off of.
I also journal every day, in both a personal journal and a work journal, so I also have a lot of free-form data along with handwriting from that.</p>
<p>Now, looking at my data, across multiple factors, I see distinct changes in how I operate both three and six weeks ago. Internally, I already knew this, but having physical data to back up my internal awareness definitely validates my understanding of my system.
In addition to providing solid quantitative evidence of my system, logging data about myself requires me to be observant and mindful of my life&rsquo;s activities, which in turn helps me to gain internal awareness of how I operate.</p>
<p>In a way, I am collecting data about myself to solve an inverse problem. Given the data that I acquire about myself, can I determine the underlying model about how I operate? With time, as I acquire more data, its becoming increasingly more clear. I am figuring out how I operate, slowly but surely, using the best way I know how&mdash;using data.</p>
<p>I feel I am in a different stage of recovery now than I was even a few months ago. I have become much more aware about who I am and how I operate. I am an amalgamation of hundreds of parts who are working together, with varying levels of cooperation, to live life. As life goes on and the data I collect about myself along with my awareness grows, my confidence about the way that I operate increases. I can now definitively say that I am a polyfragmented system operating with hundreds of parts, many of which are fragments. I split parts regularly, and switch between my parts a handful to hundreds of times a day. I have different scales of parts&mdash;while I have parts that I switch between every day, I also have longer-scale parts that I shift between on the order of days to weeks. My longer-scale parts seem to be roughly cyclical, and seem to repeat on the order of a few months, seemingly dependent on life stressors. On the other hand, my daily parts seem to come out much more consistently due to more concrete triggers, such as task-based reasons or reminders of trauma.</p>
<p>Since capturing long-scale variations in data is much simpler than capturing short-scale variations in data<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, I am currently more focused on capturing my long-scale parts. With time and increased awareness, I hope to be able to acquire more data about my parts that switch more frequently.
But with the data I have now, I have made a few observations.
Depending on which &ldquo;part of the cycle&rdquo; I am in (in other words, which long-scale part is out), the way I operate in life is distinctly different. This includes things like my bedtime and morning routine, how well I cook and the foods I eat, my hobbies and interests, how aware of/productive I am at work, how often I shower, how long/frequently I walk, my handwriting, my gait, how often I socialize/interact with others, the video games I play and how often I play them, how interested I am in/how frequently I use marijuana, how much I am aware of/interested in my pets and plants, my awareness of my past and my future, how clean my apartment is, how aware I am of my appearance, how connected I am with my body/how sensitive I am to pain, my outlook on life, my entire internal experience, and many other things that are too personal to list here.
While for a long time I was suspicious that this was my system structure and the way that I operate, I now have sufficient enough data for me to be convinced my model is correct.</p>
<!--

 life feels distinctly different. 

Between three and six weeks ago, I was very focused and aware of my PhD work---I advanced in my research greatly and spent almost every day during that time period, including weekends, fully working. I also feel asleep and woke up at regular times. I journaled proficiently, walked every day, and was very aware of my present life and what I needed to do to graduate. I ate meals at regular times every day. I had a consistent morning and evening routine. My life was moving forward smoothly.

Between three weeks ago and the present, things have been very different and more chaotic. I am working on research, at most, three hours a day, and often times much less than that. Instead, I have become incredibly aware of my future life and have spent excessive amounts of time planning potential career options. My sleep and eating schedules have become incredibly inconsistent, and I journal much less than I used to. Additionally, what I journal about and the handwritings of my journal entries are distinctly different. I am practically unaware of my present life and what I need to do to graduate. 

So now I have data to back up what I already knew---I am still splitting parts. 







I also, very sadly, forgot about several plants that I was growing in my closet under grow lights. One day, I opened my closet, only to find a bunch of dead plants that I had no idea were in there. 

If this had happened six months ago, I wouldn't have been aware of my part splitting. But now, I collect enough data about myself that it's clear that I am still creating parts.

For example, I have a part with a weird gait that causes severe pain in my right leg while walking. For about a week every few months, I am unable to walk long distances because the pain is so severe. Then, my gait gradually changes again and I can walk normally. I log other strange habits like seem to be associated with parts like habitually chewing on my tongue in a specific way, or 


I'm afraid I'm going to split a new cluster of parts soon. 

I log many different metrics about me, most of which are too personal to even say what online. When analyzing this data, it's clear I have a distinct change in lots of aspects of my life  starting around July 5th, exactly 3 weeks ago. Looking further back, 

and I have split a new cluster of parts

I am in the thick of things right now.
Tracking metrics about myself.


It has been six weeks since I wrote the last post on this blog. In [Waking up to the present](/posts/wakingup/), 

I am now aquiring enough data about myself now that I can distinctly see 

For the past few years, I have been tracking various amounts of data about myself

I am now intensely aware of the future.

I forgot I had this blog. Reading posts now.
I reopened my blog for the first time in several weeks and started reading some of my old posts.


-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Capturing short-scale variations (the parts that switch multiple times a day) requires sampling, or capturing data points, at a much smaller time interval than capturing large-scale variations (parts that shift every few days to weeks).&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/datadriven/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/datadriven/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 22:37:26 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Data-driven system mapping</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I am a perfectionist. For most of my life, I thought that was a good thing. However, I now see how much it has negatively impacted my life. In this post, I explore my understanding one aspect of that&mdash;I believe that the combination of my perfectionistic tendencies plus my capacity to dissociate to a high degree is a main cause of my difficulties in the present.</p>
<p>Growing up, I strived to be the &ldquo;perfect child&rdquo;&mdash;I made good grades, never got into trouble, and was always submissive, smiling, and pleasant to be around. I made life incredibly easy for my parents and everyone else around me.
Of course, I had my difficult moments, but for the most part, my main goal in life was to embody perfection in every way possible.
And I believed that I succeeded.
However, while most parts of me strived for and held a perfect view of myself, not all parts of me met expectations.
In order to maintain my internal perception that I was perfect, I used dissociation to disown the parts of self and experiences that didn&rsquo;t fit my perfect view of self. Because I have DID, I learned the ability to subconsciously compartmentalize and disown any actions and experiences that are ego-dystonic, thus allowing me to curate my view of my self and the world around me.
In order to maintain this perfect self-view, I relied on maintaining dissociative barriers between parts of self&mdash;the &ldquo;perfect&rdquo; parts of me disowned the &ldquo;bad&rdquo; parts of me, resulting in amnesia for times where I didn&rsquo;t meet my own inflated expectations.</p>
<p>For most of my life, I was able to hold this perfectionist view of my life while still remaining functional. Although while in high school I had some academic difficulties, I found college to be pretty easy, primarily due to the fact that I had no life outside of school and academics. I strived to only earn As, and was successful, for the most part, because of how much energy I put into my studies. Overall, I had a pretty solid understanding and memory of my life during my undergraduate years, and showed effectively no negative symptoms of DID.</p>
<p>During grad school, things became more difficult. I was surrounded by peers who were more hard-working and intelligent than I was. I was taking classes that were more difficult than I was used to, along with doing research that I didn&rsquo;t feel like I had enough time or energy for. I struggled with the transition from undergrad to grad school, but I wasn&rsquo;t aware of it. My automatic response of disowning difficult experiences took over, resulting in me truly only seeing the &ldquo;good&rdquo; aspects of life. My worldview was so skewed towards the positive that I didn&rsquo;t see myself slipping more and more behind as my degree progressed. Parts of me held onto the perfectionistic view of self and life, while other parts of me were struggling with the reality of grad school, and neither parts were fully aware of the other parts. In grad school, my parts became more separated from each other than they had ever been before because I was not able to maintain the perfect view of myself, resulting in amnesia for large chunks of my grad school experience.</p>
<p>Over time, I went from functioning well at a high level to being effectively unaware of large aspects of my life and the world around me. I was not meeting my own expectations, and instead of allowing myself to realize that, I automatically turned to dissociation to make myself unaware of my perceived failings. While in reality, I was just encountering the stress that almost every graduate student faces, it was enough to trigger my dissociative defenses. However, I cannot emphasize enough that, for the vast majority of the time, I was simply unaware that I even had any stress or troubles because I had amnesia for those experiences. Thus, until starting therapy, I genuinely thought I was doing well in graduate school.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s only within the past year that I realized anything abnormal was happening. Last June, at the recommendation of others with DID, I started a journal to process my thoughts about my life. When I would read my journal back, I realized that there were entries in my journal that I didn&rsquo;t remember writing, in handwritings that I didn&rsquo;t recognize as my own. I&rsquo;d read these entries and see that they had a very different perspective of my life than I did. Over time, it became clear that I had separation between parts who were aware of my life&rsquo;s difficulties and those who were not. I had split parts to allow me to maintain my perfectionistic and positive world view.</p>
<p>Now, about 1.5 years after starting therapy, my amnesia surrounding negative life experiences has significantly improved. I now recognize my multiple handwritings and am mostly able to tell when parts who hold negative emotions, memories, and views of life are active. However, once more positive-viewing parts are out, I still have trouble relating to those negative emotions and experiences. I still generally have a positive view of life and self the vast majority of the time, but I&rsquo;m now also aware of the negative aspects of myself and life as well.</p>
<p>Having DID allowed to me believe that I truly <em>was</em> perfect. Not because I actually was&mdash;because nobody is&mdash;but because I would disown parts of self and experiences that didn&rsquo;t fit my perfectionistic view of myself, resulting in amnesia and an incomplete view of my life and circumstances. Because I strove for perfection over all else, I was able to mostly meet my perfecionsitic standards through high school and college&mdash;not much happened in my life then that fell outside of my range of &ldquo;perfect&rdquo;. In graduate school, however, I fell far behind because I wasn&rsquo;t able to meet my own expectations. I&rsquo;d then disown those experiences, leading to amnesia for large chunks of my life. When things got hard, I automatically relied on maladaptive coping mechanisms instead of fixing the problem at its root, resulting in more and more problems piling up. However, now that I am in touch with both the negative and positive aspects of life, I&rsquo;m more aware of my life circumstances and am functioning much better. I still have a long way to go, but I&rsquo;m making progress to becoming a more integrated person every day. One of the most important lessons I&rsquo;ve learned thus far is that I am not perfect, and that&rsquo;s okay.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/notperfect/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/notperfect/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 15:16:02 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>I’m not perfect, and that’s okay</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I switch a lot on a daily basis, probably because I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented/">polyfragmented</a>. The vast majority of the time, however, I&rsquo;m switching between parts who are familiar with one-another, so this kind of switching is smooth, with only a small blip in my conscious awareness. I typically call this kind of switching <em>shifting</em>, because, although I am changing between parts, it isn&rsquo;t jarring and I don&rsquo;t feel like I have a loss of control&mdash;I am able to hold a conversation and mostly remember my train of thought while shifting between parts.</p>
<p>When I experience true switching, however, I may lose awareness of the world around me, in a time span range of anywhere from seconds to hours. Typically this disconnect feels gradual and seamless, so much so that, unless something notable happens while I was in the dissociated state so I come back to a discretely different situation than before the switch, I&rsquo;m usually not aware that I ever switched.
It can feel like I&rsquo;m waking up from a dream, and I&rsquo;m not fully aware if I&rsquo;m still dreaming or if this is my reality.</p>
<p>I see a lot of parallels in how I experience dreaming and how I experience switching between parts that aren&rsquo;t familiar with one another. When a trauma-holding part, one that my more regulated adult parts aren&rsquo;t acquainted with, is triggered to take control, it can feel like a kind of dream-state. Typically leading up to the switch, I start to feel heavy&mdash;my thinking slows down and my vision starts to fade. It feels slow, gradual, and, most importantly, natural. In reality, however, my switches are much faster than how they feel internally. When the part takes over, the dream-like state gets deeper. Most of the time, I&rsquo;m just along for the ride while the trauma-holding part has control. Everything feels a bit off, but I&rsquo;m usually not aware enough to even realize that. My thinking has slowed so far down that I&rsquo;m unable to grasp onto the reality of the situation. My vision has faded, and I have no control. My body is moving in ways that I have no awareness of, and time is suspended. I am not even aware that I do not have control because I&rsquo;m not aware of the world around me.</p>
<p>Since starting therapy, I&rsquo;ve been more able to identify when I&rsquo;m in this dissociated state.
This is because my therapist, who is able to recognize when I have dissociated, can prompt my adult parts to get back online by reminding me that we are safe and asking where my adult parts are.
When this happens, I&rsquo;m now able to do something analogous to lucid dreaming, where I am aware that something is off about my reality and I can sometimes exhibit partial control over the situation. I may be able to suggest to the part in control about what to do. I can tell the part, by thinking, that we are safe and update them on the reality of the situation. Sometimes, when this happens, my adult parts switch back in and I gradually gain control over the situation again. Other times, however, the part in control may get even more scared and confused about what is happening, resulting in an even more painful situation. For the most part, these trauma-holding parts aren&rsquo;t aware of present time and context, and think that trauma is happening right now, so they&rsquo;re often terrified.</p>
<p>It is a very strange feeling when a trauma-holding part is in control and I am simultaneously aware of the situation. I have a little control over my actions, but not too much. If, for example, I try to move my arm, my arm may feel so heavy that I am unable to move it. If I try to speak, I can feel like I am being blocked from doing so. Meanwhile, my body is moving in ways and I am doing things that I have no control over and cannot predict. Everything feels very slow, heavy, and visually dark. That part has more control over my actions than I do, and that part feels like a separate entity to me. Because of this, it can feel like I am possessed, so it can be a really scary experience for all parts involved.</p>
<p>Eventually, I switch back in and gain control again. While in reality this is typically an instantaneous switch, it feels like I&rsquo;m slowly waking up from a dream. After I&rsquo;m back in control, if I think back to what just happened, I&rsquo;m often genuinely unsure if what just happened actually happened. Sometimes, my memory of the event is simply not there. Other times, I remember only fractions of the time that the other part was in control. When I do remember the event, I typically only remember certain aspects of it&mdash;for the most part, my visual memory is not there, but I may remember what I heard while I was in a dissociated state. Sometimes, when I switch back, my memories of the event come back to me all of a sudden, as if to update me about what just happened but without having experienced it myself.</p>
<p>For most of my life, I was so used to entering and exiting this dream-like state where other parts have control that I genuinely didn&rsquo;t know it was abnormal&mdash;it was normal to me.
I was never consciously aware that other parts ever took over until starting therapy. At first, when this would happen in my therapy sessions, I&rsquo;d switch back after an episode to my therapist asking me if I knew what had just happened. I didn&rsquo;t, but I&rsquo;d pretend that I did because I didn&rsquo;t want to come to terms with the fact that I didn&rsquo;t.
Over time, my therapist was able to cue me forward when I was actively in a dissociated state, thus allowing me to become more aware while other parts were in control to help me create connections between my parts.
Now, I am more able to recognize when I am in a dissociated state, but I absolutely would not have been able to do so without having my therapist explicitly point it out to me first&mdash;I was simply unaware otherwise.</p>
<p>Having DID is a confusing experience, and it&rsquo;s really difficult to put into words the reality of my situation. Most of my life feels no different to anybody elses, yet I also have these otherworldy experiences. Up until recently, I wasn&rsquo;t conscious of the times that I didn&rsquo;t not have control over my life. Since becoming aware, the awareness of the lack of control over my own actions is, quite frankly, terrifying. I don&rsquo;t know what all of my triggers are, so I could, in theory, have a dissociative episode at any moment. Thankfully, I believe that the vast majority of these episodes occur in the controlled environment of therapy.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/traumapart/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/traumapart/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 07:50:32 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>What does it feel like when a trauma-holding part takes control?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>One impactful symptom of DID that I struggle with is amnesia, which is significant enough for me that it impacts my daily functioning and severely affects my awareness of my life history.
I not only have difficulty constructing a functional narrative of my past, but I also often struggle with day-to-day amnesia.
The puzzling part of this all is that I seem to have gaps in awareness for things that are not at all trauma related. For example, I have at least one playful kid part, and after she has come out, my more regulated adult selves don&rsquo;t necessarily remember what I did when that part was out.
Additionally, when that kid part is out, I seem to have trouble fully remembering my adult life, along with my adult responsibilities.
Why is this? Why do my non-trauma-holding parts have amnesia for the actions of other non-trauma-holding parts? Isn&rsquo;t the point of amnesia to protect against difficult memories and experiences? Yes, but in my case, I believe it&rsquo;s also to protect me from the awareness that I have other parts of self with potentially ego-dystonic ways of being.</p>
<p>I believe I have day-to-day amnesia because I still haven&rsquo;t come to terms with the reality of having DID.
I have multiple versions of me that I switch between, and each only has a narrow view of how my life is supposed to function. The playful kid part doesn&rsquo;t want to deal with adult responsibilities, so she simply does not remember the boring aspects of my adult life. The more responsible parts of me do not want to realize that I can be so careless at times, spending hours obsessing over my fish tank and plants rather than dealing with the adult responsibilities that I&rsquo;m supposed to, so my responsible parts disown the actions of the kid part from my view of myself, resulting in partial amnesia.
My parts want to remain separate from each other because they each have different and conflicting ways of being in the world.
Different parts have different views of who <em>I</em> am, each following their narrow view of who they believe I am supposed to be.
In reality, I am <em>all</em> of my parts, and they are all me. I just haven&rsquo;t come to terms with that yet.</p>
<p>Since realizing this, I have tried to take on a new mindset of fully accepting all of my parts as they are.
However, since I&rsquo;ve spent my entire life operating with several disconnected versions of myself, each disowning the actions and experiences of the other parts, I have been incredibly unsuccessful at adopting this mindset thus far.
It&rsquo;s going to take a significant amount of effort, and a whole lot of teamwork between my parts, to change my ways and learn to accept all parts of myself.
The process of disowning the different versions of me has been an automatic process for my entire life thus far, so I can&rsquo;t expect this mindset change to be quick and seamless. I feel like I&rsquo;m at the stage now where I am aware of my parts, but still have not accepted them yet. I hope that, with time and acceptance, my amnesia will reduce and I will be able to gain more control over my life again.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/disowningparts/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/disowningparts/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 19:55:02 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Disowning different parts of self</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I began therapy for DID in January 2022, I had no idea how much my life had already spiraled out of control. Over the course of several years, I had gone from being a high-achieving student at the top of my class to being effectively unable to work because I was so triggered by the world around me.
However, because of my severe internal compartmentalization, I was unaware of my dysfunction&mdash;I had no idea anything abnormal was happening, and, for the most part, thought I was still the successful student I previously was.
I went from being an over-achiever to effectively dysfunctional.
This is because work went from a source of fun and inspiration to a source of stress, so work became triggering to me. There are a variety of factors that affect why work became so triggering, but the end result is the same&mdash;just as in the past I learned to avoid traumatic or stressful things by dissociating away from them, I continued the pattern and subconsciously learned to dissociate away from work.</p>
<p>Within my system structure, I have separate compartments for work, which are differentiated enough from my other compartments such that when the work parts aren&rsquo;t out, I&rsquo;m practically unaware of my work life.
However, because my work parts are so compartmentalized, when my work parts are out, I&rsquo;m able to hyperfocus on work, undistracted by the happenings of the world around me.
This is something I developed as a child&mdash;I learned to separate my work and home lives because they were so different.
When my system is running smoothly, the right parts come out on queue, working together harmoniously. My internal compartmenalization of different facets of my life has always been severe, and since it had had worked well in the past, I had never questioned it before.</p>
<p>During graduate school, over the span of several years, as work gradually became more and more triggering for me, my work parts slowly started coming out less and less organically. I began a cycle of behavior: when work was not stressful, I&rsquo;d work as normal. Then, when something stressful would come up, it&rsquo;d become much more difficult to work. For a period of time spanning days to weeks, I&rsquo;d be effectively unable to work, but I&rsquo;d be unaware that I wasn&rsquo;t working as normal. Then, I&rsquo;d inevitably become aware that I was &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; at work, and force myself to start work again, which was always incredibly difficult as I was working through being triggered. Once the stressor was alleviated or sufficiently forgotten about, I&rsquo;d be back to working as normal again. And then when the next stressor came up, the cycle would repeat.</p>
<p>This cycle has repeated at least a dozen times during my PhD thus far, and each time it has repeated, new parts would be created to &ldquo;take control of my life again&rdquo; once I realized I was not working productively. Because of this, my awareness of my work life has become increasingly fragmented. For me, my handwriting is a great indicator to differentiate between parts.
For most of my undergraduate years, I had two main handwritings, indicating the two main work parts who were consistent through the entirety of undergrad. But in graduate school, my handwriting has become much more inconsistent. Because of the way I&rsquo;ve split work parts, I can see in my academic journal that, over the span of several months, I&rsquo;m writing the same concepts down over and over again, all in different handwritings. I have difficulty picking up where the previous part left off, so I practically have to start my work all over again once a new part is created. It&rsquo;s clear that I&rsquo;m trying really hard to advance in work, but because I&rsquo;m creating new compartments to work as opposed to utilizing the old ones, my awareness of my work life has become extremely fractured and inconsistent.</p>
<p>Why am I creating new parts instead of using already created work parts? I&rsquo;m not entirely sure, but I can speculate. I believe it&rsquo;s because <a href="/posts/polyfragmented/">I am polyfragmented</a>, so I create parts really easily. And because the previous parts I subconsciously create to take control of my life eventually become too stressed to come out, I create new parts who are unaware of the stress in order to advance.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me an incredibly long time to gain the insight that I have now, and even now that I&rsquo;ve gained this insight, it&rsquo;s hard for me to break the cycle. Right now, I&rsquo;m at the stage that I&rsquo;m aware that this is how I operate, but I&rsquo;m not yet at the place where I&rsquo;m able to change it&mdash;I&rsquo;m stuck observing my cyclical parts.
I seem to have very little control over what goes on in my life, but it&rsquo;s starting to get better.
I am learning to become aware of what stage of the cycle I&rsquo;m in at any given time, which has allowed me to stay in the stage where work parts are out longer and the stage where I&rsquo;m dysfunctional shorter. I&rsquo;m making progress, but it&rsquo;s slow and incredibly difficult.</p>
<p>I truly hate that this is the way I operate. I do not enjoy being so stressed by my work that my dissociative defenses are constantly activated. There are large spans of time where I&rsquo;m totally unaware of work because I&rsquo;m so stressed by it, followed by times where I&rsquo;m hyperaware of how much I&rsquo;ve been &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; on work and have to pick up the pieces, over and over again.
To be clear, I do not believe I&rsquo;m &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; when I&rsquo;m in a stage of the cycle where I&rsquo;m unable to work. Rather, I consider myself to be in a triggered state that I have little to no control over. But from the outside looking in, if one is unaware that I have DID, it really looks like I do not care about my PhD and am intentionally slacking on my responsibilities.
This has been incredibly frustrating to come to terms with, as my behavior is still mostly out of my control as I am constantly responding to triggers in my environment, yet I have the strong desire to break the cycle.</p>
<p>What is the path forward? Ideally, I&rsquo;d like to stop this cyclical behavior so I can work as normal again. I want to stop creating new parts when I get too stressed. I want to have one or two dedicated work parts out like I did in my undergraduate years so my awareness of my work life isn&rsquo;t so fragmented. I want to stop being so triggered by work that my dissociate defenses are constantly activated. I truly just want to become productive at work again, and while I see the light at the end of the tunnel, I have a long way to go before I get there. For now, I&rsquo;ll take it one day at a time, as I slowly take back control of my life.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/howdidaffectswork/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/howdidaffectswork/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 04:18:25 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>How DID affects my work</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>While I do experience what one could call &ldquo;dissociative episodes&rdquo; where a trauma-holding part takes full control of our body for a period of time, most of the time I experience momentary episodes of dissociation, where a part only takes control of our body for a few seconds at the maximum. However, these can still be difficult and disrupting to my daily life.</p>
<p>These types of episodes are quite common for me&mdash;they occur several times a day, often clustered together in time.
For that brief moment, my concentration is entirely focused internally, and I have no little to no awareness of the external world around me.
Simultaneously, my face and/or body may be moving in ways that I have no control over or awareness of. I may make noises, or mumble things, that are indicative of what&rsquo;s going on internally.
Internally, I am flooded by difficult emotions, such as fear or shame, along with an associated thought or memory. I perceive what I am experiencing internally as if it&rsquo;s happing in reality.
My heart rate may spike, and I may break into a sweat.
And then, all of a sudden, it&rsquo;s over, and I&rsquo;m back to doing what I was doing before, unphased by what just occurred.
These episodes can last from fractions of a second to several seconds, and occur several times a day.
After they&rsquo;re over, I can easily forget what went on during the episode or what triggered it. I describe one of these episodes in <em><a href="/posts/partscontrol/">The parts I don’t know about still have control</a></em>.
Within DID language, I could describe such an event by saying that a trauma-holding part that I do not have full memory sharing with was triggered and briefly took over.
These events seem to be triggered by either queues in my external environment or internal happenings that I, for the most part, seem to be unaware of.</p>
<p>From the outside, all of this happens so fast that if you blink you might miss it. Or, you may think it a tic, or a flinch. Personally, I try to hide them so they&rsquo;re as undetectable as possible to the outside observer&mdash;I don&rsquo;t want to inadvertently let others know what I&rsquo;m experiencing.</p>
<p>From a therapeutic perspective, I&rsquo;m supposed to try and connect with these parts, or take a moment to reflect inwards, when they come up. However, I&rsquo;m so used to just moving on with my life after they occur, as I&rsquo;ve been doing my whole life, that it has become habitual. I typically don&rsquo;t even realize that I&rsquo;ve had one of these dissociative intrusions because they occur so frequently for me that I perceive them as being normal, and I rapidly forget that they even occurred and move on with life. I have too many of these a day to stop and reflect internally after every episode. I still see these episodes as a nuisance, rather than parts that are surfacing into my consciousness because they need help, as I should if I want to encourage integration between my parts. Healing is difficult work.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/intrusions/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/intrusions/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 19:07:13 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative intrusions</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>One impactful but not immediately obvious symptom of DID for me is that I do not seem to have a continuous internal sense of time&mdash;my awareness of my life is shuffled.
Because of this, I may have a hard time differentiating what happened yesterday versus what happened last week or last month,
or struggle with remembering if, for example, I have leftovers in my fridge now or if that was from weeks ago.
This has made things like tracking changes in my environment difficult.
For example, I have had spring-time allergies for much of my life, but I was unable to realize that until recently&mdash;every day in the spring, I&rsquo;d wake up with allergies, but to me that was just accepted as fact. I didn&rsquo;t remember that I had allergies yesterday or every day last week, or that I didn&rsquo;t have allergies last fall, or that I&rsquo;ve had allergies every spring since childhood. All I am aware of is that I have allergies in that moment. Only since concretely tracking my symptoms this year was I able to determine that I do have springtime allergies, despite having them for years.
Life really feels like a blur to me.</p>
<p>I believe these experiences can be explained by my system structure, which is heavily impacted by the fact that I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented">polyfragmented</a>.
I seem to shift and switch between compartments a significant amount on a daily basis, and many of these compartments, or parts, only seem to come out every few days or weeks. Since what is at the forefront of my awareness depends on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, and many of these parts only come out once in a while, the end result seems to be that my understanding of my life is very shuffled.</p>
<p>Right now, I have a hard time differentiating between these parts, which makes it difficult to map how my understanding of my life is shuffled. I can vaguely tell when the last time I was in an active compartment was because I remember those memories most prominently, but I don&rsquo;t know <em>who</em> the part is. Many of them feel the same except for mild memory differences, seemingly because I have low identity alteration.
I have been told that differentiating between parts takes time, so I am hopeful that I&rsquo;ll soon be able to identify my parts.
I&rsquo;ve been operating like this for my entire life without awareness that most others do not have such a shuffled awareness.
I&rsquo;m glad that I finally understand that I have DID and that I operate in this way, as it provides me language to contextualize my experiences. With time, I hope to gain a more broad view of my life and form a more continuous relationship with time.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/shuffledawareness/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/shuffledawareness/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 21:19:32 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Shuffled sense of time</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>DID is very much internal disorder. That is, unless I tell you that I have it, you wouldn&rsquo;t know<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. One of the ways DID affects my internal experience is that I have significant gaps in my memory, both of my past childhood, and of my present adulthood.
But amnesia is tricky&mdash;I don&rsquo;t know what I don&rsquo;t remember, so most of the time I don&rsquo;t realize I&rsquo;ve forgotten anything.</p>
<p>I believe I experience amnesia in a few ways.
The most innocuous type that I experience seems due to me having constricted awareness&mdash;each of my parts seems to act as a compartment of memory, so when I&rsquo;m in one compartment it may be difficult for me to index memories that occurred when I was in a different compartment of memory.
For example, if my partner talks about a hike we went on a few months ago when I&rsquo;m in a task-based compartment for cleaning, I may not remember the hike, but I may eventually get a very vague memory of it if they prompt me about it further. If I see a picture of us on the hike, it may help queue my memory of it more, but it still isn&rsquo;t a complete memory like it would be if I were in the compartment that was actually there on that hike.
I believe this is because hiking and cleaning occupy two entirely different compartments of my life; there&rsquo;s little in common between the two, and my constricted awareness makes it so that these memories aren&rsquo;t shared well between the two parts. This seems to be a version of state-dependent memory.</p>
<p>I also experience full amnesia between parts. That is, I will not have access to any of the memories of one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This typically seems to occur between compartments that hold trauma memories and ones that do not, but I also seem to experience this between non-trauma holding parts, and I&rsquo;m not yet sure why.</p>
<p>Within full amnesia, I seem to exhibit two types. The first is when I experience a discrete jump in my awareness when I switch between compartments where I have no idea what was happening just before the switch. This causes an obvious jump in my awareness, and may make it more noticeable that I have amnesia. I might find myself, all of a sudden, in a different room than I remember being in just a second ago, when in reality another part had moved me to that room outside of my awareness<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I experienced this when I was younger<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, but not as much as I&rsquo;ve gotten older. Now, I more so seem to have a sliding-window type memory&mdash;rather than a discrete jump in awareness, my memory of what happened gradually disappears over several minutes after a switch. This leads to a perceived smoother transition between parts, making my memory loss less obvious to me.</p>
<p>Regardless of the type of amnesia I have, I experience shuffling of memories and time jumps&mdash;I do not have a continuous, linear understanding of my life. For example, it may be hard for me to differentiate what occurred last week vs what occurred years ago, and sometimes things that occurred months ago feel more current to me than things that occurred even yesterday. As always, this seems to be justified by my understanding of how I operate&mdash;if I&rsquo;m in a compartment of memory that was last active a few months ago, those memories are more at the forefront of my awareness than memories formed in a different compartment yesterday.
This leads to a lot of confusing experiences, like looking out of my window and expecting it to be winter but seeing that it&rsquo;s actually summer, or all of a sudden noticing that the furniture in my apartment has moved from what I last remember, or looking at my plants and being amazed by how much they had grown because I remembered them being much smaller.
These sorts of experiences occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still early on in my DID discovery journey, so my understanding of my amnesia will likely change over time as I learn more about how I operate.
I hope this post serves as a snapshot in time of my awareness of how I operate a little over one year after starting therapy.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Unless you really know what to look for or you catch me in a dissociative episode, neither of which are likely.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, I have never had a full dissociative fugue where I end up in an entirely different location than I was before. Most of my dissociative episodes occur at home when I&rsquo;m alone or in when I&rsquo;m in threapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This, along with other symptoms, led to me receiving a dissociative disorder diagnosis as a pre-teen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/amnesia/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/amnesia/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 12:10:19 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative amnesia</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Imagine if, without your awareness, your deepest, most repressed thoughts and feelings were displayed for the world to see. With how my DID presents, this is something that occurs quite frequently for me. Because much of my most difficult emotions are separated from the core me, I am usually unaware of them until they surface and they&rsquo;re in the forefront of my awareness. Then, after they are over, I may forget that these dissociative episodes ever happened. This has led to me into many scary and sometimes dangerous situations, which typically leave me puzzled by what is happening in the world around me.</p>
<p>As an example, I like to go on evening walks for exercise. I typically walk one of a few routes in the densely populated city I live in. One day this past summer, I walked by a person who had some of the same characteristics as someone who caused me harm in the past. I walked by this individual without awareness that I was at all triggered. Then, in a split second, they started yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&rsquo;re scared of me, huh? What do you have to be scared about?&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>What?</em> It was so out of context for me; I had no idea why they were yelling at me. I wasn&rsquo;t scared of them&mdash;up until they started yelling at me, I hadn&rsquo;t even noticed them. I ignored them and calmly kept walking in the direction I was going. Then, they started moving towards me<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, continually yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why are you scared of me? You think I&rsquo;m threatening? There&rsquo;s nothing to be scared about!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I sped up walking and continued ignoring them. I felt very calm while this was happening, although I was confused by what going on. I eventually made it to the next block over and lost sight of them. I calmly walked home, and went out of my way to reassure myself that I had done nothing wrong, and that the person was at fault, not me. But <em>why</em> did this person think I was scared of them? Was I scared of them?</p>
<p>As it turns out, a part of me <em>was</em> scared of them. When I saw that person, that part became so scared, that they momentarily took control of our face and made a scared microexpression, directed at that person. However, I had no awareness that I was scared of them or that I had made any facial expression. This is because the parts of me who were on my evening walk were not connected with the part of me that was scared of the person, so from the perspective of the part of me that was going on a walk, I had no idea that anything abnormal was happening, while the scared part was simultaneously terrified.</p>
<p>Over the next few days, I intentionally went on my evening walk, purposefully walking past the location of the event to ensure I didn&rsquo;t associate anything negative with it. The parts of me walking felt perfectly fine, and I didn&rsquo;t realize anything was off.
Then, within a week, without realizing it, I stopped going on my evening walks. A month went by, and I still avoided walking, but it didn&rsquo;t even occur to me that I stopped.
I went from walking every day for months to only leaving my apartment when absolutely necessary. I didn&rsquo;t feel any fear associated with walking or leaving my apartment, but it was clearly there, dictating my behavior. It took over a month for me to realize anything was wrong, and once I pondered why I was no longer walking the reason became obvious&mdash;a part of me was still clearly scared of what had happened on that walk.
In order to get back to my walking routine, I gradually had to show that part that we were safe, and that that wasn&rsquo;t going to happen again, and even if it did, there were other parts who could take care of the situation like we had done last time. With this awareness in mind, over time, I managed to get back to going on my evening walks.</p>
<p>This is one example of how having DID affects my life and functioning. Before I became aware that I have DID, I was unaware of how much influence my parts had over my life. My behaviors are influenced by fear I cannot even grasp onto or feel. Other people may be more aware of my own internal state than even I am, since my body language may be contradictory to how I feel on the inside.
Getting to know my parts is helping me to become more aware of my internal state, and, in turn, will allow me to live a more complete life.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, they used a walker, so I was in little danger.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/partscontrol/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/partscontrol/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:30:21 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>The parts I don’t know about still have control</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was initially hesitant to write about anger, as it&rsquo;s an emotion I am not used to feeling<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
How could I write about something I know nothing about?
But I now realize that the absence of anger in my life is significant in itself, and is indicative of how I operate.</p>
<p>Anger is an emotion that I am simultaneously very sensitive to, yet not at all familar with&mdash;I am incredibly sensitive to the external display of anger in others, yet not at all familiar with how it feels internally.
I believe this is because when I was small, I grew up in an environment where my primary caregiver frequently displayed anger.
This is because they had unprocessed trauma of their own, which came out as fits of rage.
These bouts of anger were extremely terrifying for me as a young child, and ended in emotional and sometimes physical harm done to me.
Because of the repeated association of anger with terror, pain, and instability, I believe I learned to internally separate anger as a &ldquo;bad&rdquo; emotion, and shoved it away as an emotion that I did not want to experience.
My relationship with anger was tainted by my early childhood experiences, making a powerful emotion that should be utilized as part of an emotionally healthy life inaccessible to me as an adult.</p>
<p>I once naively believed that not feeling anger was an asset of mine&mdash;that anger was a disruptive emotion, and it was safer for me not to feel it. While it is beneficial to those around me for me to not ever display anger, I now believe that anger is an important emotion that should be part of my emotional repertoire.
Anger enables people to enact change. By my not being able to experience anger, I&rsquo;m more likely to stay involved in situations and environments which are not good for me, making me to be more likely to be repeatedly victimized.
Due to my upbringing, I learned to value other peoples' comfort over my own, and use dissociation to subconsciously withhold my sometimes justified anger.</p>
<p>I believe that because I have DID<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, my dynamic range of emotions is very shallow&mdash;most of the time, I feel mild contentment. I grew up in an environment where I didn&rsquo;t feel like I could take up any emotional space, as the emotional landscape in my family of origin was dominated by others' strong emotional displays. I enjoy my internal stability&mdash;I do not want to feel strong emotions. I am scared of the loss of control I was so used to seeing in others while growing up.
However, this separation of anger and other emotions leads to a less full life, including amnesia, behavior that feels out of my control when I&rsquo;m triggered, along with stunted &ldquo;good&rdquo; emotions, like happiness and excitement. By using dissociation, I&rsquo;ve traded experiencing a full range of emotions for internal stability. This served me well in the past, but in the future I&rsquo;d like to live a more full, complete life&mdash;one that does not rely on maladaptive dissociative coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>While I now see anger as a valuable emotion, my learned patterns of removing it from my awareness continue, so still I have difficulty accessing it.
My understanding of anger comes from a theoretical view&mdash;I can intellectually understand it, but I do not believe I have felt genuine anger before. With time, I hope that will change.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>And maybe I was right to be hesitant, as I don&rsquo;t have much to say since I&rsquo;m early in my awareness journey, but I want to document my understanding of things at various stages of healing.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I believe I am this way due to how I responded to experiences in my childhood, which resulted in me forming maladaptive coping mechanisms which can be labeled DID.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/anger/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/anger/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 11:05:58 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anger</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from minutes to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
Additionally, <a href="/posts/shuffledawareness/">my internal awareness of my life is shuffled</a>, so I do not have a linear narrative history of my life or day-to-day activities.
This can affect my daily functioning significantly.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I use <em>switch</em> to denote a hard, discrete change between parts, which usually occurs when I&rsquo;m triggered and can be disorienting. I use <em>shift</em> to denote a smooth change between parts, which occurs more often than switching for me and can internally feel like a gear shifting in my brain.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12, I stopped feeling anxiety. Prior to that, I was a child ravished by anxiety. Then, one day, it stopped<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. And I have never experienced anxiety in the same way since.</p>
<p>I now understand that anxiety is one of the experiences that I dissociated away&mdash;it&rsquo;s a state that I did not enjoy experiencing, so I learned how to compartmentalize it and push it out of my awareness.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean I do not <em>experience</em> anxiety; rather, it means that when I do, I am so detached from it that I do not experience all aspects of it.</p>
<p>My body trembles, lower lip quivers, and heart races, yet I don&rsquo;t know why I am experiencing these physical symptoms.
My mind races with irrational thought loops, yet I can&rsquo;t quite grasp onto them so they feel like meaningless noise to me.
I am disconnected and emotionally numb. Except for when I am not.</p>
<p>When I am able to connect with the feeling of anxiety, it is all-encompassing and feels everlasting. When something triggers anxiety to the forefront of my awareness, it is all I can concentrate on, and I will do whatever I need to do to alleviate the feeling. Then, all of a sudden, it goes away as quickly as it came, and after it&rsquo;s over I gradually forget that it ever happened.</p>
<p>Right now, as I write this, I do not know what anxiety feels like. Parts of me do, but I am not connected with those parts. For the most part, I feel like an emotionless machine, going through the motions of life. Despite the fact that I&rsquo;m unable to connect with anxiety, that doesn&rsquo;t mean it doesn&rsquo;t affect me. My behaviors are controlled by fear and anxiety that I cannot feel&mdash;I can only intellectually infer that I am being affected by anxiety by examining my behaviors. I avoid leaving my apartment, interacting with others, and doing things that may eventually lead to stressful situations. Yet I do not experience the associated emotions with these behaviors&mdash;I am numb.</p>
<p>When I was 12, I didn&rsquo;t become a less anxious person&mdash;I just became more detached from my anxiety. My crippling anxiety wasn&rsquo;t miraculously cured. Instead, it was like fixing a wound that needed stitches with a band-aid&mdash;an easy, temporary solution that left me worse-off in the long term.</p>
<p>In order to decrease my amnesia and regain control of my life, I need to connect back with my anxiety.
Although it allows me to avoid difficult feelings in the moment, my current method of dealing with anxiety&mdash;compartmentalizing it and shoving it from my awareness&mdash;leads to uncontrollable fear-based behavior, a lack of internal awareness, and amnesia. I need to connect with this destabilizing experience once again, this time working though it instead of shoving it from my awareness. Then, I can address its root causes and gain control of my life again.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My mom reports me having a discrete personality change when this occurred.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/anxiety/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/anxiety/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 19:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anxiety</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have always been nerdy. From a young age, I immersed myself in academic work, as I enjoyed learning and the strict routine that school provided for me. I also had an intense need to perform well&mdash;my perfectionistic tendencies dominated my life as a child. While I often did perform well academically, there were times where I performed markedly poorly on assessments, so far outside the norm of what would have ordinarily be expected of me, despite preparing and knowing the material. For example, on one occasion in high school, I was so prepared for an exam that I helped tutor my friends about the material leading up to it, only for me to fail while they performed well. I wasn&rsquo;t ordinarily a bad test taker&mdash;I genuinely didn&rsquo;t understand the material when exam time came. To put it simply, there were times when I was smart, and times when I was&hellip; not. I  now understand this to be as a result of having DID.</p>
<p>Some of my parts were formed when I was a small child. When I am in these compartments, although I may be aware that I am an adult, I typically have the mental ability of around the age in which those parts developed. These compartments are essentially snapshots of my mindset at the time they were created, with varying levels of awareness of the present day. One major implication of this is that my ability to understand information varies depending on which compartment of awareness I am in. For example, I have a younger, very timid part that sometimes comes out that has the mental ability of a 7-year-old. When this part is active, I am unable to grasp onto the complex topics required of me for my PhD that I can normally do with relative ease when the right part of me is active. I am not aware of what I do not know, believing what I know in that moment is all that I do know. This part of me often comes out around others while I&rsquo;m supposed to be having intellectual discussions. The results are humiliating&mdash;I am unable to discuss even my own research, which the right parts of me are very familiar with. Many a time I have left a meeting feeling absolutely defeated and frustrated that I was unable to discuss my research properly. However, there were other times, when the correct parts were out, that I was very much able to hold an academic discussion about my work. My fluctuating knowledge of my work has detrimentally impacted my academic career thus far.</p>
<p>Before I knew I had DID, I never questioned my fluctuating levels of intelligence. However, I did come up with a justification for my poor performance&mdash;when I was in compartments that weren&rsquo;t aware of my more academic parts, I truly believed that I was dumber than all of my peers. I believed that any time I had performed well I had cheated, and I had faked my way to where I am today as a PhD student. There are times where I&rsquo;d look at my academic papers, ones that I had written, and not only did I not understand what the material was about, but I didn&rsquo;t fully remember writing them. I developed extreme imposter syndrome as a result of this&mdash;I truly didn&rsquo;t feel like I belonged in my institution, and I believed that I had genuine reasons as to why.</p>
<p>It has only been within the last several months that I&rsquo;ve been able to identify when I&rsquo;m in a compartment of awareness that is not necessarily able to understand the material required of me in order to complete my degree, and I now see that the difference in ability is pronounced. When one of these parts of me are active, I now stop working and try to understand why it is out. What is preventing me from accessing the compartments of me that do work? Sometimes the answer is obvious; other times, I&rsquo;m not so sure. Most frequently, however, I don&rsquo;t realize that a non-academic part has been out until after it has already gone, when I relook at a problem that I was previously agonizing over and it becomes obvious. I&rsquo;m still trying to understand these parts of myself, but just knowing that my having DID explains much of my academic distress really helps me understand why I am the way that I am.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 21:52:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Fluctuating intelligence</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
