







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/amnesia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>amnesia</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/amnesia/</link>
        
        
            <title>amnesia</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>While I do experience what one could call &ldquo;dissociative episodes&rdquo; where a trauma-holding part takes full control of our body for a period of time, most of the time I experience momentary episodes of dissociation, where a part only takes control of our body for a few seconds at the maximum. However, these can still be difficult and disrupting to my daily life.</p>
<p>These types of episodes are quite common for me&mdash;they occur several times a day, often clustered together in time.
For that brief moment, my concentration is entirely focused internally, and I have no little to no awareness of the external world around me.
Simultaneously, my face and/or body may be moving in ways that I have no control over or awareness of. I may make noises, or mumble things, that are indicative of what&rsquo;s going on internally.
Internally, I am flooded by difficult emotions, such as fear or shame, along with an associated thought or memory. I perceive what I am experiencing internally as if it&rsquo;s happing in reality.
My heart rate may spike, and I may break into a sweat.
And then, all of a sudden, it&rsquo;s over, and I&rsquo;m back to doing what I was doing before, unphased by what just occurred.
These episodes can last from fractions of a second to several seconds, and occur several times a day.
After they&rsquo;re over, I can easily forget what went on during the episode or what triggered it. I describe one of these episodes in <em><a href="/posts/partscontrol/">The parts I don’t know about still have control</a></em>.
Within DID language, I could describe such an event by saying that a trauma-holding part that I do not have full memory sharing with was triggered and briefly took over.
These events seem to be triggered by either queues in my external environment or internal happenings that I, for the most part, seem to be unaware of.</p>
<p>From the outside, all of this happens so fast that if you blink you might miss it. Or, you may think it a tic, or a flinch. Personally, I try to hide them so they&rsquo;re as undetectable as possible to the outside observer&mdash;I don&rsquo;t want to inadvertently let others know what I&rsquo;m experiencing.</p>
<p>From a therapeutic perspective, I&rsquo;m supposed to try and connect with these parts, or take a moment to reflect inwards, when they come up. However, I&rsquo;m so used to just moving on with my life after they occur, as I&rsquo;ve been doing my whole life, that it has become habitual. I typically don&rsquo;t even realize that I&rsquo;ve had one of these dissociative intrusions because they occur so frequently for me that I perceive them as being normal, and I rapidly forget that they even occurred and move on with life. I have too many of these a day to stop and reflect internally after every episode. I still see these episodes as a nuisance, rather than parts that are surfacing into my consciousness because they need help, as I should if I want to encourage integration between my parts. Healing is difficult work.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/intrusions/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/intrusions/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 19:07:13 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative intrusions</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>DID is very much internal disorder. That is, unless I tell you that I have it, you wouldn&rsquo;t know<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. One of the ways DID affects my internal experience is that I have significant gaps in my memory, both of my past childhood, and of my present adulthood.
But amnesia is tricky&mdash;I don&rsquo;t know what I don&rsquo;t remember, so most of the time I don&rsquo;t realize I&rsquo;ve forgotten anything.</p>
<p>I believe I experience amnesia in a few ways.
The most innocuous type that I experience seems due to me having constricted awareness&mdash;each of my parts seems to act as a compartment of memory, so when I&rsquo;m in one compartment it may be difficult for me to index memories that occurred when I was in a different compartment of memory.
For example, if my partner talks about a hike we went on a few months ago when I&rsquo;m in a task-based compartment for cleaning, I may not remember the hike, but I may eventually get a very vague memory of it if they prompt me about it further. If I see a picture of us on the hike, it may help queue my memory of it more, but it still isn&rsquo;t a complete memory like it would be if I were in the compartment that was actually there on that hike.
I believe this is because hiking and cleaning occupy two entirely different compartments of my life; there&rsquo;s little in common between the two, and my constricted awareness makes it so that these memories aren&rsquo;t shared well between the two parts. This seems to be a version of state-dependent memory.</p>
<p>I also experience full amnesia between parts. That is, I will not have access to any of the memories of one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This typically seems to occur between compartments that hold trauma memories and ones that do not, but I also seem to experience this between non-trauma holding parts, and I&rsquo;m not yet sure why.</p>
<p>Within full amnesia, I seem to exhibit two types. The first is when I experience a discrete jump in my awareness when I switch between compartments where I have no idea what was happening just before the switch. This causes an obvious jump in my awareness, and may make it more noticeable that I have amnesia. I might find myself, all of a sudden, in a different room than I remember being in just a second ago, when in reality another part had moved me to that room outside of my awareness<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I experienced this when I was younger<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, but not as much as I&rsquo;ve gotten older. Now, I more so seem to have a sliding-window type memory&mdash;rather than a discrete jump in awareness, my memory of what happened gradually disappears over several minutes after a switch. This leads to a perceived smoother transition between parts, making my memory loss less obvious to me.</p>
<p>Regardless of the type of amnesia I have, I experience shuffling of memories and time jumps&mdash;I do not have a continuous, linear understanding of my life. For example, it may be hard for me to differentiate what occurred last week vs what occurred years ago, and sometimes things that occurred months ago feel more current to me than things that occurred even yesterday. As always, this seems to be justified by my understanding of how I operate&mdash;if I&rsquo;m in a compartment of memory that was last active a few months ago, those memories are more at the forefront of my awareness than memories formed in a different compartment yesterday.
This leads to a lot of confusing experiences, like looking out of my window and expecting it to be winter but seeing that it&rsquo;s actually summer, or all of a sudden noticing that the furniture in my apartment has moved from what I last remember, or looking at my plants and being amazed by how much they had grown because I remembered them being much smaller.
These sorts of experiences occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still early on in my DID discovery journey, so my understanding of my amnesia will likely change over time as I learn more about how I operate.
I hope this post serves as a snapshot in time of my awareness of how I operate a little over one year after starting therapy.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Unless you really know what to look for or you catch me in a dissociative episode, neither of which are likely.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Thankfully, I have never had a full dissociative fugue where I end up in an entirely different location than I was before. Most of my dissociative episodes occur at home when I&rsquo;m alone or in when I&rsquo;m in threapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>This, along with other symptoms, led to me receiving a dissociative disorder diagnosis as a pre-teen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/amnesia/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/amnesia/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 12:10:19 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative amnesia</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Imagine if, without your awareness, your deepest, most repressed thoughts and feelings were displayed for the world to see. With how my DID presents, this is something that occurs quite frequently for me. Because much of my most difficult emotions are separated from the core me, I am usually unaware of them until they surface and they&rsquo;re in the forefront of my awareness. Then, after they are over, I may forget that these dissociative episodes ever happened. This has led to me into many scary and sometimes dangerous situations, which typically leave me puzzled by what is happening in the world around me.</p>
<p>As an example, I like to go on evening walks for exercise. I typically walk one of a few routes in the densely populated city I live in. One day this past summer, I walked by a person who had some of the same characteristics as someone who caused me harm in the past. I walked by this individual without awareness that I was at all triggered. Then, in a split second, they started yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&rsquo;re scared of me, huh? What do you have to be scared about?&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>What?</em> It was so out of context for me; I had no idea why they were yelling at me. I wasn&rsquo;t scared of them&mdash;up until they started yelling at me, I hadn&rsquo;t even noticed them. I ignored them and calmly kept walking in the direction I was going. Then, they started moving towards me<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, continually yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why are you scared of me? You think I&rsquo;m threatening? There&rsquo;s nothing to be scared about!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I sped up walking and continued ignoring them. I felt very calm while this was happening, although I was confused by what going on. I eventually made it to the next block over and lost sight of them. I calmly walked home, and went out of my way to reassure myself that I had done nothing wrong, and that the person was at fault, not me. But <em>why</em> did this person think I was scared of them? Was I scared of them?</p>
<p>As it turns out, a part of me <em>was</em> scared of them. When I saw that person, that part became so scared, that they momentarily took control of our face and made a scared microexpression, directed at that person. However, I had no awareness that I was scared of them or that I had made any facial expression. This is because the parts of me who were on my evening walk were not connected with the part of me that was scared of the person, so from the perspective of the part of me that was going on a walk, I had no idea that anything abnormal was happening, while the scared part was simultaneously terrified.</p>
<p>Over the next few days, I intentionally went on my evening walk, purposefully walking past the location of the event to ensure I didn&rsquo;t associate anything negative with it. The parts of me walking felt perfectly fine, and I didn&rsquo;t realize anything was off.
Then, within a week, without realizing it, I stopped going on my evening walks. A month went by, and I still avoided walking, but it didn&rsquo;t even occur to me that I stopped.
I went from walking every day for months to only leaving my apartment when absolutely necessary. I didn&rsquo;t feel any fear associated with walking or leaving my apartment, but it was clearly there, dictating my behavior. It took over a month for me to realize anything was wrong, and once I pondered why I was no longer walking the reason became obvious&mdash;a part of me was still clearly scared of what had happened on that walk.
In order to get back to my walking routine, I gradually had to show that part that we were safe, and that that wasn&rsquo;t going to happen again, and even if it did, there were other parts who could take care of the situation like we had done last time. With this awareness in mind, over time, I managed to get back to going on my evening walks.</p>
<p>This is one example of how having DID affects my life and functioning. Before I became aware that I have DID, I was unaware of how much influence my parts had over my life. My behaviors are influenced by fear I cannot even grasp onto or feel. Other people may be more aware of my own internal state than even I am, since my body language may be contradictory to how I feel on the inside.
Getting to know my parts is helping me to become more aware of my internal state, and, in turn, will allow me to live a more complete life.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Thankfully, they used a walker, so I was in little danger.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/partscontrol/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/partscontrol/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:30:21 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>The parts I don’t know about still have control</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
