







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/academia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>academia</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/academia/</link>
        
        
            <title>academia</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I am a perfectionist. For most of my life, I thought that was a good thing. However, I now see how much it has negatively impacted my life. In this post, I explore my understanding one aspect of that&mdash;I believe that the combination of my perfectionistic tendencies plus my capacity to dissociate to a high degree is a main cause of my difficulties in the present.</p>
<p>Growing up, I strived to be the &ldquo;perfect child&rdquo;&mdash;I made good grades, never got into trouble, and was always submissive, smiling, and pleasant to be around. I made life incredibly easy for my parents and everyone else around me.
Of course, I had my difficult moments, but for the most part, my main goal in life was to embody perfection in every way possible.
And I believed that I succeeded.
However, while most parts of me strived for and held a perfect view of myself, not all parts of me met expectations.
In order to maintain my internal perception that I was perfect, I used dissociation to disown the parts of self and experiences that didn&rsquo;t fit my perfect view of self. Because I have DID, I learned the ability to subconsciously compartmentalize and disown any actions and experiences that are ego-dystonic, thus allowing me to curate my view of my self and the world around me.
In order to maintain this perfect self-view, I relied on maintaining dissociative barriers between parts of self&mdash;the &ldquo;perfect&rdquo; parts of me disowned the &ldquo;bad&rdquo; parts of me, resulting in amnesia for times where I didn&rsquo;t meet my own inflated expectations.</p>
<p>For most of my life, I was able to hold this perfectionist view of my life while still remaining functional. Although while in high school I had some academic difficulties, I found college to be pretty easy, primarily due to the fact that I had no life outside of school and academics. I strived to only earn As, and was successful, for the most part, because of how much energy I put into my studies. Overall, I had a pretty solid understanding and memory of my life during my undergraduate years, and showed effectively no negative symptoms of DID.</p>
<p>During grad school, things became more difficult. I was surrounded by peers who were more hard-working and intelligent than I was. I was taking classes that were more difficult than I was used to, along with doing research that I didn&rsquo;t feel like I had enough time or energy for. I struggled with the transition from undergrad to grad school, but I wasn&rsquo;t aware of it. My automatic response of disowning difficult experiences took over, resulting in me truly only seeing the &ldquo;good&rdquo; aspects of life. My worldview was so skewed towards the positive that I didn&rsquo;t see myself slipping more and more behind as my degree progressed. Parts of me held onto the perfectionistic view of self and life, while other parts of me were struggling with the reality of grad school, and neither parts were fully aware of the other parts. In grad school, my parts became more separated from each other than they had ever been before because I was not able to maintain the perfect view of myself, resulting in amnesia for large chunks of my grad school experience.</p>
<p>Over time, I went from functioning well at a high level to being effectively unaware of large aspects of my life and the world around me. I was not meeting my own expectations, and instead of allowing myself to realize that, I automatically turned to dissociation to make myself unaware of my perceived failings. While in reality, I was just encountering the stress that almost every graduate student faces, it was enough to trigger my dissociative defenses. However, I cannot emphasize enough that, for the vast majority of the time, I was simply unaware that I even had any stress or troubles because I had amnesia for those experiences. Thus, until starting therapy, I genuinely thought I was doing well in graduate school.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s only within the past year that I realized anything abnormal was happening. Last June, at the recommendation of others with DID, I started a journal to process my thoughts about my life. When I would read my journal back, I realized that there were entries in my journal that I didn&rsquo;t remember writing, in handwritings that I didn&rsquo;t recognize as my own. I&rsquo;d read these entries and see that they had a very different perspective of my life than I did. Over time, it became clear that I had separation between parts who were aware of my life&rsquo;s difficulties and those who were not. I had split parts to allow me to maintain my perfectionistic and positive world view.</p>
<p>Now, about 1.5 years after starting therapy, my amnesia surrounding negative life experiences has significantly improved. I now recognize my multiple handwritings and am mostly able to tell when parts who hold negative emotions, memories, and views of life are active. However, once more positive-viewing parts are out, I still have trouble relating to those negative emotions and experiences. I still generally have a positive view of life and self the vast majority of the time, but I&rsquo;m now also aware of the negative aspects of myself and life as well.</p>
<p>Having DID allowed to me believe that I truly <em>was</em> perfect. Not because I actually was&mdash;because nobody is&mdash;but because I would disown parts of self and experiences that didn&rsquo;t fit my perfectionistic view of myself, resulting in amnesia and an incomplete view of my life and circumstances. Because I strove for perfection over all else, I was able to mostly meet my perfectionsitic standards through high school and college&mdash;not much happened in my life then that fell outside of my range of &ldquo;perfect&rdquo;. In graduate school, however, I fell far behind because I wasn&rsquo;t able to meet my own expectations. I&rsquo;d then disown those experiences, leading to amnesia for large chunks of my life. When things got hard, I automatically relied on maladaptive coping mechanisms instead of fixing the problem at its root, resulting in more and more problems piling up. However, now that I am in touch with both the negative and positive aspects of life, I&rsquo;m more aware of my life circumstances and am functioning much better. I still have a long way to go, but I&rsquo;m making progress to becoming a more integrated person every day. One of the most important lessons I&rsquo;ve learned thus far is that I am not perfect, and that&rsquo;s okay.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/notperfect/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/notperfect/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 15:16:02 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>I’m not perfect, and that’s okay</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I began therapy for DID in January 2022, I had no idea how much my life had already spiraled out of control. Over the course of several years, I had gone from being a high-achieving student at the top of my class to being effectively unable to work because I was so triggered by the world around me.
However, because of my severe internal compartmentalization, I was unaware of my dysfunction&mdash;I had no idea anything abnormal was happening, and, for the most part, thought I was still the successful student I previously was.
I went from being an over-achiever to effectively dysfunctional.
This is because work went from a source of fun and inspiration to a source of stress, so work became triggering to me. There are a variety of factors that affect why work became so triggering, but the end result is the same&mdash;just as in the past I learned to avoid traumatic or stressful things by dissociating away from them, I continued the pattern and subconsciously learned to dissociate away from work.</p>
<p>Within my system structure, I have separate compartments for work, which are differentiated enough from my other compartments such that when the work parts aren&rsquo;t out, I&rsquo;m practically unaware of my work life.
However, because my work parts are so compartmentalized, when my work parts are out, I&rsquo;m able to hyperfocus on work, undistracted by the happenings of the world around me.
This is something I developed as a child&mdash;I learned to separate my work and home lives because they were so different.
When my system is running smoothly, the right parts come out on queue, working together harmoniously. My internal compartmenalization of different facets of my life has always been severe, and since it had had worked well in the past, I had never questioned it before.</p>
<p>During graduate school, over the span of several years, as work gradually became more and more triggering for me, my work parts slowly started coming out less and less organically. I began a cycle of behavior: when work was not stressful, I&rsquo;d work as normal. Then, when something stressful would come up, it&rsquo;d become much more difficult to work. For a period of time spanning days to weeks, I&rsquo;d be effectively unable to work, but I&rsquo;d be unaware that I wasn&rsquo;t working as normal. Then, I&rsquo;d inevitably become aware that I was &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; at work, and force myself to start work again, which was always incredibly difficult as I was working through being triggered. Once the stressor was alleviated or sufficiently forgotten about, I&rsquo;d be back to working as normal again. And then when the next stressor came up, the cycle would repeat.</p>
<p>This cycle has repeated at least a dozen times during my PhD thus far, and each time it has repeated, new parts would be created to &ldquo;take control of my life again&rdquo; once I realized I was not working productively. Because of this, my awareness of my work life has become increasingly fragmented. For me, my handwriting is a great indicator to differentiate between parts.
For most of my undergraduate years, I had two main handwritings, indicating the two main work parts who were consistent through the entirety of undergrad. But in graduate school, my handwriting has become much more inconsistent. Because of the way I&rsquo;ve split work parts, I can see in my academic journal that, over the span of several months, I&rsquo;m writing the same concepts down over and over again, all in different handwritings. I have difficulty picking up where the previous part left off, so I practically have to start my work all over again once a new part is created. It&rsquo;s clear that I&rsquo;m trying really hard to advance in work, but because I&rsquo;m creating new compartments to work as opposed to utilizing the old ones, my awareness of my work life has become extremely fractured and inconsistent.</p>
<p>Why am I creating new parts instead of using already created work parts? I&rsquo;m not entirely sure, but I can speculate. I believe it&rsquo;s because <a href="/posts/polyfragmented/">I am polyfragmented</a>, so I create parts really easily. And because the previous parts I subconsciously create to take control of my life eventually become too stressed to come out, I create new parts who are unaware of the stress in order to advance.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me an incredibly long time to gain the insight that I have now, and even now that I&rsquo;ve gained this insight, it&rsquo;s hard for me to break the cycle. Right now, I&rsquo;m at the stage that I&rsquo;m aware that this is how I operate, but I&rsquo;m not yet at the place where I&rsquo;m able to change it&mdash;I&rsquo;m stuck observing my cyclical parts.
I seem to have very little control over what goes on in my life, but it&rsquo;s starting to get better.
I am learning to become aware of what stage of the cycle I&rsquo;m in at any given time, which has allowed me to stay in the stage where work parts are out longer and the stage where I&rsquo;m dysfunctional shorter. I&rsquo;m making progress, but it&rsquo;s slow and incredibly difficult.</p>
<p>I truly hate that this is the way I operate. I do not enjoy being so stressed by my work that my dissociative defenses are constantly activated. There are large spans of time where I&rsquo;m totally unaware of work because I&rsquo;m so stressed by it, followed by times where I&rsquo;m hyperaware of how much I&rsquo;ve been &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; on work and have to pick up the pieces, over and over again.
To be clear, I do not believe I&rsquo;m &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; when I&rsquo;m in a stage of the cycle where I&rsquo;m unable to work. Rather, I consider myself to be in a triggered state that I have little to no control over. But from the outside looking in, if one is unaware that I have DID, it really looks like I do not care about my PhD and am intentionally slacking on my responsibilities.
This has been incredibly frustrating to come to terms with, as my behavior is still mostly out of my control as I am constantly responding to triggers in my environment, yet I have the strong desire to break the cycle.</p>
<p>What is the path forward? Ideally, I&rsquo;d like to stop this cyclical behavior so I can work as normal again. I want to stop creating new parts when I get too stressed. I want to have one or two dedicated work parts out like I did in my undergraduate years so my awareness of my work life isn&rsquo;t so fragmented. I want to stop being so triggered by work that my dissociate defenses are constantly activated. I truly just want to become productive at work again, and while I see the light at the end of the tunnel, I have a long way to go before I get there. For now, I&rsquo;ll take it one day at a time, as I slowly take back control of my life.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/howdidaffectswork/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/howdidaffectswork/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 04:18:25 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>How DID affects my work</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have always been nerdy. From a young age, I immersed myself in academic work, as I enjoyed learning and the strict routine that school provided for me. I also had an intense need to perform well&mdash;my perfectionistic tendencies dominated my life as a child. While I often did perform well academically, there were times where I performed markedly poorly on assessments, so far outside the norm of what would have ordinarily be expected of me, despite preparing and knowing the material. For example, on one occasion in high school, I was so prepared for an exam that I helped tutor my friends about the material leading up to it, only for me to fail while they performed well. I wasn&rsquo;t ordinarily a bad test taker&mdash;I genuinely didn&rsquo;t understand the material when exam time came. To put it simply, there were times when I was smart, and times when I was&hellip; not. I  now understand this to be as a result of having DID.</p>
<p>Some of my parts were formed when I was a small child. When I am in these compartments, although I may be aware that I am an adult, I typically have the mental ability of around the age in which those parts developed. These compartments are essentially snapshots of my mindset at the time they were created, with varying levels of awareness of the present day. One major implication of this is that my ability to understand information varies depending on which compartment of awareness I am in. For example, I have a younger, very timid part that sometimes comes out that has the mental ability of a 7-year-old. When this part is active, I am unable to grasp onto the complex topics required of me for my PhD that I can normally do with relative ease when the right part of me is active. I am not aware of what I do not know, believing what I know in that moment is all that I do know. This part of me often comes out around others while I&rsquo;m supposed to be having intellectual discussions. The results are humiliating&mdash;I am unable to discuss even my own research, which the right parts of me are very familiar with. Many a time I have left a meeting feeling absolutely defeated and frustrated that I was unable to discuss my research properly. However, there were other times, when the correct parts were out, that I was very much able to hold an academic discussion about my work. My fluctuating knowledge of my work has detrimentally impacted my academic career thus far.</p>
<p>Before I knew I had DID, I never questioned my fluctuating levels of intelligence. However, I did come up with a justification for my poor performance&mdash;when I was in compartments that weren&rsquo;t aware of my more academic parts, I truly believed that I was dumber than all of my peers. I believed that any time I had performed well I had cheated, and I had faked my way to where I am today as a PhD student. There are times where I&rsquo;d look at my academic papers, ones that I had written, and not only did I not understand what the material was about, but I didn&rsquo;t fully remember writing them. I developed extreme imposter syndrome as a result of this&mdash;I truly didn&rsquo;t feel like I belonged in my institution, and I believed that I had genuine reasons as to why.</p>
<p>It has only been within the last several months that I&rsquo;ve been able to identify when I&rsquo;m in a compartment of awareness that is not necessarily able to understand the material required of me in order to complete my degree, and I now see that the difference in ability is pronounced. When one of these parts of me are active, I now stop working and try to understand why it is out. What is preventing me from accessing the compartments of me that do work? Sometimes the answer is obvious; other times, I&rsquo;m not so sure. Most frequently, however, I don&rsquo;t realize that a non-academic part has been out until after it has already gone, when I relook at a problem that I was previously agonizing over and it becomes obvious. I&rsquo;m still trying to understand these parts of myself, but just knowing that my having DID explains much of my academic distress really helps me understand why I am the way that I am.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 21:52:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Fluctuating intelligence</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
