







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="http://www.lico.blog/tags/narrative/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>narrative</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>http://www.lico.blog/tags/narrative/</link>
        
        
            <title>narrative</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>My relationship with my DID diagnoses&mdash;both with regards to accepting it as my diagnosis and understanding how it affects me&mdash;has evolved significantly since starting therapy.
Over the past approximately 1.5 years, I&rsquo;ve been through several distinct stages of recovery.</p>
<h4 id="stage-0-buildup-to-starting-therapy-october-2021--january-2022">Stage 0: Buildup to starting therapy (October 2021&ndash;January 2022)</h4>
<p>In October of 2021, I had what I thought were a series of panic attacks due to a highly specific trigger of trauma that I experienced as a child.
I eventually met with a psychiatrist at my school who, upon hearing of my symptoms and pediatric mental health history, likely immediately knew that I had a dissociative disorder and recommended therapy.
They connected me with a therapist who specializes in dissociative disorders, who I started working with in January 2022.</p>
<p>At this time, I genuinely did not know what DID was. I was aware I experienced depersonalization <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, and that I had some strange psychiatric symptoms in my childhood, but I thought I was mentally healthy other than that panic associated with a trigger. I started therapy with the hopes of stopping the inconvenient &ldquo;panic attacks&rdquo;, and came in with the intention that I&rsquo;d only be in therapy for a year or so. I truly had no idea what I was signing up for.</p>
<h4 id="stage-1-denial-january--april-2022">Stage 1: Denial (January&ndash;April 2022)</h4>
<p>Upon learning that DID was my working diagnosis, the first stage was denial.
Despite the fact that I had a prior pediatric dissociative disorder diagnosis and had been experiencing symptoms of DID my entire life, I genuinely did not think I had DID.
Several parts of me believed that I was faking to get out of my adult responsibilities<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, other parts thought that DID was fake as I was matching my symptoms to the disorder because I was reading so much about it<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, and one part thought my therapist was inducing my symptoms<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
In fact, none of these excuses were correct, but the denial was protective&mdash;it prevented me, albeit momentarily, from the awareness that I had a disorder caused by childhood trauma, which I was not yet ready to to terms with.</p>
<p>During this stage, I didn&rsquo;t really even know that my symptoms were symptoms&mdash;they were normal to me, so I assumed everyone was experiencing what I did. I was switching between parts with full amnesia, but <a href="/posts/amnesia/">amnesia is tricky, and less obvious than it sounds</a>, so I genuinely didn&rsquo;t know I had any amnesia. I was emotionally numb, like I normally am, and life was a blur. During this stage, I was unaware that I was affected by a dissociative disorder because I refused to see it.</p>
<h4 id="stage-2-acceptance-april--august-2022">Stage 2: Acceptance (April&ndash;August 2022)</h4>
<p>The next stage was acceptance.
In April, I had several strange experiences that could only be explained by me having DID. I started noticing switches between parts, and became aware that my handwriting changed depending on which part of me was active. I began to accept that I actually did have a dissociative disorder, and that the mental health professionals I was working with were correct.
My symptoms starting becoming more obvious, with me realizing I experience full amnesia between parts by repeatedly finding evidence that I had done things that I had no memory of doing. I also began having more dissociative episodes, where traumatized parts would take over, but thankfully most of them occurred in therapy or while I was home alone. I began experiencing rapid switching, where I switch between parts in a quick succession in response to stress. This is a disorienting experience, which typically ends in me being very confused and having a headache.</p>
<p>However, while my symptoms starting coming to light, I could not tell apart my parts&mdash;I was sometimes able to tell when I switched, but I wouldn&rsquo;t know which part I switched to or from. This was a particularly scary stage, as I started seeing the chaos but I simultaneously had no idea what exactly was going on&mdash;how was my system structured? I had no idea&mdash;I hadn&rsquo;t had time to collect enough data yet.</p>
<h4 id="stage-3-seeing-my-parts-august-2022--march-2023">Stage 3: Seeing my parts (August 2022&ndash;March 2023)</h4>
<p>In the next stage, rather than simply seeing <em>symptoms</em>, I started seeing the <em>parts</em> underlying those symptoms.  I started being able to correlate my handwriting changes with changes in other attributes, like interests and posture. I looked back at what I remembered of my life and started being able to see what roles different parts played. I began to learn more about my system structure, and realized that I was polyfragmented.
I started assigning labels to parts that would come up frequently, and started mapping out my amnesia between parts. I sought out reasons for why my parts split in the way that they did, and why my system was so chaotic. During this time, my system was very unstable, but I internally felt fine&mdash;I was used to the chaos. I had significant lapses in memory and was trying my hardest to advance in my PhD despite this, although I was having difficulties with memory and <a href="/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/">fluctuating intelligence</a><sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.
I was still internally numb with a low dynamic range of emotions, just as I always was.</p>
<p>I was <em>seeing</em> my parts&mdash;as in, I was tracking my symptoms and assigning meaning to them&mdash;but I wasn&rsquo;t <em>connected</em> to them&mdash;I couldn&rsquo;t feel their associated emotions. I didn&rsquo;t want to feel their emotions, as I was used to being emotionally numb and enjoyed the internal stability. But in order to heal, I needed to truly connect with my parts, and that, too, came with time.</p>
<h4 id="stage-4-connecting-with-my-parts-march-2023--now">Stage 4: Connecting with my parts (March 2023&ndash;now)</h4>
<p>Finally, I believe I am in a new stage of recovery&mdash;I am beginning to truly connect with my parts and feel their associated feelings.
While I&rsquo;ve in no way fully mapped out my system or always know which part of me is active (so I&rsquo;m still also in stage 3!), my relationship with my parts has changed significantly. Rather than solely <em>observing</em> them like I was before, I&rsquo;m beginning to <em>hear</em> my parts' problems and <em>feel</em> their emotions. This has been tough&mdash;I&rsquo;m connecting with thoughts, feelings, and emotions I&rsquo;m not used to feeling, like <a href="/posts/anxiety/">anxiety</a> and <a href="/posts/anger">anger</a>. Because I&rsquo;ve been so disconnected from these emotions my entire life, I&rsquo;m genuinely not used to feeling <em>anything</em>, let alone the negative emotions that I had previously dissociated away. Most of the time, I&rsquo;m not even sure what emotions I&rsquo;m feeling&mdash;I&rsquo;m having to map sensations in my body and a general awareness that the emotion is negative and infer what I should be feeling in the situation.</p>
<p>So while I&rsquo;m in a difficult stage of recovery now, this is progress, so should be framed as good. I believe my amnesia is lessening as I&rsquo;m becoming more accepting of my parts, and I&rsquo;m also starting to connect with positive emotions. One younger part, in particular, has felt more comfortable to come out more, bringing excitement, joy, and happy memories with them. Most of my parts, however, hold a lot of fear, pain, sorrow, and anger. I can feel that my dynamic range of emotions is increasing as I&rsquo;m connecting more of my parts.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know what my healing journey will look like in the future, but I&rsquo;m happy with the progress I&rsquo;ve made thus far.
Coming to terms with having DID has been
a difficult journey and I have a long, complex healing path ahead, but I&rsquo;m hopeful for what the future will bring.</p>
<!--

I could only really tell when I did experience a switch, but I didn't know which part I was switching from or to. 
I even took the [DES-II](http://traumadissociation.com/des), a screening tool for dissociative disorders, and scored sub-threshold for PTSD, so there was no way I thought I could have DID. In reality, I had amnesia for my symptoms---if I take the test today, I would score within the range for DID. 

One day in April, I had my first experience of "rapid switching" where I was aware that I was switching---I had a blip in consciousness, and my handwriting would change. Then another blip, and my handwriting changed again. This switching happened several times, each part having 
as I switched between parts, giving me a massive headache and definitive evidence that I had DID.
which are much more subtle than it sounds, and essentially feels like a blip in cons

One year 3 months into 


But while I started being able to see my some of symptoms more clearly, I still could not tell apart my parts. 
they kept me from coming to terms with the fact that I was having the difficulties I did as an adult due to trauma I experienced as a child. 

I've experienced what I label as depersonalization since I was very small. At age 4, my mom documents me telling her that I felt like a doll, that I didn't feel real. Throughout my life, the severity of my depersonalization has fluctuated significantly.

[^4]: To me, depersonalization feels like I do not feel real---I feel floaty in my body, and, as a 4 year old me described it, "I feel like a doll". That is, I feel fake and unreal. 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>To me, when I experience depersonalization I do not feel real&mdash;I feel floaty in my body, my limbs feel heavy, and it feels like I&rsquo;m a puppet being moved around by another being. My mom reports that, as early as age 4, that I&rsquo;d tell her that I felt like a doll, and that I didn&rsquo;t feel real. I&rsquo;ve experienced depersonalization off and on with varying severity for as long as I can remember.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I started &ldquo;failing&rdquo; at my adult responsibilities when my symptoms became worse. Instead of seeing my difficulties increasing as a result of my becoming more symptomatic, I saw it as the other way around&mdash;I believed I started faking symptoms as an excuse for my failings. I now see this as being unequivocally untrue&mdash;there is no way I could be faking these symptoms. Feelings of faking are apparently very common in early stages of treatment of DID.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Upon learning that I likely had DID, I began reading as much as I possibly could about the disorder. Understanding DID became a &ldquo;special interest&rdquo; of mine, as I wanted to understand what I was apparently going through, and some parts took that as a sign I was reading about DID in order to fake it. This is also untrue.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>They definitely were not as I&rsquo;ve had symptoms of DID since before I started therapy, but a common argument of DID deniers is that it&rsquo;s therapist induced, which, in my case, is not true.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Because different parts of me were created at different times of my life and are essentially a snapshot of who I was at that time, my intelligence, and ability to grasp onto complex ideas, fluctuates depending on which part of me is active. This has been extremely difficult as a PhD student who needs to hold onto complex ideas.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/stagesofrecovery/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/stagesofrecovery/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 16:33:21 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>My stages of recovery</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>DID is very much internal disorder. That is, unless I tell you I have it, you wouldn&rsquo;t know <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. One of the ways DID affects my internal experience is that I have significant gaps in my memory, both of my past childhood, and of my present adulthood.
But amnesia is tricky&mdash;I don&rsquo;t know what I don&rsquo;t remember, so most of the time I don&rsquo;t realize I&rsquo;ve forgotten anything.</p>
<p>I believe I experience amnesia in a few ways.
The most innocuous type that I experience seems due to me having constricted awareness&mdash;each of my parts seems to act as a compartment of memory, so when I&rsquo;m in one compartment it may be difficult for me to index memories that occurred when I was in a different compartment of memory.
For example, if my partner talks about a hike we went on a few months ago when I&rsquo;m in a task-based compartment for cleaning, I may not remember the hike, but I may eventually get a very vague memory of it if they prompt me about it further. If I see a picture of us on the hike, it may help queue my memory of it more, but it still isn&rsquo;t a complete memory like it would be if I were in the compartment that was actually there on that hike.
I believe this is because hiking and cleaning occupy two entirely different compartments of my life; there&rsquo;s little in common between the two, and my constricted awareness makes it so that these memories aren&rsquo;t shared well between the two parts. This seems to be a version of state-dependent memory.</p>
<p>I also experience full amnesia between parts. That is, I will not have access to any of the memories of one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This typically seems to occur between compartments that hold trauma memories and ones that do not, but I also seem to experience this between non-trauma holding parts, and I&rsquo;m not yet sure why.</p>
<p>Within full amnesia, I seem to exhibit two types. The first is when I experience a discrete jump in my awareness when I switch between compartments where I have no idea what was happening just before the switch. This causes an obvious jump in my awareness, and may make it more noticeable that I have amnesia. I might find myself, all of a sudden, in a different room than I remember being in just a second ago, when in reality another part had moved me to that room outside of my awareness<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I experienced this when I was younger<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, but not as much as I&rsquo;ve gotten older. Now, I more so seem to have a sliding-window type memory&mdash;rather than a discrete jump in awareness, my memory of what happened gradually disappears over several minutes after a switch. This leads to a perceived smoother transition between parts, making my memory loss less obvious to me.</p>
<p>Regardless of the type of amnesia I have, I experience shuffling of memories and time jumps&mdash;I do not have a continuous, linear understanding of my life. For example, it may be hard for me to differentiate what occurred last week vs what occurred years ago, and sometimes things that occurred months ago feel more current to me than things that occurred even yesterday. As always, this seems to be justified by my understanding of how I operate&mdash;if I&rsquo;m in a compartment of memory that was last active a few months ago, those memories are more at the forefront of my awareness than memories formed in a different compartment yesterday.
This leads to a lot of confusing experiences, like looking out of my window and expecting it to be winter but seeing that it&rsquo;s actually summer, or all of a sudden noticing that the furniture in my apartment has moved from what I last remember, or looking at my plants and being amazed by how much they had grown because I remembered them being much smaller.
These sorts of experiences occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still early on in my DID discovery journey, so my understanding of my amnesia will likely change over time as I learn more about how I operate.
I hope this post serves as a snapshot in time of my awareness of how I operate a little over one year after starting therapy.</p>
<!--

How does one know if the way they experience the world is _normal_? It never even occurred to me that aspects my experience could be considered disordered until recently. Now that I'm aware, so much of my life makes sense. 

The way I experience amnesia seems to be more nuanced than what I have described here thus far, but I haven't formulated the words to fully describe these experiences yet.


These experiences can be explained by me switching between compartments of memory that I haven't been in in a while, and occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.

Another type of amnesia that some people with dissociative disorders report[^3] is emotional amnesia, where they remember the events of what happened when they're in a different compartment, but don't have the associated emotions attached with that memory. I believe I experience this too, but because of the structure of my DID, I believe almost all of my memories do not have associated emotions attached to them[^6]. This seems to be my normal memory, so for me 
the distinction between experiencing emotional amnesia or having a "normal" memory isn't clear. I don't believe I often experience strong emotions[^4], though, so I'm not sure if I'm experiencing some sort of amnesia or if I just don't have the associated emotions to encode in my memories. 
[^4]: I don't remember what I don't remember, so maybe I do experience strong emotions more than I think; I'm honestly not sure.
[^3]: I learned about this from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit
[^6]: Also, most, if not all, of my memories seem to be in third person, even if they aren't trauma related. This may be why I don't have the first-person perspective of emotion attached to them.


In fact, one way I can differentiate between my parts is by 

it isn't clear if I could be experiencing something different.

so out of context for a part of me that cleans because it seems like a different section of my life.

I personally see myself as having three types of amnesia.

This memory will not be clear, and often has a "not me" feeling associated with it---it can feel like I'm indexing someone else's memories

I'm used to living with a constricted internal awareness that realizing I have amensia isn't surprising to me much anymore---it seems to be a normal part of my 

I'm only aware I'm in a different compartment when looking back in time. In the moment-to-moment, I always feel like _me_. That is; my sense of "I" does not change. This is why I like to conceptualize my experience as me switching between different compartments rather than 

Now that I know what switching feels like, I realize that I have day-to-day amnesia. 

When I look backat the 

I also often have the experience of 
Memory is tricky. When I think about my life, I am unaware I have amnesia

My whole life, I've had experiences where people claimed I had done things I had absolutely no memory of doing. These things seemed like things I would absolutely never do, and to be honest, I never thought too much about it.

In high school, I saw the same group of friends in class that I did outside of school. I clearly had different parts 

So now, looking back, of course I had amnesia. However, it's a lot more hidden than one would expect, because I simply do not remember what I do not remember. It's only when I have external sources notifying me that something happened that I didn't remember do I realize I must have had amnesia. 

It's honestly really scary know that I could potentially forget what I am doing right now in the future. How much of my life will I remember? Are these memories I'm making in my life encoding properly? I sure hope so---I don't want gaps in my memory.

With that being said, because I truly don't know what I don't know, I'm often not aware I'm missing anything.

My justification for these events was always that the other person was lying,

Is it amnesia proper, or is it just my awareness is so shuffled since I switch between many different compartments of memory in a day? 

At the end of the day, when my partner and I ask each other how our days were, I can typically give him a general impression of how the day went---I remember the major events 



One of the hardest parts of my DID discovery journey is coming to terms that I did, in fact, do those things. I had dissociated---putting me in a different compartment of awareness with a different mindset.

Who I thought I was is not who I actually was. Some parts 

I have difficulties tracking the passage of time. 
When I wake up in the morning, I have to orient myself to what day it 
Because I have so many different parts with varying levels of memory sharing between them, there are times where I won't know what I'm doing moment-to-moment.
the way I encoded and accessed memories was different from most others

In this case, it's not that I don't remember what happened when I was in a different compartment. 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Unless you catch me in a dissociative episode, which is very unlikely to happen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, I have never had a full dissociative fugue where I end up in an entirely different location than I was before. Most of my dissociative episodes occur at home, so the scariest thing might be I find myself hiding under the blanets of my bed when I thought I was in my kitchen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This, along with other symptoms, led to me receiving a dissociative disorder diagnosis as a pre-teen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/amnesia/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/amnesia/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 12:10:19 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative amnesia</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Imagine if, without your awareness, your deepest, most repressed thoughts and feelings were displayed for the world to see. With how my DID presents, this is something that occurs quite frequently for me. Because much of my most difficult emotions are separated from the core me, I am usually unaware of them until they surface and they&rsquo;re in the forefront of my awareness. Then, after they are over, I may forget that these dissociative episodes ever happened. This has led to me into many scary and sometimes dangerous situations, which typically leave me puzzled by what is happening in the world around me.</p>
<p>As an example, I like to go on evening walks for exercise. I typically walk one of a few routes in the densely populated city I live in. One day this past summer, I walked by a person who had some of the same characteristics as someone who caused me harm in the past. I walked by this individual without awareness that I was at all triggered. Then, in a split second, they started yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&rsquo;re scared of me, huh? What do you have to be scared about?&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>What?</em> It was so out of context for me; I had no idea why they were yelling at me. I wasn&rsquo;t scared of them&mdash;up until they started yelling at me, I hadn&rsquo;t even noticed them. I ignored them and calmly kept walking in the direction I was going. Then, they started moving towards me <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, continually yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why are you scared of me? You think I&rsquo;m threatening? There&rsquo;s nothing to be scared about!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I sped up walking and continued ignoring them. I felt very calm while this was happening, although I was confused by what going on. I eventually made it to the next block over and lost sight of them. I calmly walked home, and went out of my way to reassure myself that I had done nothing wrong, and that the person was at fault, not me. But <em>why</em> did this person think I was scared of them? Was I scared of them?</p>
<p>As it turns out, a part of me <em>was</em> scared of them. When I saw that person, that part became so scared, that they momentarily took control of my face and made a scared microexpression, directed at that person. However, I had no awareness that I was scared of them or that I had made any facial expression. This is because the parts of me who were on my evening walk were not connected with the part of me that was scared of the person, so from the perspective of the part of me that was going on a walk, I had no idea that anything abnormal was happening, while the scared part was simultaneously terrified.</p>
<p>Over the next few days, I intentionally went on my evening walk, purposefully walking past the location of the event to ensure I didn&rsquo;t associate anything negative with it. The parts of me walking felt perfectly fine, and I didn&rsquo;t realize anything was off.
Then, within a week, without realizing it, I stopped going on my evening walks. A month went by, and I still avoided walking, but it didn&rsquo;t even occur to me that I stopped.
I went from walking every day for months to only leaving my apartment when absolutely necessary. I didn&rsquo;t feel any fear associated with walking or leaving my apartment, but it was clearly there, dictating my behavior. It took over a month for me to realize anything was wrong, and once I pondered why I was no longer walking the reason became obvious&mdash;a part of me was still clearly scared of what had happened on that walk.
In order to get back to my walking routine, I gradually had to show that part that we were safe, and that that wasn&rsquo;t going to happen again, and even if it did, there were other parts who could take care of the situation like we had done last time. With this awareness in mind, over time, I managed to get back to going on my evening walks.</p>
<p>This is one example of how having DID affects my life and functioning. Before I became aware that I have DID, I was unaware of how much influence my parts had over my life. My behaviors are influenced by fear I cannot even grasp onto or feel. Other people may be more aware of my own internal state than even I am, since my body language may be contradictory to how I feel on the inside.
Getting to know my parts is helping me to become more aware of my internal state, and, in turn, will allow me to live a more complete life.</p>
<!--



It's not that I as a whole am not experiencing this fear; rather I simply am not connected with it. 


_Yeah, sure. You're chasing and yelling at me. Clearly there's something to be scared about_.
---my months long routine of going on an eveng walk ended, and I genuinely didn't even notice. I felt no fear associated with walking, but my behavior was controlled by the fear of that event occurring again, held by a part of me who wasn't connected with the core me.

About a month into stopping, I suddenly realized that I hadn't gone on a walk in a long time.
However, beyond my awareness, a part was terrified.  

 being mindful of my surroundings. I forced myself to walk past the location of the event again, trying to disassociate it with fear. 

I feel as though this is a classic example for how I ---my deepest emotions and fears, that I am not even aware of, can show up on my face for others to see without me even realizing it. 
One of the ways I experience DID is that the parts of me who hold onto traumatic memories and emotions are separated from the parts of me who 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, they used a walker, so I was in little danger.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/partscontrol/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/partscontrol/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:30:21 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>The parts I don’t know about still have control</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was initially hesitant to write about anger, as it&rsquo;s an emotion I am not used to feeling<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
How could I write about something I know nothing about?
But I now realize that the absence of anger in my life is significant in itself, and is indicative of how I operate.</p>
<p>Anger is an emotion that I am simultaneously very familiar with, yet not at all familar with&mdash;I am incredibly sensitive to the external display of anger in others, yet not at all familiar with how it feels internally.
I believe this is because when I was small, I grew up in an environment where my primary caregiver frequently displayed anger.
This is because they had unprocessed trauma of their own, which came out as fits of rage.
These bouts of anger were extremely terrifying for me as a young child, and ended in emotional and sometimes physical harm done to me.
Because of the repeated association of anger with terror, pain, and instability, I believe I learned to internally separate anger as a &ldquo;bad&rdquo; emotion, and shoved it away as an emotion that I did not want to experience.
My relationship with anger was tainted by my early childhood experiences, making a powerful emotion that should be utilized as part of an emotionally healthy life inaccessible to me as an adult.</p>
<p>I once naively believed that not feeling anger was an asset of mine&mdash;that anger was a disruptive emotion, and it was safer for me not to feel it. While it is beneficial to those around me for me to not ever display anger, I now believe that anger is an important emotion that should be part of my emotional repertoire.
Anger enables people to enact change. By my not being able to experience anger, I&rsquo;m more likely to stay involved in situations and environments which are not good for me, making me to be more likely to be repeatedly victimized.
Due to my upbringing, I learned to value other peoples' comfort over my own, and use dissociation to subconsciously withhold my sometimes justified anger.</p>
<p>I believe that because I have DID<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, my dynamic range of emotions is very shallow&mdash;most of the time, I feel mild contentment. I grew up in an environment where I didn&rsquo;t feel like I could take up any emotional space, as the emotional landscape in my family of origin was dominated by others' strong emotional displays. I enjoy my internal stability&mdash;I do not want to feel strong emotions. I am scared of the loss of control I was so used to seeing in others while growing up.
However, this separation of anger and other emotions leads to a less full life, including amnesia, behavior that feels out of my control when I&rsquo;m triggered, along with stunted &ldquo;good&rdquo; emotions, like happiness and excitement. By using dissociation, I&rsquo;ve traded experiencing a full range of emotions for internal stability. This served me well in the past, but in the future I&rsquo;d like to live a more full, complete life&mdash;one that does not rely on maladaptive dissociative coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>While I now see anger as a valuable emotion, my learned patterns of removing it from my awareness continue, so still I have difficulty accessing it.
My understanding of anger comes from a theoretical view&mdash;I can intellectually understand it, but I do not believe I have felt genuine anger before. With time, I hope that will change.</p>
<!--


## THIS POST NEEDS TO BE REWORKED
But I now realize that the absence of anger in my life is significant in itself, and is indicative of how my underlying dissociative defense system operates.
Anger is an emotion I learned to dissociate away from a very young age. 

---it can be the driving force required to get one out of bad situations


Because of this, I learned to associate anger with terror and instability, and internally decided that anger was an emotion I did not want to experience.






I do not believe I have ever experienced anger before.

 Like anxiety, anger is an emotion I have dissociated away. However, unlike anxiety, which I do experience, I do not believe I have ever experienced true anger before.


Anger is an emotion I am not acquainted with. 

My mom tells me she's only seen me angry twice in my life---both involved her doing things to my cat without getting permission. In these cases, I'm sure I was acting to protect my cat, but I do not fully remember either incident. It would be too destabilizing for me to realize that 

I have been trained to be very sensitive to the signs of anger in others---


I am very familiar with anger as expressed by others. 



My understanding of anger comes from a theoretical view---I can intellectually understand it, but I do not believe I have ever felt anger before. 

I have a rudimentary understanding of anger. 


I understand why anger is important
It can be the driving force one needs to fight against harm or injustice done to them.

change one's situation

Anger is a powerful emotion. It can help one to enact change in their life, 
The absense of anger in my life 

Rather than feeling angry about something

I do not feel anger, because it was modeled to me as an unstable 

My mother could not control her anger. It was an emotion she turned to frequently, and her emotions 

I am very unfamiliar with anger

I do not believe I have ever felt anger before. I believe this is common 
It may be hypocritical for me to write a post on an emotion that I am so unfamiliar with. 


My dynamic range of emotions is very shallow---most of the time, I feel mild contentment. 
I grew up in an environment where I didn't feel like I could take up any emotional space, as the emotional landscape in my family of origin was dominated by others' strong emotional displays. 

I enjoy my internal stability---I do not want to feel strong emotions. I am scared of the loss of control I was so used to seeing while growing up. 

those around me dominated the emotional landscape. 
I do not have much experience with strong emotions, 


I have never experienced strong emotions
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>And maybe I was right to be hesitant, as I don&rsquo;t have much to say since I&rsquo;m early in my awareness journey, but I want to document my understanding of things at various stages of healing.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I believe I am this way due to how I responded to experiences in my childhood, which resulted in me forming maladaptive coping mechanisms which can be labeled DID.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/anger/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/anger/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 11:05:58 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anger</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12, I stopped feeling anxiety. Prior to that, I was a child ravished by anxiety. Then, one day, it stopped <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. And I have never experienced anxiety in the same way since.</p>
<p>I now understand that anxiety is one of the experiences that I dissociated away&mdash;it&rsquo;s a state that I did not enjoy experiencing, so I learned how to compartmentalize it and push it out of my awareness.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean I do not <em>experience</em> anxiety; rather, it means that when I do, I am so detached from it that I do not experience all aspects of it.</p>
<p>My body trembles, lower lip quivers, and heart races, yet I don&rsquo;t know why I am experiencing these physical symptoms.
My mind races with irrational thought loops, yet I can&rsquo;t quite grasp onto them so they feel like meaningless noise to me.
I am disconnected and emotionally numb. Except for when I am not.</p>
<p>When I am able to connect with the feeling of anxiety, it is all-encompassing and feels everlasting. When something triggers anxiety to the forefront of my awareness, it is all I can concentrate on, and I will do whatever I need to do to alleviate the feeling. Then, all of a sudden, it goes away as quickly as it came, and after it&rsquo;s over I gradually forget that it ever happened.</p>
<p>Right now, as I write this, I do not know what anxiety feels like. Parts of me do, but I am not connected with those parts. For the most part, I feel like an emotionless machine, going through the motions of life. Despite the fact that I&rsquo;m unable to connect with anxiety, that doesn&rsquo;t mean it doesn&rsquo;t affect me. My behaviors are controlled by fear and anxiety that I cannot feel&mdash;I can only intellectually infer that I am being affected by anxiety by examining my behaviors. I avoid leaving my apartment, interacting with others, and doing things that may eventually lead to stressful situations. Yet I do not experience the associated emotions with these behaviors&mdash;I am numb.</p>
<p>When I was 12, I didn&rsquo;t become a less anxious person&mdash;I just became more detached from my anxiety. My crippling anxiety wasn&rsquo;t miraculously cured. Instead, it was like fixing a wound that needed stitches with a band-aid&mdash;an easy, temporary solution that left me worse-off in the long term.</p>
<p>In order to decrease my amnesia and regain control of my life, I need to connect back with my anxiety.
Although it allows me to avoid difficult feelings in the moment, my current method of dealing with anxiety&mdash;compartmentalizing it and shoving it from my awareness&mdash;leads to uncontrollable fear-based behavior, a lack of internal awareness, and amnesia. I need to connect with this destabilizing experience once again, this time working though it instead of shoving it from my awareness. Then, I can address its root causes and gain control of my life again.</p>
<!--

I have a very curated internal experience---emotionally, I feel 

The irrational thought loops 
At least not in a normal way anymore. 

DID shapes the way I experience emotions.

Different aspects of my life are compartmentalized 

When I was a child, I was filled with worry. 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My mom reports me having a discrete personality change when this occurred.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/anxiety/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/anxiety/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 19:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anxiety</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have always been nerdy. From a young age, I immersed myself in academic work, as I enjoyed learning and the strict routine that school provided for me. I also had an intense need to perform well&mdash;my perfectionistic tendencies dominated my life as a child. While I often did perform well academically, there were times where I performed markedly poorly on assessments, so far outside the norm of what would have ordinarily be expected of me, despite preparing and knowing the material. For example, on one occasion in high school, I was so prepared for an exam that I helped tutor my friends about the material leading up to it, only for me to fail while they performed well. I wasn&rsquo;t ordinarily a bad test taker&mdash;I genuinely didn&rsquo;t understand the material when exam time came. To put it simply, there were times when I was smart, and times when I was&hellip; not. I  now understand this to be as a result of having DID.</p>
<p>Some of my parts were formed when I was a small child. When I am in these compartments, although I may be aware that I am an adult, I typically have the mental ability of around the age in which those parts developed. These compartments are essentially snapshots of my mindset at the time they were created, with varying levels of awareness of the present day. One major implication of this is that my ability to understand information varies depending on which compartment of awareness I am in. For example, I have a younger, very timid part that sometimes comes out that has the math ability of a middle schooler. When this part is active, I am unable to grasp onto the complex topics required of me for my PhD that I can normally do with relative ease when the right part of me is active. I am not aware of what I do not know, believing what I know in that moment is all that I do know. This part of me often comes out around others while I&rsquo;m supposed to be having intellectual discussions. The results are humiliating&mdash;I am unable to discuss even my own research, which the right parts of me are very familiar with. Many a time I have left a meeting feeling absolutely defeated and frustrated that I was unable to discuss my research properly. However, there were other times, when the correct parts were out, that I was very much able to hold an academic discussion about my work. My fluctuating knowledge of my work has detrimentally impacted my academic career thus far.</p>
<p>Before I knew I had DID, I never questioned my fluctuating levels of intelligence. However, I did come up with a justification for my poor performance&mdash;when I was in compartments that weren&rsquo;t aware of my more academic parts, I truly believed that I was dumber than all of my peers. I believed that any time I had performed well I had cheated, and I had faked my way to where I am today as a PhD student. There are times where I&rsquo;d look at my academic papers, ones that I had written, and not only did I not understand what the material was about, but I didn&rsquo;t fully remember writing them. I developed extreme imposter syndrome as a result of this&mdash;I truly didn&rsquo;t feel like I belonged in my institution, and I believed that I had genuine reasons as to why.</p>
<p>It has only been within the last several months that I&rsquo;ve been able to identify when I&rsquo;m in a compartment of awareness that is not necessarily able to understand the material required of me in order to complete my degree, and I now see that the difference in ability is pronounced. When this part of me is active, I now stop working and try to understand why it is out. What is preventing me from accessing the compartments of me that do work? Sometimes the answer is obvious; other times, I&rsquo;m not so sure. Most frequently, however, I don&rsquo;t realize that a non-academic part has been out until after it has already gone, when I relook at a problem that I was previously agonizing over and it becomes obvious. I&rsquo;m still trying to understand these parts of myself, but just knowing that my having DID explains much of my academic distress really helps me understand why I am the way that I am.</p>
<!--


, but now that I'm aware of the problem, I see the path forward in how to improve.

Becoming aware that I have DID has offered a much-needed explanation for why my brain works in this way. 

## THIS POST NEEDS TO BE REWORKED
talk more about the disconnect between feeling smart vs not smart. pompous part too.

The divide between aspects of life that are hard to hold together. fault lines between parts of self.


In a PhD program[^1], other than one's thesis defense that is the capstone of their degree, the qualifying exam is the most important test of one's degree. The qualifying exam typically occurs a year or two into the degree, and is meant to assess if one is qualified to continue in the PhD program. What exactly a qualifying exam consists of differs from school to school, and department to department. In my program, my qualifying exam was a "chalk talk"---you choose three topics of concentration, and three experts on those fields will ask you questions which you answer on the chalk board. They assess your responses and determine if you're qualified to continue in the degree.

[^1]: Ones I am familiar with in the USA.


In high school. I wasn't aware I had DID. But looking back with the awareness I now have, there are many instances of fluctuating intelligence that can be perfectly explained by having DID. My freshman year, I had a turbulent home environment


For example, in high school, there were times where I'd teach my friends material that would be on the exam, and then I'd do poorly on the exam while they would do well.

My qualifying exam


I do not have access to my full set of knowledge and skills, and 
When this part of me is active

I can feel the intelligence differential between myself and others around me. Over time, when I was in that compartment 



There are some things in life that just made so much more sense after I realized I had DID. Probably the most frustrating one was my fluctuating intelligence. This explained how I could teach my friends the material for a math exam and subsequently fail it while my friends did well. 

I have a complicated relationship with academics.
As a PhD student, 

One of the most frustrating symptoms that falls under the category of _symptoms I've had my entire life but didn't realize_ is flucutating intelligence.

My intelligence, 

This is, perhaps, one of the most frustrating parts of having DID.
-->
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 21:52:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Fluctuating intelligence</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Pretty early on in my DID discovery journey, I realized that my handwriting was different depending on which part of me was writing. This was very useful information, as I had taken well-catalogued academic notes for years prior to starting therapy, so I had a solid bank of data of which I could look back on and see which parts of me were active at different times of my life.</p>
<p>One thing I quickly noticed was that any time I traveled to a conference, my handwriting changed. And then when I got back, my handwriting changed back to whatever was normal at that time of my life <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
Internally, this also made sense&mdash;I tend to index my life by location rather than time. In fact, in all of my notebooks' index sections, I had added a column for location, in addition to the standard page number and date. My mind likes segmenting my life based on location.</p>
<p>Why could this be the case? Why do I create parts when I travel? Looking back at my life story, it actually makes a lot of sense.
My first several years of life involved a lot of traveling. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad&rsquo;s job.
As a perk of being an expat, my dad&rsquo;s job paid for two vacations a year&mdash;one for rest and relaxation, and another to visit family.
Because of this, by my 5th birthday, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips.</p>
<p>This sounds like an incredibly fortunate childhood, and while it was, it was also very stressful for me.
As an autistic person, I regulate myself by following a strict routine. As an adult, changes in plans are very dysregulating, and usually leave me in a detached dissociated state with difficulty picking up the newly created plans.
I can only imagine how dysregulating it was for me as a small child to have my routine entirely upended every several months to travel to a new environment with an unknown routine.
I had no option&mdash;my family chose to travel, and since within my family structure the emotional landscape was already dominated by others, I had to be an easy child and submit to whatever they wanted. This led to me dissociating and creating parts to handle the traveling for me.</p>
<p>This past summer, I went to my first conference while aware that I create parts this way.
The night leading up to the event, I remember absolutely dreading the trip, wishing I could back out but knowing that I couldn&rsquo;t. Then, when the time came, I genuinely enjoyed the conference&mdash;the right part showed up for the job. I did seem to create a part for this trip, and this was the first part that I was self-aware I was creating. I had no control over it; instead, I observed its creation as I walked into the hotel lobby to check in. A new persona emerged, and was ready to take on whatever routine was required of me for my week-long conference that was just getting started. With that part as the dominant part, other parts came out periodically to do what was required of me, like networking, socializing, and presenting. But this newly created part was the star of the show, helping me create a solid routine I could stick to throughout the week to help keep me regulated. Then, on the last day, once again the dread came&mdash;this time, I, as the newly created part, didn&rsquo;t want to change my routine back again as I was only familiar with the one I had created. However, when I arrived in my apartment after a long journey back, a different part switched in and I was so glad to be home and back again in my standard routine.</p>
<p>We traveled to many beautiful locations in my early childhood, and I truly appreciate all the culturally enriching experiences I acquired, which I believe to this day have helped shaped my worldview. I do, however, wish that my parents were more aware of how stressful this was for me as a child. I did not understand the significance of the locations we would visit, and felt as though I was being dragged from place to place without understanding what was going on around me. In pictures of our family vacations, it&rsquo;s clear that I am dissociating&mdash;many of them show me with a blank expression with my eyes glazed over. I learned to regulate myself by dissociating, detaching from the world around me. And these repeated experiences of traveling = part creation have continued throughout my life, increasingly fragmenting my awareness when I take trips.</p>
<p>I believe this is a good example of how trauma, but not necessarily abuse, can lead to the formation of DID.
I would not consider traveling as much as we did abuse, but it was traumatic because it was too much for me to handle at the developmental stages it occurred in.
One could argue that this was neglect or negligence&mdash;that my parents weren&rsquo;t attuned to my emotional needs at the time.
However, it does not fit into the category of extreme abuse that is often attributed to the creation of DID.
While I do not believe this was the only trauma that caused me to form DID, and some of those traumas would be considered abuse,
traveling in the way that we did when I was small had a major impact on how I create parts, and is perhaps the most influential mechanism of part creation in my adult life.</p>
<!--

One part of me is very grateful that I had traveled so much in my childhood because that meant that I had already seen everything I would ever to in life and would never have to travel again. That part of me sees vacations a check box to complete, rather than an experience to enjoy. This line of thinking was influenced by the stress I 


 I, as the newly created part, did not want to change my routine back again.

I was a very well traveled child, and while I used to think of this as an amazing opportunity 
I even in my adult life, and is perhaps the most influential 


One could argue that this was neglect, not abuse.


With that being said, in my adult life at least, I do enjoy vacations---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.

One part of me was very happy that I had traveled so much as a child because that would mean that I wouldn't 
My understanding of vacations was that they were a check box to complete, rather than an experience to enjoy.
With that being said, I did enjoy them---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.
With that being said, I did enjoy them---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.

I did not understand the significance of the locations I was being 


My system is very chaotic---I seem to split parts in complex 

As I understand it, one can create parts to respond to stressors in their environment.

To me, traveling is stressful. And incredibly unpredictable. When I was young, I didn't know what was going on in the environment around me as my parents moved me from landmark to landmark that I didn't understand the significance of. 

By the time I was 5 years old, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips. I did not understand the significance of the locations I was being 

One of the first mechanisms of creating parts 

I have kept detailed work journals for 
Something I've always done 

At first, it didn't make sense to me 
Over time, it became obvious why.


As a polyfragmented system, I seem to split parts
Early into my discovery journey, something puzzled me. I learned pretty quicky 

My first several years of life were very chaotic. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad's job. 
For my whole life up to that point, while my handwriting was floridly changing, I never had questioned it or honestly really noticed it. Now, I am very thankful that I have a solid visual indicator for which parts of me were active at different times of my life.
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My handwriting isn&rsquo;t usually discretely clear, and is often a blend of many different parts' handwritings. However, on several trips my handwriting made a clear enough change for me to notice this pattern.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/traveling/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/traveling/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 22:14:57 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Parts are created from trauma, not necessarily abuse</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
