







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="https://example.com/tags/narrative/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>narrative</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>https://example.com/tags/narrative/</link>
        
        
            <title>narrative</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12, I stopped feeling anxiety. Prior to that, I was a child ravished by anxiety. Then, one day, it stopped <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. And I have never experienced anxiety in the same way since.</p>
<p>I now understand that anxiety is one of the experiences that I dissociated away&mdash;it&rsquo;s a state that I did not enjoy experiencing, so I learned how to compartmentalize it and push it out of my awareness.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean I do not <em>experience</em> anxiety; rather, it means that when I do, I am so detached from it that I do not experience all aspects of it.</p>
<p>My body trembles, lower lip quivers, and heart races, yet I don&rsquo;t know why I am experiencing these physical symptoms.
My mind races with irrational thought loops, yet I can&rsquo;t quite grasp onto them so they feel like meaningless noise to me.
I am disconnected and emotionally numb. Except for when I am not.</p>
<p>When I am able to connect with the feeling of anxiety, it is all-encompassing and feels everlasting. When something triggers anxiety to the forefront of my awareness, it is all I can concentrate on, and I will do whatever I need to do to alleviate the feeling. Then, all of a sudden, it goes away as quickly as it came, and after it&rsquo;s over I gradually forget that it ever happened.</p>
<p>Right now, as I write this, I do not know what anxiety feels like. Parts of me do, but I am not connected with those parts. For the most part, I feel like an emotionless machine, going through the motions of life. Despite the fact that I&rsquo;m unable to connect with anxiety, that doesn&rsquo;t mean it doesn&rsquo;t affect me. My behaviors are controlled by fear and anxiety that I cannot feel&mdash;I can only intellectually infer that I am being affected by anxiety by examining my behaviors. I avoid leaving my apartment, interacting with others, and doing things that may eventually lead to stressful situations. Yet I do not experience the associated emotions with these behaviors&mdash;I am numb.</p>
<p>When I was 12, I didn&rsquo;t become a less anxious person&mdash;I just became more detached from my anxiety. My crippling anxiety wasn&rsquo;t miraculously cured. Instead, it was like fixing a wound that needed stitches with a band-aid&mdash;an easy, temporary solution that left me worse-off in the long term.</p>
<p>In order to decrease my amnesia and regain control of my life, I need to connect back with my anxiety.
My current method of dealing with anxiety&mdash;compartmentalizing it and shoving it from my awareness&mdash;leads to uncontrollable fear-based behavior, a lack of internal awareness, and amnesia. I need to connect with this destabilizing experience once again, this time working though it instead of shoving it from my awareness. Then, I can address its root causes and gain control of my life again.</p>
<!--

The irrational thought loops 
At least not in a normal way anymore. 

DID shapes the way I experience emotions.

Different aspects of my life are compartmentalized 

When I was a child, I was filled with worry. 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My mom reports me having a discrete personality change when this occurred.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/anxiety/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/anxiety/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 19:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anxiety</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have always been nerdy. From a young age, I immersed myself in academic work, as I enjoyed learning and the strict routine that school provided for me. I also had an intense need to perform well&mdash;my perfectionistic tendencies dominated my life as a child. While I often did perform well academically, there were times where I performed markedly poorly on assessments, so far outside the norm of what would have ordinarily be expected of me, despite preparing and knowing the material. For example, one one occasion in high school, I was so prepared for an exam that I helped tutor my friends about the material leading up to it, only for me to fail while they performed well. I wasn&rsquo;t ordinarily a bad test taker&mdash;I genuinely didn&rsquo;t understand the material when exam time came. To put it simply, there were times when I was smart, and times when I was&hellip; not. I  now understand this to be as a result of having DID.</p>
<p>Some of my parts were formed when I was a small child. When I am in these compartments, although I may be aware that I am an adult, I typically have the mental ability of around the age in which those parts developed. These compartments are essentially snapshots of my mindset at the time, with varying levels of awareness of the present day. One major implication of this is that my ability to understand information varies depending on which compartment of awareness I am in. For example, I have a younger, very timid part that sometimes comes out that has the math ability of a middle schooler. When this part is active, I am unable to grasp onto the complex topics required of me for my PhD that I can normally do with relative ease when the right part of me is active. I am not aware of what I do not know, believing what I know in that moment is all that I do know. This part of me often comes out around others while I&rsquo;m supposed to be having intellectual discussions. The results are humiliating&mdash;I am unable to discuss even my own research, which the right parts of me are very familiar with. Many a time I have left a meeting feeling absolutely defeated and frustrated that I was unable to discuss my research properly. However, there were other times, when the correct parts were out, that I was very much able to hold an academic discussion about my work. Becoming aware that I have DID has offered a much-needed explanation for why my brain works in this way.</p>
<p>Before I knew I had DID, I never questioned my fluctuating levels of intelligence. However, I did come up with a justification for my poor performance&mdash;when I was in compartments that weren&rsquo;t aware of my more academic parts, I truly believed that I was dumber than all of my peers. That, somehow, any time I had performed well I had cheated, and I faked my way to where I am today as a PhD student. There are times where I&rsquo;d look at my academic papers, ones that I had written, and not only did I not understand what the material was about, but I didn&rsquo;t fully remember writing them. I developed extreme imposter syndrome as a result of this&mdash;I truly didn&rsquo;t feel like I belonged in my institution, and I believed that I had genuine reasons as to why.</p>
<p>It has only been within the last several months that I&rsquo;ve been able to identify when I&rsquo;m in a compartment of awareness that is not necessarily able to understand the material required of me in order to complete my degree, and I now see that the difference in ability is pronounced. When this part of me is active, I now stop working and try to understand why it is out. What is preventing me from accessing the compartments of me that do work? Sometimes the answer is obvious; other times, I&rsquo;m not so sure. I&rsquo;m still trying to understand these parts of myself, but just knowing that my having DID explains much of my academic distress really helps me understand why I am the way that I am.</p>
<!--


In a PhD program[^1], other than one's thesis defense that is the capstone of their degree, the qualifying exam is the most important test of one's degree. The qualifying exam typically occurs a year or two into the degree, and is meant to assess if one is qualified to continue in the PhD program. What exactly a qualifying exam consists of differs from school to school, and department to department. In my program, my qualifying exam was a "chalk talk"---you choose three topics of concentration, and three experts on those fields will ask you questions which you answer on the chalk board. They assess your responses and determine if you're qualified to continue in the degree.

[^1]: Ones I am familiar with in the USA.


In high school. I wasn't aware I had DID. But looking back with the awareness I now have, there are many instances of fluctuating intelligence that can be perfectly explained by having DID. My freshman year, I had a turbulent home environment


For example, in high school, there were times where I'd teach my friends material that would be on the exam, and then I'd do poorly on the exam while they would do well.

My qualifying exam


I do not have access to my full set of knowledge and skills, and 
When this part of me is active

I can feel the intelligence differential between myself and others around me. Over time, when I was in that compartment 



There are some things in life that just made so much more sense after I realized I had DID. Probably the most frustrating one was my fluctuating intelligence. This explained how I could teach my friends the material for a math exam and subsequently fail it while my friends did well. 

I have a complicated relationship with academics.
As a PhD student, 

One of the most frustrating symptoms that falls under the category of _symptoms I've had my entire life but didn't realize_ is flucutating intelligence.

My intelligence, 

This is, perhaps, one of the most frustrating parts of having DID.
-->
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 21:52:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Fluctuating intelligence</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Pretty early on in my DID discovery journey, I realized that my handwriting was different depending on which part of me was writing. This was very useful information, as I had taken well-catalogued academic notes for years prior to starting therapy, so I had a solid bank of data of which I could look back on and see which parts of me were active at different times of my life.</p>
<p>One thing I quickly noticed was that any time I traveled to a conference, my handwriting changed. And then when I got back, my handwriting changed back to whatever was normal at that time of my life <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
Internally, this also made sense&mdash;I tend to index my life by location rather than time. In fact, in all of my notebooks' index sections, I had added a column for location, in addition to the standard page number and date. My mind likes segmenting my life based on location.</p>
<p>Why could this be the case? Why do I create parts when I travel? Looking back at my life story, it actually makes a lot of sense.
My first several years of life involved a lot of traveling. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad&rsquo;s job.
As a perk of being an expat, my dad&rsquo;s job paid for two vacations a year&mdash;one for rest and relaxation, and another to visit family.
Because of this, by my 5th birthday, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips.</p>
<p>This sounds like an incredibly fortunate childhood, and while it was, it was also very stressful for me.
As an autistic person, I regulate myself by following a strict routine. As an adult, changes in plans are very dysregulating, and usually leave me in a detached dissociated state with difficulty picking up the newly created plans.
I can only imagine how dysregulating it was for me as a small child to have my routine entirely upended every several months to travel to a new environment with an unknown routine.
I had no option&mdash;my family chose to travel, and since within my family structure the emotional landscape was already dominated by others, I had to be an easy child and submit to whatever they wanted. This led to me dissociating and creating parts to handle the traveling for me.</p>
<p>This past summer, I went to my first conference while aware that I create parts this way.
The night leading up to the event, I remember absolutely dreading the trip, wishing I could back out but knowing that I couldn&rsquo;t. Then, when the time came, I genuinely enjoyed the conference&mdash;the right part showed up for the job. I did, in fact, create a part for this trip, and this was the first part that I was self-aware I was creating. I had no control over it; instead, I observed its creation as I walked into the hotel lobby to check in. A new persona emerged, and was ready to take on whatever routine was required of me for my week-long conference that was just getting started. With that part as the dominant part, other parts came out periodically to do what was required of me, like networking, socializing, and presenting. But this newly created part was the star of the show, helping me create a solid routine I could stick to throughout the week to help keep me regulated. Then, on the last day, once again the dread came&mdash;this time, I, as the newly created part, didn&rsquo;t want to change my routine back again as I was only familiar with the one I had created. However, when I arrived in my apartment after a long journey back, a different part switched in and I was so glad to be home and back again in my standard routine.</p>
<p>We traveled to many beautiful locations in my early childhood, and I truly appreciate all the culturally enriching experiences I acquired, which I believe to this day have helped shaped my worldview. I do, however, wish that my parents were more aware of how stressful this was for me as a child. I did not understand the significance of the locations we would visit, and felt as though I was being dragged from place to place without understanding what was going on around me. In pictures of our family vacations, it&rsquo;s clear that I am dissociating&mdash;many of them show me with a blank expression with my eyes glazed over. I learned to regulate myself by dissociating, detaching from the world around me. And these repeated experiences of traveling = part creation have continued throughout my life, increasingly fragmenting my awareness when I take trips.</p>
<p>I believe this is a good example of how trauma, but not necessarily abuse, can lead to the formation of DID.
I would not consider traveling as much as we did abuse, but it was traumatic because it was too much for me to handle at the developmental stages it occurred in.
One could argue that this was neglect or negligence&mdash;that my parents weren&rsquo;t attuned to my emotional needs at the time.
However, it does not fit into the category of extreme abuse that is often attributed to the creation of DID.
While I do not believe this was the only trauma that caused me to form DID, and some of those traumas would be considered abuse,
traveling in the way that we did when I was small had a major impact on how I create parts, and is perhaps the most influential mechanism of part creation in my adult life.</p>
<!--

One part of me is very grateful that I had traveled so much in my childhood because that meant that I had already seen everything I would ever to in life and would never have to travel again. That part of me sees vacations a check box to complete, rather than an experience to enjoy. This line of thinking was influenced by the stress I 


 I, as the newly created part, did not want to change my routine back again.

I was a very well traveled child, and while I used to think of this as an amazing opportunity 
I even in my adult life, and is perhaps the most influential 


One could argue that this was neglect, not abuse.


With that being said, in my adult life at least, I do enjoy vacations---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.

One part of me was very happy that I had traveled so much as a child because that would mean that I wouldn't 
My understanding of vacations was that they were a check box to complete, rather than an experience to enjoy.
With that being said, I did enjoy them---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.
With that being said, I did enjoy them---I'd create a part to enjoy them for me as the me that deals with every day life does not like interruptions.

I did not understand the significance of the locations I was being 


My system is very chaotic---I seem to split parts in complex 

As I understand it, one can create parts to respond to stressors in their environment.

To me, traveling is stressful. And incredibly unpredictable. When I was young, I didn't know what was going on in the environment around me as my parents moved me from landmark to landmark that I didn't understand the significance of. 

By the time I was 5 years old, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips. I did not understand the significance of the locations I was being 

One of the first mechanisms of creating parts 

I have kept detailed work journals for 
Something I've always done 

At first, it didn't make sense to me 
Over time, it became obvious why.


As a polyfragmented system, I seem to split parts
Early into my discovery journey, something puzzled me. I learned pretty quicky 

My first several years of life were very chaotic. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad's job. 
For my whole life up to that point, while my handwriting was floridly changing, I never had questioned it or honestly really noticed it. Now, I am very thankful that I have a solid visual indicator for which parts of me were active at different times of my life.
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My handwriting isn&rsquo;t usually discretely clear, and is often a blend of many different parts' handwritings. However, on several trips my handwriting made a clear enough change for me to notice this pattern.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/traveling/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/traveling/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 22:14:57 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Parts are created from trauma, not necessarily abuse</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
