







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="https://example.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>Posts</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>https://example.com/posts/</link>
        
        
            <title>Posts</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>It took me several months of therapy with a dissociative disorders specialist in order for me to even consider that I had DID, despite having a pediatric dissociative disorder diagnosis. Like many others would in my generation, as soon as I realized I was being assessed for DID, I immediately went to sites like Reddit and YouTube to see how other people with this disorder conceptualize their experiences. Needless to say, I did not relate to others' experiences that I found online. Most people I had encountered seemed to have a relatively small number clearly defined parts with clear roles. I genuinely did not believe that I had DID, despite the fact that I was frequently dissociating in therapy sessions without realizing I was doing so.</p>
<p>Then, about 4 months into therapy, I noticed my first switch. It was incredibly subtle, but as I was working at my desk I noticed I momentarily started to dissociate, to detach from the world around me, and then all of a sudden everything became clear again. And I felt internally different. <em>Did I just switch?</em> I thought. I then went back to working and noticed that my handwriting had changed. <em>Why?</em> Upon noticing this, I switched again. It was once again incredibly subtle, but I looked back at my notebook, and tried to pick up where I had left off. Yet again, my handwriting had changed. I started panicking. <em>What is happening? Am I switching?</em> Then I switched again, and felt calm. By then, I knew I was switching, and that I must have DID, and that my disorder was going to be more complex than the clean switching between well-defined parts that I was used to seeing in social and traditional media. This was my first known occurrence of what many in the community call &ldquo;rapid switching&rdquo;, and is something I would experience on a near daily basis after that.</p>
<p>I, for the most part, have very little identity alteration between parts. To me, it seems like my one singular identity is fragmented into discrete pieces rather than me being the current part that I am, and other parts being different to me. I do have some parts which feel distinctly different than the mass of parts I consider to be <em>me</em>, but a majority of the time, I feel like I have a singular sense of self, with the same personality. But that sense of self is extremely fragmented.</p>
<!--

The analogy of an individual having multiple parts 

So, the question remains: why do I have so many parts?
 -->
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/comingtoterms/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/comingtoterms/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 15:25:41 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Coming to terms with having DID</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&hellip; it&rsquo;s about childhood trauma.</p>
<p>Dissociative Identity Disorder (DID) can be thought of as a coping mechanism one may develop when they experience repeated trauma in early childhood. It is arguably one of the most misunderstood and controversial mental health conditions, perhaps because it&rsquo;s been repeatedly sensationalized in the media. Or, maybe because the name and clinical description of the disorder implies that it&rsquo;s about having multiple identities or personality states. However, these personality states are often incredibly subtle and are instead indicative of a post-traumatic reaction involving severe compartmentalization of experience.</p>
<p>DID is a highly individualized disorder which forms based off of one&rsquo;s reaction to their life experiences. As such, I can only speak for myself and how I personally experience this disorder. While DID can be difficult to understand, it&rsquo;s fundamentally about two psychological phenomena&mdash;<em>detachment</em> and <em>compartmentalization</em>. Using myself as an example, when I was small, there were times where I experienced extreme repeated abuse<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, but otherwise had a happy childhood. While I was being abused, I mentally <em>detached</em> myself from the situation&mdash;I disconnected from my body and the external world, choosing instead to escape into my mind to distract myself from a situation I knew no other way to get out of. I also internally <em>compartmentalized</em> the experience and shoved it from my awareness, effectively allowing me to forget that it even occurred after it was over as I lived an otherwise happy childhood<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. Because this abuse occurred repeatedly, I continually used this strategy of switching to the compartment that held the abuse when I experienced triggers that the abuse was going to happen again. Then, when the abuse was over, I would switch back to the compartment that had a happy childhood and was blissfully unaware of the abuse that was taking place. This repeated pattern of behavior further increased my compartmentalization of memory, awareness, experience, and identity. All of this was done on a subconscious level.</p>
<p>This strategy of compartmentalization can only develop when trauma occurs in early childhood, while the brain still is rapidly developing and has the capacity to use such defenses. And because I learned to use these defenses when I was very young and my brain wired based on my experiences of the world around me, I learned that this was a very effective strategy for minimizing psychological discomfort.
Because of this, over time my threshold for what constituted compartment creation lowered as I relied more and more on this coping mechanism.
Because I was able to compartmentalize my experience, I subconsciously learned to separate the good aspects of my life&mdash;like emotions of happiness, contentment, and good memories&mdash;from the bad aspects of my life&mdash;like anger, grief, and memories of trauma.
Additionally, I learned to use compartmentalization in areas of my life that weren&rsquo;t inherently traumatic.
While this started as a very effective coping mechanism in response to childhood trauma, it has rapidly turned maladaptive as I have continually created compartments to respond to adult stressors.</p>
<p>Rather than fluidly being able to access all aspects of my personality like a more integrated individual, I have to switch between discrete personality states as I move throughout life.
While many of these compartments share memory (i.e., when I am in one compartment of memory, I will likely remember at least most of what happened when I was in a different compartment of memory), when I switch between compartments it can be like a RAM drop&mdash;my working memory, or what I was actively thinking about, gets wiped.
I also have compartments of memory with varying degrees of amnesia between them, so I genuinely may not remember what happened when I was in one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This lack of memory sharing typically happens between compartments who hold traumatic memories and emotions and ones who do not.
Additionally, depending on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, I will have different motivations and awareness of my current life. So while I may be an enthusiastic PhD student in several compartments, I also have compartments where I have no idea what my research is, or even that I am a student working towards my degree.
These compartments are so far removed from present time and context that, when I am in them, I do not perceive myself as being the adult me I actually am.
Sometimes, instead of fully taking over, these compartments intrude on my awareness, so I may have unexplained feelings of, say, fear that I have no idea where is coming from or what is triggering it.
On this blog, I hope to document my experiences as a system of memory compartments working together in the relay race of life in an attempt to live it to the fullest.</p>
<p>So DID is really not about identity&mdash;it&rsquo;s about childhood trauma and the extreme compartmentalization that may form because of it. The identity alteration and switching/influence of multiple personality states is merely a side effect of a brilliant psychological defense mechanism in response to early childhood trauma. But while it&rsquo;s not about identity explicitly, the fact that one has several distinct identities as opposed to a single unified one can be a major component to the disorder that may severely affect, both positively and negatively, how one experiences life with DID.</p>
<!---
This only scratches the surface of what I experience as a results of having DID.
There are many occasions that I have been shocked to hear how I behaved when more vulnerable parts of my personality have been out,.

For example, I have parts that clean for me, because at one time I likely decided that although I really didn't want to clean, I needed to, so I created a part to do so for me. 

While this was an incredibly effective coping strategy for me when I was actively experiencing trauma, it 

This has been an incredibly effective strategy in emotional regulation for me. In fact, my dynamic range of emotions is so low, that my main emotional state exists solely of mild contentment, which I seemingly experience most of the time.






Because this compartment creation strategy has been my primary coping mechanism, as time went on, I created more and more compartments as a response to small life stressors, which has been unsustainable. 
 an unsustainable 

Detaching from the world around me allowed me to regulate how much of my surroundings I experienced, which has been particularly helpful as an autistic person with sound and light sensitivities.
Over time, rather than the standard development of a fluid personality with a singular sense of "me", I developed several discretely separated personality states that I need to switch between to experience life.

Because of the internal compartmentalization, the parts of me who lived a normal childhood did not remember the events that occurred to the parts of me who experienced trauma. This allowed my compartments that experienced life to grow and thrive as a child, while my other compartments held the hurt and pain of the abuse. 
This led to 

While many individuals with this disorder may only experience a split in traumatized vs untraumatized parts of their personality, 

As I became older and was no longer actively encountering abuse, because it was so deeply engrained in how I operate, I still used this part creation strategy to aid in every day life.

Detaching from the world around me was a way I learned to regulate myself. For example, because I am autistic, I have sound and light sensitivities. 

, which has been particularly helpful as an autistic person with sound and light sensitivities.

This became a highly effective strategy---I learned to dedicate parts of me to handling abuse, and other parts of me to learning and growing as a child. 
---I was oblivious to the fact that this abuse caused me to form a severe mental disorder that would impact me for the rest of my life.

Because this abuse occurred at a time in which my brain was rapidly developing, this strategy of detachment and compartmentalization became engrained as an effective 
I learned how

which was damaging to my develping brain. 





extreme repeated abuse outside of the home (along with less severe abuse and traumas within my family). Because this abuse was so severe, 


To put it simply, how I understand 



And while that may be true about

Truthfully, as much as I want to generalize, I understand how personal

Yet, perhaps because of the name, or the media representation, 

When I started therapy almost 14 months ago, I genuinely believed that dissociative identity disorder (DID) was a fake disorder that people feigned to get out of trouble or for attention. My understanding of DID was influenced by the social and traditional media representation of the disorder, which generally portrayed people experiencing drastic personality shifts, or seemingly role-playing characters. I never thought this disorder could apply to me---for the most part, I was soft spoken, reclusive, and tried my hardest to blend into society. However, as I know now, I am a typical, but not stereotypical, example of how DID presents.

DID is caused by repetitive trauma in early childhood, while the brain is rapidly developing. To put it simply, one way a child can cope with trauma 

if a young child experiences trauma, one way they can cope with 

At an early age, if one 




So it's not about identity. Having multiple identities is a side effect of the extreme internal compartmentalization caused by trauma. But because it's the most sensational part of the disorder, that's what it's known as.
but somehow it's been made 

Alternative title: How I conceptualize my experience 1 year and 2 months into therapy.--->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This example is an oversimplification, and this extreme abuse occurred outside the home. However, I did experience less severe abuse and other traumas within my family which shaped my development of this disorder as well.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This was not fully the case, but I wanted to emphasize the differential between the good and bad parts of my childhood to provide a more concrete this example of how parts in DID may split.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/notaboutidentity/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/notaboutidentity/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 21:43:08 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>It’s not about identity</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
