







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="https://example.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>Recent content</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>https://example.com/</link>
        
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Alternative title: How I conceptualize my experience 1 year and 2 months into therapy.</p>
<p>When I started therapy almost 14 months ago, I had no idea what I was getting myself into.</p>
<p>So it&rsquo;s not about identity. Having multiple identities is a side effect of the extreme internal compartmentalization caused by trauma. Somehow
but somehow it&rsquo;s been made</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/notaboutidentity/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/notaboutidentity/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 21:43:08 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>It’s not about identity</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Dissociation can be a confusing concept, mostly because it is so broadly defined.</p>
<p>I like to think of dissociation as two distinct yet related concepts&mdash;detachment and compartmentalization.</p>
<!--Dissociation is a phenomena that we all experience and rely -->
<p>On a spectrum of being fully immersed in external reality, when one has a grasp on the current time and context in the world around them, to being fully immersed in internal reality, where one&rsquo;s concentration is fully focused on their internal thoughts,</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/howibecamefragmented/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/howibecamefragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 08:12:10 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>How I Became Fragmented</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>In January 2022, I started trauma therapy. I had no idea what I was getting myself into&mdash;I knew I had a traumatic childhood, but I didn&rsquo;t yet understand how much my past experiences had affected me in the present. When I started therapy, I thought dissociative identity disorder (DID) was a fake disorder people feigned for attention. It sounded too fantastical to be real, and my logic-driven mind couldn&rsquo;t comprehend how</p>
<p>However, my understanding of the disorder was severely flawed, influenced by both traditional and social media. In reality, I was a perfect case example of what DID looks like before one is aware. Most noteably, I had no idea I was even symptomatic.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/ididntknow/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/ididntknow/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 17:49:41 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>I didn’t know I had DID</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="this-is-a-test-post">This is a test post</h1>
<p>why is it not showing up</p>
<p>This is a test</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/posts/test-post/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/posts/test-post/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 22:07:30 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Test Post</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                    <guid>https://example.com/search/</guid>
                    <link>https://example.com/search/</link>
                
                
                
                    <title>Search</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
