







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/topics/about-did/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>About DID</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/topics/about-did/</link>
        
        
            <title>About DID</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Everybody, regardless of if they have DID or not, has parts of their personality. For example, one may generally behave differently at work with their colleagues than they do at home with their family&mdash;they have a &ldquo;work self&rdquo; and a &ldquo;home self&rdquo;.
In someone without DID,
when one transitions between their work self and their home self, they likely have a continuous internal sense of memory and identity&mdash;when they&rsquo;re at home, they still remember what happened while they were at work and relate to those experiences. Using graphs, we can represent the relationship between their work self and their home self with two nodes, each denoting a part of their personality, and one edge connecting the nodes, relating the shared sense of memory and identity between the two parts.



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div >
<div id="twoparts" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/twoparts.js"></script>


Here, in an individual without DID, their work self and their home self are aware of and relate to the thoughts, feelings, and actions of the other part.
But people have more than just a work self and a home self&mdash;they have a multitude of parts, representing many different facets of their personality. For simplicity&rsquo;s sake we will only look at 6 of these parts to represent their entire personality.
In an individual without DID, their parts form a complete graph&mdash;all the nodes are connected with edges to all the other nodes, representing that all their parts remember and relate to the actions of other parts.</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div >
<div id="singlet" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/singlet.js"></script>


<p>The similar colors of the nodes, or parts, represents the small variations between parts of their whole personality.
Because their parts are familiar with and aware of one another, their changes in identity and experience would generally blend smoothly between their parts.</p>
<p>Things may be a bit different in an individual with DID. While they still may have similar types of parts to someone without DID, their graph may look something like this:</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div >
<div id="system1" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/system1.js"></script>


<p>Their parts do not form a complete graph&mdash;the lack of connection between their parts represents the lack of continuity of memory and identity between parts of self. The different colors represent that their identity and personality variation is likely to be larger than that of a more integrated individual because their parts are more separated.
In an individual with DID, when one part of them is active, they may experience the world in an entirely different way than when a different part is active. They may have a different awareness of their life, different memories, and have a different felt sense of identity. Their life is compartmentalized into different pockets of awareness, identity, memory, and experience that they switch between to experience life. Not all of their parts are aware of the feelings and actions of other parts, and this is by design&mdash;from a young age, they learned to separate parts of self who hold difficult memories and experiences from other parts of self. This separation of parts of self is protective, as it allowed them to learn and grow as a child when some parts of them were active, while simultaneously using different parts to compartmentalize traumatic experiences away from the more healthy parts of self.</p>
<p>It is important to note that just as everybody&rsquo;s personality structure is different from one another&rsquo;s, people with DID are going to have different system structures, which depend on their reactions to their individual life experiences.
While some people may have parts that are well-defined and differentiated, others have systems of parts that are less structured.
Some may have parts that can fit into categories such as &ldquo;work self&rdquo; and &ldquo;home self&rdquo;, while others do not.
Some may have multiple parts that do the same job, and other parts that don&rsquo;t have clearly defined jobs.
In my case, while I do have parts that I could represent in a graph like this, my system of parts doesn&rsquo;t fully fit into a neat, clearly-defined structure.
Also, because I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented">polyfragmented</a> and thus create parts easily, I have multiple parts that do the same job.
As an example, part of my system structure looks something like this:</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div >
<div id="mysystem" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/mysystem.js"></script>


<p>This is a far overly simplistic view, and only shows the parts of my system structure that I am aware of and am comfortable sharing. Here, I use the weights of edges between nodes to represent how connected two parts are, I use squares to denote clusters of parts rather than individual parts, and I only show three parts in each cluster when there are typically many more.
In reality, I believe my awareness of my system is still too abstract for me to accurately represent it with a concrete graph structure<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
However, I feel as though graphs such as this one can be a good visual representation of how parts relate to one another in individuals with a dissociative disorder.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>To be more accurate, I&rsquo;d also probably need to use a directed graph to show the one-way amnesia I sometimes experience&mdash;a part may be aware of the actions of another part, but that other part isn&rsquo;t aware of the first part. This is quite common in my system.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/visualgraphs/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/visualgraphs/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 17:56:15 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>A visual representation of DID using graphs</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from minutes to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
Additionally, <a href="/posts/shuffledawareness/">my internal awareness of my life is shuffled</a>, so I do not have a linear narrative history of my life or day-to-day activities.
This can affect my daily functioning significantly.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I use <em>switch</em> to denote a hard, discrete change between parts, which usually occurs when I&rsquo;m triggered and can be disorienting. I use <em>shift</em> to denote a smooth change between parts, which occurs more often than switching for me and can internally feel like a gear shifting in my brain.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&hellip; it&rsquo;s about childhood trauma.</p>
<p>Dissociative Identity Disorder (DID) can be thought of as a coping mechanism one may develop when they experience repeated trauma in early childhood. It is arguably one of the most misunderstood and controversial mental health conditions, perhaps because it&rsquo;s been repeatedly sensationalized in the media. Or, maybe because the name and clinical description of the disorder implies that it&rsquo;s about having multiple identities or personality states. However, these personality states are often incredibly subtle and are instead indicative of a post-traumatic reaction involving severe internal compartmentalization.</p>
<p>DID is a highly individualized disorder which forms based off of one&rsquo;s reaction to their life experiences. As such, I can only speak for myself and how I personally experience this disorder. While DID can be difficult to understand<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, it can be thought of as being fundamentally about two psychological phenomena&mdash;<em>detachment</em> and <em>compartmentalization</em>. Using myself as an example, when I was small, there were times where I experienced severe repeated abuse<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, but at other times had a happy childhood. While I was being abused, I mentally <em>detached</em> myself from the situation&mdash;I disconnected from my body and the external world, choosing instead to escape into my mind to distract myself from a situation I knew no other way to get out of. Perhaps more importantly, I also internally <em>compartmentalized</em> the experience and shoved it from my awareness, effectively allowing me to forget that it even occurred after it was over as I lived an otherwise happy childhood<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. Because this abuse occurred repeatedly, I continually used this strategy of switching to the compartment that held the abuse when I experienced triggers that the abuse was going to happen again. Then, when the abuse was over, I would switch back to the compartment that had a happy childhood and was blissfully unaware of the abuse that was taking place. This repeated pattern of switching between compartments further increased my compartmentalization of memory, awareness, experience, and identity. However, this was incredibly protective, as it allowed some parts of me to learn and grow as a child while other parts of me held the difficult memories and feelings of being abused out of awareness. All of this was done on a subconscious level.</p>
<p>This strategy of compartmentalization can only develop when trauma occurs in early childhood, while the brain still is rapidly developing and has the capacity to use such defenses. And because I learned to use these defenses when I was very young and my brain wired based on my experiences of the world around me, I learned that this was a very effective strategy for minimizing psychological discomfort.
Because of this, over time my threshold for what constituted compartment creation lowered as I relied more and more on this coping mechanism.
Because I was able to compartmentalize my experience, I subconsciously learned to separate the good aspects of my life&mdash;like emotions of happiness, contentment, and good memories&mdash;from the bad aspects of my life&mdash;like anger, grief, and memories of trauma.
Additionally, I learned to use compartmentalization in areas of my life that weren&rsquo;t inherently traumatic.
While this started as a very effective coping mechanism in response to childhood trauma, it has rapidly turned maladaptive as I have continually created compartments to respond to adult stressors.</p>
<p>Rather than fluidly being able to access all aspects of my personality like a more integrated individual, I have to switch between discrete personality states as I move throughout life.
While many of these compartments share memory (i.e., when I am in one compartment of memory, I will likely remember at least most of what happened when I was in a different compartment of memory), when I switch between compartments it can feel like a RAM drop&mdash;my working memory, or what I was actively thinking about, gets wiped.
I also have compartments of memory with varying degrees of amnesia between them, so I genuinely may not remember what happened when I was in one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This lack of memory sharing typically happens between compartments who hold traumatic memories and emotions and ones who do not.
Additionally, depending on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, I will have different motivations and awareness of my current life. So while I may be an enthusiastic PhD student in several compartments, I also have compartments where I have no idea what my research is, or even that I am a student working towards my degree.
Sometimes, instead of fully taking over, these compartments intrude on my awareness, so I may have unexplained feelings of, say, fear that I have no idea where is coming from or what is triggering it.</p>
<p>For a long time, I was adamant that I did not experience identity alteration. I&rsquo;m now realizing that while I do have many compartments that all seem to identify as &ldquo;me&rdquo;, some compartments are so far removed from present time and context that, when I am in them, I do not perceive myself as being the adult me I actually am.
The identity alteration I do experience is incredibly subtle, and is much more an internal phenomena than an external one&mdash;an external observer will most likely not be able to tell apart my parts<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. These parts are just different versions of me, so even with the identity alteration I do have, I see these parts as all being <em>me</em>.</p>
<p>So DID is really not <em>about</em> identity, even if that&rsquo;s the most sensationalized part of the disorder. I personally see the identity alteration and switching/influence of multiple personality states as merely a side effect of a brilliant psychological defense mechanism in response to early childhood trauma. But while it&rsquo;s not about identity explicitly, the fact that one has several distinct identities<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> as opposed to a single unified one can be a major component to the disorder that may severely affect, both positively and negatively, how one experiences life with DID.</p>
<!--
While many of these compartments share memory (i.e., when I am in one compartment of memory, I will likely remember at least most of what happened when I was in a different compartment of memory), when I switch between compartments it can feel like a RAM drop---my working memory, or what I was actively thinking about, gets wiped. 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>There are many different theories about how DID forms and works, but this is one of the ways that I like to think about it.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This example is an oversimplification, and this severe abuse occurred outside the home. However, I did experience less severe abuse and other traumas within my family which shaped my development of this disorder as well.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This was not fully the case, but I wanted to emphasize the differential between the good and bad parts of my childhood to provide a more concrete example of how parts in DID may split.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>For the most part, I still can&rsquo;t even tell apart my parts. This is something that I&rsquo;m sure I will get better at with time, as I get more acquainted with how I operate.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>These distinct indentities are not whole on their own. Rather, they represent different parts of my whole personality. Rather than having one unified identity, I have several fragmented identities/personality states that I switch between.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/notaboutidentity/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/notaboutidentity/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 21:43:08 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>It’s not about identity</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
