







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/polyfragmented/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>polyfragmented</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/polyfragmented/</link>
        
        
            <title>polyfragmented</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I switch a lot on a daily basis, probably because I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented/">polyfragmented</a>. The vast majority of the time, however, I&rsquo;m switching between parts who are familiar with one-another, so this kind of switching is smooth, with only a small blip in my conscious awareness. I typically call this kind of switching <em>shifting</em>, because, although I am changing between parts, it isn&rsquo;t jarring and I don&rsquo;t feel like I have a loss of control&mdash;I am able to hold a conversation and mostly remember my train of thought while shifting between parts.</p>
<p>When I experience true switching, however, I may lose awareness of the world around me, in a time span range of anywhere from seconds to hours. Typically this disconnect feels gradual and seamless, so much so that, unless something notable happens while I was in the dissociated state so I come back to a discretely different situation than before the switch, I&rsquo;m usually not aware that I ever switched.
It can feel like I&rsquo;m waking up from a dream, and I&rsquo;m not fully aware if I&rsquo;m still dreaming or if this is my reality.</p>
<p>I see a lot of parallels in how I experience dreaming and how I experience switching between parts that aren&rsquo;t familiar with one another. When a trauma-holding part, one that my more regulated adult parts aren&rsquo;t acquainted with, is triggered to take control, it can feel like a kind of dream-state. Typically leading up to the switch, I start to feel heavy&mdash;my thinking slows down and my vision starts to fade. It feels slow, gradual, and, most importantly, natural. In reality, however, my switches are much faster than how they feel internally. When the part takes over, the dream-like state gets deeper. Most of the time, I&rsquo;m just along for the ride while the trauma-holding part has control. Everything feels a bit off, but I&rsquo;m usually not aware enough to even realize that. My thinking has slowed so far down that I&rsquo;m unable to grasp onto the reality of the situation. My vision has faded, and I have no control. My body is moving in ways that I have no awareness of, and time is suspended. I am not even aware that I do not have control because I&rsquo;m not aware of the world around me.</p>
<p>Since starting therapy, I&rsquo;ve been more able to identify when I&rsquo;m in this dissociated state.
This is because my therapist, who is able to recognize when I have dissociated, can prompt my adult parts to get back online by reminding me that we are safe and asking where my adult parts are.
When this happens, I&rsquo;m now able to do something analogous to lucid dreaming, where I am aware that something is off about my reality and I can sometimes exhibit partial control over the situation. I may be able to suggest to the part in control about what to do. I can tell the part, by thinking, that we are safe and update them on the reality of the situation. Sometimes, when this happens, my adult parts switch back in and I gradually gain control over the situation again. Other times, however, the part in control may get even more scared and confused about what is happening, resulting in an even more painful situation. For the most part, these trauma-holding parts aren&rsquo;t aware of present time and context, and think that trauma is happening right now, so they&rsquo;re often terrified.</p>
<p>It is a very strange feeling when a trauma-holding part is in control and I am simultaneously aware of the situation. I have a little control over my actions, but not too much. If, for example, I try to move my arm, my arm may feel so heavy that I am unable to move it. If I try to speak, I can feel like I am being blocked from doing so. Meanwhile, my body is moving in ways and I am doing things that I have no control over and cannot predict. Everything feels very slow, heavy, and visually dark. That part has more control over my actions than I do, and that part feels like a separate entity to me. Because of this, it can feel like I am possessed, so it can be a really scary experience for all parts involved.</p>
<p>Eventually, I switch back in and gain control again. While in reality this is typically an instantaneous switch, it feels like I&rsquo;m slowly waking up from a dream. After I&rsquo;m back in control, if I think back to what just happened, I&rsquo;m often genuinely unsure if what just happened actually happened. Sometimes, my memory of the event is simply not there. Other times, I remember only fractions of the time that the other part was in control. When I do remember the event, I typically only remember certain aspects of it&mdash;for the most part, my visual memory is not there, but I may remember what I heard while I was in a dissociated state. Sometimes, when I switch back, my memories of the event come back to me all of a sudden, as if to update me about what just happened but without having experienced it myself.</p>
<p>For most of my life, I was so used to entering and exiting this dream-like state where other parts have control that I genuinely didn&rsquo;t know it was abnormal&mdash;it was normal to me.
I was never consciously aware that other parts ever took over until starting therapy. At first, when this would happen in my therapy sessions, I&rsquo;d switch back after an episode to my therapist asking me if I knew what had just happened. I didn&rsquo;t, but I&rsquo;d pretend that I did because I didn&rsquo;t want to come to terms with the fact that I didn&rsquo;t.
Over time, my therapist was able to cue me forward when I was actively in a dissociated state, thus allowing me to become more aware while other parts were in control to help me create connections between my parts.
Now, I am more able to recognize when I am in a dissociated state, but I absolutely would not have been able to do so without having my therapist explicitly point it out to me first&mdash;I was simply unaware otherwise.</p>
<p>Having DID is a confusing experience, and it&rsquo;s really difficult to put into words the reality of my situation. Most of my life feels no different to anybody elses, yet I also have these otherworldy experiences. Up until recently, I wasn&rsquo;t conscious of the times that I didn&rsquo;t not have control over my life. Since becoming aware, the awareness of the lack of control over my own actions is, quite frankly, terrifying. I don&rsquo;t know what all of my triggers are, so I could, in theory, have a dissociative episode at any moment. Thankfully, I believe that the vast majority of these episodes occur in the controlled environment of therapy.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/traumapart/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/traumapart/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 07:50:32 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>What does it feel like when a trauma-holding part takes control?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I began therapy for DID in January 2022, I had no idea how much my life had already spiraled out of control. Over the course of several years, I had gone from being a high-achieving student at the top of my class to being effectively unable to work because I was so triggered by the world around me.
However, because of my severe internal compartmentalization, I was unaware of my dysfunction&mdash;I had no idea anything abnormal was happening, and, for the most part, thought I was still the successful student I previously was.
I went from being an over-achiever to effectively dysfunctional.
This is because work went from a source of fun and inspiration to a source of stress, so work became triggering to me. There are a variety of factors that affect why work became so triggering, but the end result is the same&mdash;just as in the past I learned to avoid traumatic or stressful things by dissociating away from them, I continued the pattern and subconsciously learned to dissociate away from work.</p>
<p>Within my system structure, I have separate compartments for work, which are differentiated enough from my other compartments such that when the work parts aren&rsquo;t out, I&rsquo;m practically unaware of my work life.
However, because my work parts are so compartmentalized, when my work parts are out, I&rsquo;m able to hyperfocus on work, undistracted by the happenings of the world around me.
This is something I developed as a child&mdash;I learned to separate my work and home lives because they were so different.
When my system is running smoothly, the right parts come out on queue, working together harmoniously. My internal compartmenalization of different facets of my life has always been severe, and since it had had worked well in the past, I had never questioned it before.</p>
<p>During graduate school, over the span of several years, as work gradually became more and more triggering for me, my work parts slowly started coming out less and less organically. I began a cycle of behavior: when work was not stressful, I&rsquo;d work as normal. Then, when something stressful would come up, it&rsquo;d become much more difficult to work. For a period of time spanning days to weeks, I&rsquo;d be effectively unable to work, but I&rsquo;d be unaware that I wasn&rsquo;t working as normal. Then, I&rsquo;d inevitably become aware that I was &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; at work, and force myself to start work again, which was always incredibly difficult as I was working through being triggered. Once the stressor was alleviated or sufficiently forgotten about, I&rsquo;d be back to working as normal again. And then when the next stressor came up, the cycle would repeat.</p>
<p>This cycle has repeated at least a dozen times during my PhD thus far, and each time it has repeated, new parts would be created to &ldquo;take control of my life again&rdquo; once I realized I was not working productively. Because of this, my awareness of my work life has become increasingly fragmented. For me, my handwriting is a great indicator to differentiate between parts.
For most of my undergraduate years, I had two main handwritings, indicating the two main work parts who were consistent through the entirety of undergrad. But in graduate school, my handwriting has become much more inconsistent. Because of the way I&rsquo;ve split work parts, I can see in my academic journal that, over the span of several months, I&rsquo;m writing the same concepts down over and over again, all in different handwritings. I have difficulty picking up where the previous part left off, so I practically have to start my work all over again once a new part is created. It&rsquo;s clear that I&rsquo;m trying really hard to advance in work, but because I&rsquo;m creating new compartments to work as opposed to utilizing the old ones, my awareness of my work life has become extremely fractured and inconsistent.</p>
<p>Why am I creating new parts instead of using already created work parts? I&rsquo;m not entirely sure, but I can speculate. I believe it&rsquo;s because <a href="/posts/polyfragmented/">I am polyfragmented</a>, so I create parts really easily. And because the previous parts I subconsciously create to take control of my life eventually become too stressed to come out, I create new parts who are unaware of the stress in order to advance.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me an incredibly long time to gain the insight that I have now, and even now that I&rsquo;ve gained this insight, it&rsquo;s hard for me to break the cycle. Right now, I&rsquo;m at the stage that I&rsquo;m aware that this is how I operate, but I&rsquo;m not yet at the place where I&rsquo;m able to change it&mdash;I&rsquo;m stuck observing my cyclical parts.
I seem to have very little control over what goes on in my life, but it&rsquo;s starting to get better.
I am learning to become aware of what stage of the cycle I&rsquo;m in at any given time, which has allowed me to stay in the stage where work parts are out longer and the stage where I&rsquo;m dysfunctional shorter. I&rsquo;m making progress, but it&rsquo;s slow and incredibly difficult.</p>
<p>I truly hate that this is the way I operate. I do not enjoy being so stressed by my work that my dissociative defenses are constantly activated. There are large spans of time where I&rsquo;m totally unaware of work because I&rsquo;m so stressed by it, followed by times where I&rsquo;m hyperaware of how much I&rsquo;ve been &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; on work and have to pick up the pieces, over and over again.
To be clear, I do not believe I&rsquo;m &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; when I&rsquo;m in a stage of the cycle where I&rsquo;m unable to work. Rather, I consider myself to be in a triggered state that I have little to no control over. But from the outside looking in, if one is unaware that I have DID, it really looks like I do not care about my PhD and am intentionally slacking on my responsibilities.
This has been incredibly frustrating to come to terms with, as my behavior is still mostly out of my control as I am constantly responding to triggers in my environment, yet I have the strong desire to break the cycle.</p>
<p>What is the path forward? Ideally, I&rsquo;d like to stop this cyclical behavior so I can work as normal again. I want to stop creating new parts when I get too stressed. I want to have one or two dedicated work parts out like I did in my undergraduate years so my awareness of my work life isn&rsquo;t so fragmented. I want to stop being so triggered by work that my dissociate defenses are constantly activated. I truly just want to become productive at work again, and while I see the light at the end of the tunnel, I have a long way to go before I get there. For now, I&rsquo;ll take it one day at a time, as I slowly take back control of my life.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/howdidaffectswork/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/howdidaffectswork/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 04:18:25 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>How DID affects my work</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>One impactful but not immediately obvious symptom of DID for me is that I do not seem to have a continuous internal sense of time&mdash;my awareness of my life is shuffled.
Because of this, I may have a hard time differentiating what happened yesterday versus what happened last week or last month,
or struggle with remembering if, for example, I have leftovers in my fridge now or if that was from weeks ago.
This has made things like tracking changes in my environment difficult.
For example, I have had spring-time allergies for much of my life, but I was unable to realize that until recently&mdash;every day in the spring, I&rsquo;d wake up with allergies, but to me that was just accepted as fact. I didn&rsquo;t remember that I had allergies yesterday or every day last week, or that I didn&rsquo;t have allergies last fall, or that I&rsquo;ve had allergies every spring since childhood. All I am aware of is that I have allergies in that moment. Only since concretely tracking my symptoms this year was I able to determine that I do have springtime allergies, despite having them for years.
Life really feels like a blur to me.</p>
<p>I believe these experiences can be explained by my system structure, which is heavily impacted by the fact that I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented">polyfragmented</a>.
I seem to shift and switch between compartments a significant amount on a daily basis, and many of these compartments, or parts, only seem to come out every few days or weeks. Since what is at the forefront of my awareness depends on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, and many of these parts only come out once in a while, the end result seems to be that my understanding of my life is very shuffled.</p>
<p>Right now, I have a hard time differentiating between these parts, which makes it difficult to map how my understanding of my life is shuffled. I can vaguely tell when the last time I was in an active compartment was because I remember those memories most prominently, but I don&rsquo;t know <em>who</em> the part is. Many of them feel the same except for mild memory differences, seemingly because I have low identity alteration.
I have been told that differentiating between parts takes time, so I am hopeful that I&rsquo;ll soon be able to identify my parts.
I&rsquo;ve been operating like this for my entire life without awareness that most others do not have such a shuffled awareness.
I&rsquo;m glad that I finally understand that I have DID and that I operate in this way, as it provides me language to contextualize my experiences. With time, I hope to gain a more broad view of my life and form a more continuous relationship with time.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/shuffledawareness/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/shuffledawareness/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 21:19:32 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Shuffled sense of time</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from minutes to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
Additionally, <a href="/posts/shuffledawareness/">my internal awareness of my life is shuffled</a>, so I do not have a linear narrative history of my life or day-to-day activities.
This can affect my daily functioning significantly.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I use <em>switch</em> to denote a hard, discrete change between parts, which usually occurs when I&rsquo;m triggered and can be disorienting. I use <em>shift</em> to denote a smooth change between parts, which occurs more often than switching for me and can internally feel like a gear shifting in my brain.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
