







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/conceptualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>conceptualization</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/conceptualization/</link>
        
        
            <title>conceptualization</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Life is moving very rapidly right now. I wrote the previous post (<a href="/posts/wakingup/">Waking up to the present</a>) six weeks ago, shortly after I had split a new cluster of parts. Then, three weeks ago, I split a whole new cluster of parts. Both six weeks ago and three weeks ago I had very distinct changes in my behavioral patterns and how I operate. I have two very distinct &ldquo;jumps&rdquo; in my continuity of memory both three and six weeks ago.</p>
<p>I have been creating new clusters of parts due to stressors for my whole life, but up until recently I wasn&rsquo;t aware I was doing it&mdash;it was &ldquo;normal&rdquo; to me, so I didn&rsquo;t know anything was off. Until I learned that I had DID, I didn&rsquo;t have a framework from which to understand my experiences. Since starting for therapy for DID, I have become much more aware of my internal states and, with lots of practice and observation, I am now generally able to tell when I have switched between or created new compartments of memory.</p>
<p>While cultivating my internal qualitative awareness of my system is important, I am a very quantitative-minded person&mdash;I want hard, solid evidence that what I am going through is actually happening. And now I finally do.</p>
<p>A few years ago, I started tracking information about my life and logging it in a database. I started small, tracking simple things like medications taken, my weight, and when I showered. Over time, I started tracking more and more complex things as I became more aware of patterns in my life. For example, there are times when I have a distinctly different gait than normal, and other times where I chew my tongue habitually in a distinct way, along with many other factors. I also automatically log certain things such as the activity on my computer and phone, along with steps taken and when I fall asleep/wake up every day. I generally log the activities of what I do in a day, in broad categories such as work, eating, and walking, over time.
I now have tens of thousands of data points about myself, spread over a few years, from which I can draw conclusions off of.
I also journal every day, in both a personal journal and a work journal, so I also have a lot of free-form data along with handwriting from that.</p>
<p>Now, looking at my data, across multiple factors, I see distinct changes in how I operate both three and six weeks ago. Internally, I already knew this, but having physical data to back up my internal awareness definitely validates my understanding of my system.
In addition to providing solid quantitative evidence of my system, logging data about myself requires me to be observant and mindful of my life&rsquo;s activities, which in turn helps me to gain internal awareness of how I operate.</p>
<p>In a way, I am collecting data about myself to solve an inverse problem. Given the data that I acquire about myself, can I determine the underlying model about how I operate? With time, as I acquire more data, its becoming increasingly more clear. I am figuring out how I operate, slowly but surely, using the best way I know how&mdash;using data.</p>
<p>I feel I am in a different stage of recovery now than I was even a few months ago. I have become much more aware about who I am and how I operate. I am an amalgamation of hundreds of parts who are working together, with varying levels of cooperation, to live life. As life goes on and the data I collect about myself along with my awareness grows, my confidence about the way that I operate increases. I can now definitively say that I am a polyfragmented system operating with hundreds of parts, many of which are fragments. I split parts regularly, and switch between my parts a handful to hundreds of times a day. I have different scales of parts&mdash;while I have parts that I switch between every day, I also have longer-scale parts that I shift between on the order of days to weeks. My longer-scale parts seem to be roughly cyclical, and seem to repeat on the order of a few months, seemingly dependent on life stressors. On the other hand, my daily parts seem to come out much more consistently due to more concrete triggers, such as task-based reasons or reminders of trauma.</p>
<p>Since capturing long-scale variations in data is much simpler than capturing short-scale variations in data<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, I am currently more focused on capturing my long-scale parts. With time and increased awareness, I hope to be able to acquire more data about my parts that switch more frequently.
But with the data I have now, I have made a few observations.
Depending on which &ldquo;part of the cycle&rdquo; I am in (in other words, which long-scale part is out), the way I operate in life is distinctly different. This includes things like my bedtime and morning routine, how well I cook and the foods I eat, my hobbies and interests, how aware of/productive I am at work, how often I shower, how long/frequently I walk, my handwriting, my gait, how often I socialize/interact with others, the video games I play and how often I play them, how interested I am in/how frequently I use marijuana, how much I am aware of/interested in my pets and plants, my awareness of my past and my future, how clean my apartment is, how aware I am of my appearance, how connected I am with my body/how sensitive I am to pain, my outlook on life, my entire internal experience, and many other things that are too personal to list here.
While for a long time I was suspicious that this was my system structure and the way that I operate, I now have sufficient enough data for me to be convinced my model is correct.</p>
<!--

 life feels distinctly different. 

Between three and six weeks ago, I was very focused and aware of my PhD work---I advanced in my research greatly and spent almost every day during that time period, including weekends, fully working. I also feel asleep and woke up at regular times. I journaled proficiently, walked every day, and was very aware of my present life and what I needed to do to graduate. I ate meals at regular times every day. I had a consistent morning and evening routine. My life was moving forward smoothly.

Between three weeks ago and the present, things have been very different and more chaotic. I am working on research, at most, three hours a day, and often times much less than that. Instead, I have become incredibly aware of my future life and have spent excessive amounts of time planning potential career options. My sleep and eating schedules have become incredibly inconsistent, and I journal much less than I used to. Additionally, what I journal about and the handwritings of my journal entries are distinctly different. I am practically unaware of my present life and what I need to do to graduate. 

So now I have data to back up what I already knew---I am still splitting parts. 







I also, very sadly, forgot about several plants that I was growing in my closet under grow lights. One day, I opened my closet, only to find a bunch of dead plants that I had no idea were in there. 

If this had happened six months ago, I wouldn't have been aware of my part splitting. But now, I collect enough data about myself that it's clear that I am still creating parts.

For example, I have a part with a weird gait that causes severe pain in my right leg while walking. For about a week every few months, I am unable to walk long distances because the pain is so severe. Then, my gait gradually changes again and I can walk normally. I log other strange habits like seem to be associated with parts like habitually chewing on my tongue in a specific way, or 


I'm afraid I'm going to split a new cluster of parts soon. 

I log many different metrics about me, most of which are too personal to even say what online. When analyzing this data, it's clear I have a distinct change in lots of aspects of my life  starting around July 5th, exactly 3 weeks ago. Looking further back, 

and I have split a new cluster of parts

I am in the thick of things right now.
Tracking metrics about myself.


It has been six weeks since I wrote the last post on this blog. In [Waking up to the present](/posts/wakingup/), 

I am now aquiring enough data about myself now that I can distinctly see 

For the past few years, I have been tracking various amounts of data about myself

I am now intensely aware of the future.

I forgot I had this blog. Reading posts now.
I reopened my blog for the first time in several weeks and started reading some of my old posts.


-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Capturing short-scale variations (the parts that switch multiple times a day) requires sampling, or capturing data points, at a much smaller time interval than capturing large-scale variations (parts that shift every few days to weeks).&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/datadriven/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/datadriven/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 22:37:26 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Data-driven system mapping</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Everybody, regardless of if they have DID or not, has parts of their personality. For example, one may generally behave differently at work with their colleagues than they do at home with their family&mdash;they have a &ldquo;work self&rdquo; and a &ldquo;home self&rdquo;.
In someone without DID,
when one transitions between their work self and their home self, they likely have a continuous internal sense of memory and identity&mdash;when they&rsquo;re at home, they still remember what happened while they were at work and relate to those experiences. Using graphs, we can represent the relationship between their work self and their home self with two nodes, each denoting a part of their personality, and one edge connecting the nodes, relating the shared sense of memory and identity between the two parts.



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div >
<div id="twoparts" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/twoparts.js"></script>


Here, in an individual without DID, their work self and their home self are aware of and relate to the thoughts, feelings, and actions of the other part.
But people have more than just a work self and a home self&mdash;they have a multitude of parts, representing many different facets of their personality. For simplicity&rsquo;s sake we will only look at 6 of these parts to represent their entire personality.
In an individual without DID, their parts form a complete graph&mdash;all the nodes are connected with edges to all the other nodes, representing that all their parts remember and relate to the actions of other parts.</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div >
<div id="singlet" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/singlet.js"></script>


<p>The similar colors of the nodes, or parts, represents the small variations between parts of their whole personality.
Because their parts are familiar with and aware of one another, their changes in identity and experience would generally blend smoothly between their parts.</p>
<p>Things may be a bit different in an individual with DID. While they still may have similar types of parts to someone without DID, their graph may look something like this:</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div >
<div id="system1" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/system1.js"></script>


<p>Their parts do not form a complete graph&mdash;the lack of connection between their parts represents the lack of continuity of memory and identity between parts of self. The different colors represent that their identity and personality variation is likely to be larger than that of a more integrated individual because their parts are more separated.
In an individual with DID, when one part of them is active, they may experience the world in an entirely different way than when a different part is active. They may have a different awareness of their life, different memories, and have a different felt sense of identity. Their life is compartmentalized into different pockets of awareness, identity, memory, and experience that they switch between to experience life. Not all of their parts are aware of the feelings and actions of other parts, and this is by design&mdash;from a young age, they learned to separate parts of self who hold difficult memories and experiences from other parts of self. This separation of parts of self is protective, as it allowed them to learn and grow as a child when some parts of them were active, while simultaneously using different parts to compartmentalize traumatic experiences away from the more healthy parts of self.</p>
<p>It is important to note that just as everybody&rsquo;s personality structure is different from one another&rsquo;s, people with DID are going to have different system structures, which depend on their reactions to their individual life experiences.
While some people may have parts that are well-defined and differentiated, others have systems of parts that are less structured.
Some may have parts that can fit into categories such as &ldquo;work self&rdquo; and &ldquo;home self&rdquo;, while others do not.
Some may have multiple parts that do the same job, and other parts that don&rsquo;t have clearly defined jobs.
In my case, while I do have parts that I could represent in a graph like this, my system of parts doesn&rsquo;t fully fit into a neat, clearly-defined structure.
Also, because I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented">polyfragmented</a> and thus create parts easily, I have multiple parts that do the same job.
As an example, part of my system structure looks something like this:</p>



<script src="/cytoscape/cytoscape.min.js"></script>

<div >
<div id="mysystem" class="graph"></div>
<script src="/cytoscape/mysystem.js"></script>


<p>This is a far overly simplistic view, and only shows the parts of my system structure that I am aware of and am comfortable sharing. Here, I use the weights of edges between nodes to represent how connected two parts are, I use squares to denote clusters of parts rather than individual parts, and I only show three parts in each cluster when there are typically many more.
In reality, I believe my awareness of my system is still too abstract for me to accurately represent it with a concrete graph structure<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
However, I feel as though graphs such as this one can be a good visual representation of how parts relate to one another in individuals with a dissociative disorder.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>To be more accurate, I&rsquo;d also probably need to use a directed graph to show the one-way amnesia I sometimes experience&mdash;a part may be aware of the actions of another part, but that other part isn&rsquo;t aware of the first part. This is quite common in my system.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/visualgraphs/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/visualgraphs/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 17:56:15 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>A visual representation of DID using graphs</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Have you thought about how you conceptualize your internal experience, or the language you use to describe it? I personally hadn&rsquo;t given either much thought until I learned I had DID. Since then, I&rsquo;ve had a long journey of learning to understand how I operate, which has required me to think deeply about how to convey my experiences to others who likely do not operate in the same way that I do.</p>
<p>How one chooses to explain how they operate is complex and deeply personal.
As such, different people with DID may choose to convey their experiences in many different ways.
While some people are extremely creative in their portrayals of how they operate, I am someone who is more reluctant to portray myself in a way that others may deem as being too imaginative.
Because of this, I&rsquo;m still trying to find the language that feels most appropriate to describe my experiences.</p>
<p>The language one chooses is influenced by the underlying model that they use to understand what they are experiencing.
My experiences with DID seem to vary greatly, and range in severity depending on if I&rsquo;m experiencing a trauma trigger or not.
On the severe end, when parts take over my body, it can feel like I&rsquo;m being possessed and another being is controlling me.
On the other end, most often switching and shifting between parts feels so natural to me that I wonder if my experiences are even different than the norm.
To me, it seems that both these mundane and extraordinary experiences can be explained by the model of me switching, shifting, and being influenced by different compartments of memory and experience, which I call parts.</p>
<p>With time, I have realized that I see the world with multiple different perspectives&mdash;while I have the perspective of me as a whole person, I also see the perspectives of me as my individual parts.
The perspective of me as a whole person is something I was acquainted with before my DID discovery journey began, as it is what most people experience and is thus the societal norm.
On this blog, and when I discuss with others about my experiences, I typically portray the perspective of myself as a singular unified person as it&rsquo;s likely how the vast majority of people see themselves, but this language can be limiting to describe my experiences.
Writing from the perspective of me as a whole, these &ldquo;parts&rdquo; seem to be compartments of many different aspects of my life, such as memory and  identity, that I switch between to navigate through life.
For the most part, I only have the perspective of one part at any given time<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, and due to my degree of compartmentalization between parts, including amnesia and severely changing understandings of the world, depending on which compartment I am in I may have very different perspectives and things to say.
If I only portray myself as one singular unified person, I am misrepresenting aspects of my experience.
Thinking and writing as if I am a system of parts can enable me to explain experiences that simply don&rsquo;t make sense from the more restrictive whole-self perspective, like changing views about a topic, lapses in memory, possession-like experiences, losing time, and even quirks like handwriting and gait changes between parts.</p>
<p>Since starting therapy, I&rsquo;ve gradually learned to internally reference myself as a system of parts, yet I still translate that to a singular-self language when talking with others as I am hesitant to externally display my internal perspective with others.
I like portraying having a unified, singular-self view of life, even though it doesn&rsquo;t fully reflect how I&rsquo;ve learned to perceive myself.
This is probably due to the fact that it makes me uncomfortable realizing others know that the way I internally refer to myself is different than the norm.
When I was young, I was more in-touch with my individual parts' perspectives&mdash;I would often refer to myself in third person in conversation with others<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I eventually learned that others did not experience themselves in this way, as I was occasionally ridiculed for it. I learned to hide using this language, even though it was the most accurate language for my experiences, since it was not well received by others.
Perhaps because of this, I feel the same way about using other unconventional language to describe my experiences&mdash;speaking from the perspective of individual parts, like I naturally did when I was younger, is tainted with shame due to my past experiences, and something I&rsquo;m working towards getting more comfortable with when appropriate in order to become more authentically me.</p>
<p>While I am used to thinking in third person<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, thinking about myself as multiple is new<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>, and I&rsquo;m still getting used to this conceptualization and the language used to describe it.
On this blog, I have decided to use whatever language is most appropriate for describing the particular experiences that I&rsquo;m trying to convey&mdash;I don&rsquo;t want to limit myself to a particular conceptualization or vocabulary set. So while I have mostly written from the perspective of a unified self thus far, this may change as I learn what language and conceptualization feels most comfortable for me.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Although, as I&rsquo;m creating connections between parts, this is thankfully changing!&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This is because I have many parts who perceive my life in third person, and when those compartments are active, I naturally refer to myself in third person.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This is useful for trauma survivors since it allows a detached view of self&mdash;one can perceive themselves as the observer of a situation rather than a participant in it.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I didn&rsquo;t know this was an option, and it didn&rsquo;t come organically to me like the third-person perspective did. Now that I am more aware this is how I operate, I see that it aligns very well with my experiences.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/language/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/language/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 12:22:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Finding my language</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
