







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/symptoms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>symptoms</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/symptoms/</link>
        
        
            <title>symptoms</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>One impactful but not immediately obvious symptom of DID for me is that I do not seem to have a continuous internal sense of time&mdash;my awareness of my life is shuffled.
Because of this, I may have a hard time differentiating what happened yesterday versus what happened last week or last month,
or struggle with remembering if, for example, I have leftovers in my fridge now or if that was from weeks ago.
This has made things like tracking changes in my environment difficult.
For example, I have had spring-time allergies for much of my life, but I was unable to realize that until recently&mdash;every day in the spring, I&rsquo;d wake up with allergies, but to me that was just accepted as fact. I didn&rsquo;t remember that I had allergies yesterday or every day last week, or that I didn&rsquo;t have allergies last fall, or that I&rsquo;ve had allergies every spring since childhood. All I am aware of is that I have allergies in that moment. Only since concretely tracking my symptoms this year was I able to determine that I do have springtime allergies, despite having them for years.
Life really feels like a blur to me.</p>
<p>I believe these experiences can be explained by my system structure, and
are heavily impacted by the fact that I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented">polyfragmented</a>.
I seem to shift and switch between compartments a significant amount on a daily basis, and many of these compartments, or parts, only seem to come out every few days or weeks. Since what is at the forefront of my awareness depends on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, and many of these parts only come out once in a while, the end result seems to be that my understanding of my life is very shuffled.</p>
<p>Right now, I have a hard time differentiating between these parts, which makes it difficult to map how my understanding of my life is shuffled. I can vaguely tell when the last time I was in an active compartment was because I remember those memories most prominently, but I don&rsquo;t know <em>who</em> the part is. Many of them feel the same except for mild memory differences, seemingly because I have low identity alteration.
I have been told that differentiating between parts takes time, so I am hopeful that I&rsquo;ll soon be able to identify my parts.
I&rsquo;ve been operating like this for my entire life without awareness that most others do not have such a shuffled awareness.
I&rsquo;m glad that I finally understand that I have DID and that I operate in this way, as it provides me language to contextualize my experiences. With time, I hope to gain a more broad view of my life and form a more continuous relationship with time.</p>
<!--In undergrad, I had two main handwritings, but in grad school my handwriting has become much more inconsistent. Furthermore, because of the way I've split work parts, I can see in my academic journal that, over the span of several months, I'm writing the same things down over and over again, all in different handwritings. I'm trying really 

These experiences are just subtle enough for me to question if they are actually significant, or if everyone experiences them and I'm just hyperaware of my internal experience. It's taken me a while, but now that I know how DID affects me, I do believe that these experiences are significant, as they do impact my day-to-day functioning.


When I wake up in the morning, I never know which part of me will be active---it seems to be different most days, so I wake up almost every morning with a different internal sense of how to operate in the world. Throughout the day, as other parts come out, my priorities and interests are shifted elsewhere, directed by what the current part wants to be doing. Externally observing my behavior, when I'm alone I discretely switch from task to task in a somewhat chaotic manner.
Because I only have the awareness of the current part, this jumpy behavior feels natural to me as I follow my switches.


cold I have today is new or if I was also sick yesterday. 

My plants in my home don't seem to grow---to me, it appears like they abruptly jump in size. 


I now have way more parts than jobs. For example, I went from having two main work parts in my undergraduate years to an uncountable number of work parts in graduate school[^1], making 
[^1] I can see this by looking at my handwriting

When I switch, it can feel like a reset button in my brain is pressed, and I start all over instead of picking up where I just left off. Because I do not have much differentiation between my parts[^3], I often don't realize I've switched---I may just abruptly do something different to what I've previously been doing without awareness that I should be doing something else. For example, I may be working and switch to a part with no awareness of work, so I'll go do something else while that part is out and it's only when I switch to a part with awareness of work do I realize I wasn't working when I should have been. 
[^3]: I'm actively working on learning how to internally differentiate between my parts so I can sort this mess out.


I have an extremely constricted, compartmentalized awareness so that at any given time, I only have a partial understanding of my entire life, and my ability to track time between parts varies. 


It seems like I only have a full sense of time surrounding the compartment I currently am in, and when I switch between compartments it can feel like time restarts[^1].
[^1]: This seems to depend on how much the parts are familiar with each other. Some switches, which I like to call shifts, feel nearly seamless, while others, between parts who have more amnesia for each other, can feel more jarring.

For most of my life, having such a constricted awareness has been useful.
For example, as a child, this allowed me to have a compartment for when I was in an abusive situation, and a different compartment for when I was at school. Separating these experiences was beneficial---it made it so that when I was at school I had no awareness of my abusive environment, so it didn't affect me as much.
When I was in school, I was able to focus on school, and when I was in an abusive situation, I was able to focus my energy on getting through it. Separating these worlds allowed me to learn and grow as a child while simultaneously experiencing abuse. 
It seems like the shuffling of my sense of time is a side effect of my constricted awareness.

Now as an adult, I've continued to live my life in such a compartmentalized way that I'm only fully aware of what is currently going on in the compartment I am in---I've learned to live life in the moment-to-moment, without a more broad awareness of my past and future.

This level of constricted awareness has made my day-to-day functioning difficult.

I learned how to split parts and compartmentalize experiences as a coping mechanism as a young child, and because it was so effective, I've continued to use it as an adult. For me, what started as a beneficial coping mechanism seems to have gone out of control as I've used this strategy to cope with adult stressors. As a result, I now have many parts that I switch between on a regular basis with varying degrees of awareness between them. When I was younger, I seemed to have a much more structured and organized system, with each part having a unique job. Now, my system is much more chaotic, with multiple parts vying for the same job. So, for example, I have multiple different work parts that don't have full communication between them, so I can do one session of work as one part and then when I inevitably switch to a different work part, I may have difficulty picking up where the last part took off. This wasn't always the case---for most of my undergraduate years, I only had 2 main work parts who seemed to work well together. I only created many work parts when my work became a major source of stress in graduate school. Now, I have countless work parts with that don't have full awareness between them[^2].

[^2]: This can be verified by looking how my handwriting has changed through the years.
Externally, this appears that I am slacking on my work responsibilities, but in reality the intention is different---sometimes I genuinely do not know I am supposed to be working.









<!--
, as each part had its role in my life so I 


However, the way I seem to experience this is incredibly subtle.
How does this affect me?
it allows me to only be aware of the activities current environment that I am in. 
 It seems as though if Part A is active for  a period of time and Part B takes over, when Part A is active again (or, when I am in Part A's compartment of memory again), stuff that occurred when Part B was out feels like it occured longer ago than when Part A was active.
I suspect that others with more identity alteration would 

These experiences are just subtle enough for me to question if they are actually significant, or if everyone experiences them and I'm just being . 
Because the way I navigate throughout life involves switching between compartments of memory, and when I'm in one compartment I may remember different things about my life due to what I experienced while I was in that compartment of memory in the past, my awareness at any given time is constricted.

When the abused part was out, I would be able to focus all of my energy on minimizing the abuse, 

. What exactly I'm aware of depends on which memory compartment I'm in.
-->
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/shuffledawareness/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/shuffledawareness/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 21:19:32 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Shuffled sense of time</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>DID is very much internal disorder. That is, unless I tell you I have it, you wouldn&rsquo;t know<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. One of the ways DID affects my internal experience is that I have significant gaps in my memory, both of my past childhood, and of my present adulthood.
But amnesia is tricky&mdash;I don&rsquo;t know what I don&rsquo;t remember, so most of the time I don&rsquo;t realize I&rsquo;ve forgotten anything.</p>
<p>I believe I experience amnesia in a few ways.
The most innocuous type that I experience seems due to me having constricted awareness&mdash;each of my parts seems to act as a compartment of memory, so when I&rsquo;m in one compartment it may be difficult for me to index memories that occurred when I was in a different compartment of memory.
For example, if my partner talks about a hike we went on a few months ago when I&rsquo;m in a task-based compartment for cleaning, I may not remember the hike, but I may eventually get a very vague memory of it if they prompt me about it further. If I see a picture of us on the hike, it may help queue my memory of it more, but it still isn&rsquo;t a complete memory like it would be if I were in the compartment that was actually there on that hike.
I believe this is because hiking and cleaning occupy two entirely different compartments of my life; there&rsquo;s little in common between the two, and my constricted awareness makes it so that these memories aren&rsquo;t shared well between the two parts. This seems to be a version of state-dependent memory.</p>
<p>I also experience full amnesia between parts. That is, I will not have access to any of the memories of one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This typically seems to occur between compartments that hold trauma memories and ones that do not, but I also seem to experience this between non-trauma holding parts, and I&rsquo;m not yet sure why.</p>
<p>Within full amnesia, I seem to exhibit two types. The first is when I experience a discrete jump in my awareness when I switch between compartments where I have no idea what was happening just before the switch. This causes an obvious jump in my awareness, and may make it more noticeable that I have amnesia. I might find myself, all of a sudden, in a different room than I remember being in just a second ago, when in reality another part had moved me to that room outside of my awareness<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I experienced this when I was younger<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, but not as much as I&rsquo;ve gotten older. Now, I more so seem to have a sliding-window type memory&mdash;rather than a discrete jump in awareness, my memory of what happened gradually disappears over several minutes after a switch. This leads to a perceived smoother transition between parts, making my memory loss less obvious to me.</p>
<p>Regardless of the type of amnesia I have, I experience shuffling of memories and time jumps&mdash;I do not have a continuous, linear understanding of my life. For example, it may be hard for me to differentiate what occurred last week vs what occurred years ago, and sometimes things that occurred months ago feel more current to me than things that occurred even yesterday. As always, this seems to be justified by my understanding of how I operate&mdash;if I&rsquo;m in a compartment of memory that was last active a few months ago, those memories are more at the forefront of my awareness than memories formed in a different compartment yesterday.
This leads to a lot of confusing experiences, like looking out of my window and expecting it to be winter but seeing that it&rsquo;s actually summer, or all of a sudden noticing that the furniture in my apartment has moved from what I last remember, or looking at my plants and being amazed by how much they had grown because I remembered them being much smaller.
These sorts of experiences occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still early on in my DID discovery journey, so my understanding of my amnesia will likely change over time as I learn more about how I operate.
I hope this post serves as a snapshot in time of my awareness of how I operate a little over one year after starting therapy.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Unless you catch me in a dissociative episode, which is very unlikely to happen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, I have never had a full dissociative fugue where I end up in an entirely different location than I was before. Most of my dissociative episodes occur at home when I&rsquo;m alone or in when I&rsquo;m in threapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This, along with other symptoms, led to me receiving a dissociative disorder diagnosis as a pre-teen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/amnesia/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/amnesia/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 12:10:19 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative amnesia</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Imagine if, without your awareness, your deepest, most repressed thoughts and feelings were displayed for the world to see. With how my DID presents, this is something that occurs quite frequently for me. Because much of my most difficult emotions are separated from the core me, I am usually unaware of them until they surface and they&rsquo;re in the forefront of my awareness. Then, after they are over, I may forget that these dissociative episodes ever happened. This has led to me into many scary and sometimes dangerous situations, which typically leave me puzzled by what is happening in the world around me.</p>
<p>As an example, I like to go on evening walks for exercise. I typically walk one of a few routes in the densely populated city I live in. One day this past summer, I walked by a person who had some of the same characteristics as someone who caused me harm in the past. I walked by this individual without awareness that I was at all triggered. Then, in a split second, they started yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&rsquo;re scared of me, huh? What do you have to be scared about?&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>What?</em> It was so out of context for me; I had no idea why they were yelling at me. I wasn&rsquo;t scared of them&mdash;up until they started yelling at me, I hadn&rsquo;t even noticed them. I ignored them and calmly kept walking in the direction I was going. Then, they started moving towards me <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, continually yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why are you scared of me? You think I&rsquo;m threatening? There&rsquo;s nothing to be scared about!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I sped up walking and continued ignoring them. I felt very calm while this was happening, although I was confused by what going on. I eventually made it to the next block over and lost sight of them. I calmly walked home, and went out of my way to reassure myself that I had done nothing wrong, and that the person was at fault, not me. But <em>why</em> did this person think I was scared of them? Was I scared of them?</p>
<p>As it turns out, a part of me <em>was</em> scared of them. When I saw that person, that part became so scared, that they momentarily took control of my face and made a scared microexpression, directed at that person. However, I had no awareness that I was scared of them or that I had made any facial expression. This is because the parts of me who were on my evening walk were not connected with the part of me that was scared of the person, so from the perspective of the part of me that was going on a walk, I had no idea that anything abnormal was happening, while the scared part was simultaneously terrified.</p>
<p>Over the next few days, I intentionally went on my evening walk, purposefully walking past the location of the event to ensure I didn&rsquo;t associate anything negative with it. The parts of me walking felt perfectly fine, and I didn&rsquo;t realize anything was off.
Then, within a week, without realizing it, I stopped going on my evening walks. A month went by, and I still avoided walking, but it didn&rsquo;t even occur to me that I stopped.
I went from walking every day for months to only leaving my apartment when absolutely necessary. I didn&rsquo;t feel any fear associated with walking or leaving my apartment, but it was clearly there, dictating my behavior. It took over a month for me to realize anything was wrong, and once I pondered why I was no longer walking the reason became obvious&mdash;a part of me was still clearly scared of what had happened on that walk.
In order to get back to my walking routine, I gradually had to show that part that we were safe, and that that wasn&rsquo;t going to happen again, and even if it did, there were other parts who could take care of the situation like we had done last time. With this awareness in mind, over time, I managed to get back to going on my evening walks.</p>
<p>This is one example of how having DID affects my life and functioning. Before I became aware that I have DID, I was unaware of how much influence my parts had over my life. My behaviors are influenced by fear I cannot even grasp onto or feel. Other people may be more aware of my own internal state than even I am, since my body language may be contradictory to how I feel on the inside.
Getting to know my parts is helping me to become more aware of my internal state, and, in turn, will allow me to live a more complete life.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, they used a walker, so I was in little danger.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/partscontrol/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/partscontrol/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:30:21 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>The parts I don’t know about still have control</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was initially hesitant to write about anger, as it&rsquo;s an emotion I am not used to feeling<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
How could I write about something I know nothing about?
But I now realize that the absence of anger in my life is significant in itself, and is indicative of how I operate.</p>
<p>Anger is an emotion that I am simultaneously very sensitive to, yet not at all familar with&mdash;I am incredibly sensitive to the external display of anger in others, yet not at all familiar with how it feels internally.
I believe this is because when I was small, I grew up in an environment where my primary caregiver frequently displayed anger.
This is because they had unprocessed trauma of their own, which came out as fits of rage.
These bouts of anger were extremely terrifying for me as a young child, and ended in emotional and sometimes physical harm done to me.
Because of the repeated association of anger with terror, pain, and instability, I believe I learned to internally separate anger as a &ldquo;bad&rdquo; emotion, and shoved it away as an emotion that I did not want to experience.
My relationship with anger was tainted by my early childhood experiences, making a powerful emotion that should be utilized as part of an emotionally healthy life inaccessible to me as an adult.</p>
<p>I once naively believed that not feeling anger was an asset of mine&mdash;that anger was a disruptive emotion, and it was safer for me not to feel it. While it is beneficial to those around me for me to not ever display anger, I now believe that anger is an important emotion that should be part of my emotional repertoire.
Anger enables people to enact change. By my not being able to experience anger, I&rsquo;m more likely to stay involved in situations and environments which are not good for me, making me to be more likely to be repeatedly victimized.
Due to my upbringing, I learned to value other peoples' comfort over my own, and use dissociation to subconsciously withhold my sometimes justified anger.</p>
<p>I believe that because I have DID<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, my dynamic range of emotions is very shallow&mdash;most of the time, I feel mild contentment. I grew up in an environment where I didn&rsquo;t feel like I could take up any emotional space, as the emotional landscape in my family of origin was dominated by others' strong emotional displays. I enjoy my internal stability&mdash;I do not want to feel strong emotions. I am scared of the loss of control I was so used to seeing in others while growing up.
However, this separation of anger and other emotions leads to a less full life, including amnesia, behavior that feels out of my control when I&rsquo;m triggered, along with stunted &ldquo;good&rdquo; emotions, like happiness and excitement. By using dissociation, I&rsquo;ve traded experiencing a full range of emotions for internal stability. This served me well in the past, but in the future I&rsquo;d like to live a more full, complete life&mdash;one that does not rely on maladaptive dissociative coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>While I now see anger as a valuable emotion, my learned patterns of removing it from my awareness continue, so still I have difficulty accessing it.
My understanding of anger comes from a theoretical view&mdash;I can intellectually understand it, but I do not believe I have felt genuine anger before. With time, I hope that will change.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>And maybe I was right to be hesitant, as I don&rsquo;t have much to say since I&rsquo;m early in my awareness journey, but I want to document my understanding of things at various stages of healing.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I believe I am this way due to how I responded to experiences in my childhood, which resulted in me forming maladaptive coping mechanisms which can be labeled DID.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/anger/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/anger/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 11:05:58 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anger</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from minutes to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
My internal awareness of my life is also shuffled, so I may have a hard time differentiating what happened yesterday versus what happened last week or last month, or struggle with remembering if, for example, a cold I have today is new or if I was also sick yesterday.
It can feel like every day a reset button in my brain is pressed, and I start all over instead of picking up where I left off yesterday.
This can affect my daily functioning significantly.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I use <em>switch</em> to denote a hard, discrete change between parts, which usually occurs when I&rsquo;m triggered and can be disorienting. I use <em>shift</em> to denote a smooth change between parts, which occurs more often than switching for me and can internally feel like a gear shifting in my brain.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12, I stopped feeling anxiety. Prior to that, I was a child ravished by anxiety. Then, one day, it stopped <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. And I have never experienced anxiety in the same way since.</p>
<p>I now understand that anxiety is one of the experiences that I dissociated away&mdash;it&rsquo;s a state that I did not enjoy experiencing, so I learned how to compartmentalize it and push it out of my awareness.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean I do not <em>experience</em> anxiety; rather, it means that when I do, I am so detached from it that I do not experience all aspects of it.</p>
<p>My body trembles, lower lip quivers, and heart races, yet I don&rsquo;t know why I am experiencing these physical symptoms.
My mind races with irrational thought loops, yet I can&rsquo;t quite grasp onto them so they feel like meaningless noise to me.
I am disconnected and emotionally numb. Except for when I am not.</p>
<p>When I am able to connect with the feeling of anxiety, it is all-encompassing and feels everlasting. When something triggers anxiety to the forefront of my awareness, it is all I can concentrate on, and I will do whatever I need to do to alleviate the feeling. Then, all of a sudden, it goes away as quickly as it came, and after it&rsquo;s over I gradually forget that it ever happened.</p>
<p>Right now, as I write this, I do not know what anxiety feels like. Parts of me do, but I am not connected with those parts. For the most part, I feel like an emotionless machine, going through the motions of life. Despite the fact that I&rsquo;m unable to connect with anxiety, that doesn&rsquo;t mean it doesn&rsquo;t affect me. My behaviors are controlled by fear and anxiety that I cannot feel&mdash;I can only intellectually infer that I am being affected by anxiety by examining my behaviors. I avoid leaving my apartment, interacting with others, and doing things that may eventually lead to stressful situations. Yet I do not experience the associated emotions with these behaviors&mdash;I am numb.</p>
<p>When I was 12, I didn&rsquo;t become a less anxious person&mdash;I just became more detached from my anxiety. My crippling anxiety wasn&rsquo;t miraculously cured. Instead, it was like fixing a wound that needed stitches with a band-aid&mdash;an easy, temporary solution that left me worse-off in the long term.</p>
<p>In order to decrease my amnesia and regain control of my life, I need to connect back with my anxiety.
Although it allows me to avoid difficult feelings in the moment, my current method of dealing with anxiety&mdash;compartmentalizing it and shoving it from my awareness&mdash;leads to uncontrollable fear-based behavior, a lack of internal awareness, and amnesia. I need to connect with this destabilizing experience once again, this time working though it instead of shoving it from my awareness. Then, I can address its root causes and gain control of my life again.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My mom reports me having a discrete personality change when this occurred.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/anxiety/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/anxiety/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 19:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anxiety</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have always been nerdy. From a young age, I immersed myself in academic work, as I enjoyed learning and the strict routine that school provided for me. I also had an intense need to perform well&mdash;my perfectionistic tendencies dominated my life as a child. While I often did perform well academically, there were times where I performed markedly poorly on assessments, so far outside the norm of what would have ordinarily be expected of me, despite preparing and knowing the material. For example, on one occasion in high school, I was so prepared for an exam that I helped tutor my friends about the material leading up to it, only for me to fail while they performed well. I wasn&rsquo;t ordinarily a bad test taker&mdash;I genuinely didn&rsquo;t understand the material when exam time came. To put it simply, there were times when I was smart, and times when I was&hellip; not. I  now understand this to be as a result of having DID.</p>
<p>Some of my parts were formed when I was a small child. When I am in these compartments, although I may be aware that I am an adult, I typically have the mental ability of around the age in which those parts developed. These compartments are essentially snapshots of my mindset at the time they were created, with varying levels of awareness of the present day. One major implication of this is that my ability to understand information varies depending on which compartment of awareness I am in. For example, I have a younger, very timid part that sometimes comes out that has the math ability of a middle schooler. When this part is active, I am unable to grasp onto the complex topics required of me for my PhD that I can normally do with relative ease when the right part of me is active. I am not aware of what I do not know, believing what I know in that moment is all that I do know. This part of me often comes out around others while I&rsquo;m supposed to be having intellectual discussions. The results are humiliating&mdash;I am unable to discuss even my own research, which the right parts of me are very familiar with. Many a time I have left a meeting feeling absolutely defeated and frustrated that I was unable to discuss my research properly. However, there were other times, when the correct parts were out, that I was very much able to hold an academic discussion about my work. My fluctuating knowledge of my work has detrimentally impacted my academic career thus far.</p>
<p>Before I knew I had DID, I never questioned my fluctuating levels of intelligence. However, I did come up with a justification for my poor performance&mdash;when I was in compartments that weren&rsquo;t aware of my more academic parts, I truly believed that I was dumber than all of my peers. I believed that any time I had performed well I had cheated, and I had faked my way to where I am today as a PhD student. There are times where I&rsquo;d look at my academic papers, ones that I had written, and not only did I not understand what the material was about, but I didn&rsquo;t fully remember writing them. I developed extreme imposter syndrome as a result of this&mdash;I truly didn&rsquo;t feel like I belonged in my institution, and I believed that I had genuine reasons as to why.</p>
<p>It has only been within the last several months that I&rsquo;ve been able to identify when I&rsquo;m in a compartment of awareness that is not necessarily able to understand the material required of me in order to complete my degree, and I now see that the difference in ability is pronounced. When this part of me is active, I now stop working and try to understand why it is out. What is preventing me from accessing the compartments of me that do work? Sometimes the answer is obvious; other times, I&rsquo;m not so sure. Most frequently, however, I don&rsquo;t realize that a non-academic part has been out until after it has already gone, when I relook at a problem that I was previously agonizing over and it becomes obvious. I&rsquo;m still trying to understand these parts of myself, but just knowing that my having DID explains much of my academic distress really helps me understand why I am the way that I am.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 21:52:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Fluctuating intelligence</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
