







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="http://www.lico.blog/tags/symptoms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>symptoms</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>http://www.lico.blog/tags/symptoms/</link>
        
        
            <title>symptoms</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>DID is very much internal disorder. That is, unless I tell you I have it, you wouldn&rsquo;t know <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. One of the ways DID affects my internal experience is that I have significant gaps in my memory, both of my past childhood, and of my present adulthood.
But amnesia is tricky&mdash;I don&rsquo;t know what I don&rsquo;t remember, so most of the time I don&rsquo;t realize I&rsquo;ve forgotten anything.</p>
<p>I believe I experience amnesia in a few ways.
The most innocuous type that I experience seems due to me having constricted awareness&mdash;each of my parts seems to act as a compartment of memory, so when I&rsquo;m in one compartment it may be difficult for me to index memories that occurred when I was in a different compartment of memory.
For example, if my partner talks about a hike we went on a few months ago when I&rsquo;m in a task-based compartment for cleaning, I may not remember the hike, but I may eventually get a very vague memory of it if they prompt me about it further. If I see a picture of us on the hike, it may help queue my memory of it more, but it still isn&rsquo;t a complete memory like it would be if I were in the compartment that was actually there on that hike.
I believe this is because hiking and cleaning occupy two entirely different compartments of my life; there&rsquo;s little in common between the two, and my constricted awareness makes it so that these memories aren&rsquo;t shared well between the two parts. This seems to be a version of state-dependent memory.</p>
<p>I also experience full amnesia between parts. That is, I will not have access to any of the memories of one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This typically seems to occur between compartments that hold trauma memories and ones that do not, but I also seem to experience this between non-trauma holding parts, and I&rsquo;m not yet sure why.</p>
<p>Within full amnesia, I seem to exhibit two types. The first is when I experience a discrete jump in my awareness when I switch between compartments where I have no idea what was happening just before the switch. This causes an obvious jump in my awareness, and may make it more noticeable that I have amnesia. I might find myself, all of a sudden, in a different room than I remember being in just a second ago, when in reality another part had moved me to that room outside of my awareness<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I experienced this when I was younger<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, but not as much as I&rsquo;ve gotten older. Now, I more so seem to have a sliding-window type memory&mdash;rather than a discrete jump in awareness, my memory of what happened gradually disappears over several minutes after a switch. This leads to a perceived smoother transition between parts, making my memory loss less obvious to me.</p>
<p>Regardless of the type of amnesia I have, I experience shuffling of memories and time jumps&mdash;I do not have a continuous, linear understanding of my life. For example, it may be hard for me to differentiate what occurred last week vs what occurred years ago, and sometimes things that occurred months ago feel more current to me than things that occurred even yesterday. As always, this seems to be justified by my understanding of how I operate&mdash;if I&rsquo;m in a compartment of memory that was last active a few months ago, those memories are more at the forefront of my awareness than memories formed in a different compartment yesterday.
This leads to a lot of confusing experiences, like looking out of my window and expecting it to be winter but seeing that it&rsquo;s actually summer, or all of a sudden noticing that the furniture in my apartment has moved from what I last remember, or looking at my plants and being amazed by how much they had grown because I remembered them being much smaller.
These sorts of experiences occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still early on in my DID discovery journey, so my understanding of my amnesia will likely change over time as I learn more about how I operate.
I hope this post serves as a snapshot in time of my awareness of how I operate a little over one year after starting therapy.</p>
<!--

How does one know if the way they experience the world is _normal_? It never even occurred to me that aspects my experience could be considered disordered until recently. Now that I'm aware, so much of my life makes sense. 

The way I experience amnesia seems to be more nuanced than what I have described here thus far, but I haven't formulated the words to fully describe these experiences yet.


These experiences can be explained by me switching between compartments of memory that I haven't been in in a while, and occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.

Another type of amnesia that some people with dissociative disorders report[^3] is emotional amnesia, where they remember the events of what happened when they're in a different compartment, but don't have the associated emotions attached with that memory. I believe I experience this too, but because of the structure of my DID, I believe almost all of my memories do not have associated emotions attached to them[^6]. This seems to be my normal memory, so for me 
the distinction between experiencing emotional amnesia or having a "normal" memory isn't clear. I don't believe I often experience strong emotions[^4], though, so I'm not sure if I'm experiencing some sort of amnesia or if I just don't have the associated emotions to encode in my memories. 
[^4]: I don't remember what I don't remember, so maybe I do experience strong emotions more than I think; I'm honestly not sure.
[^3]: I learned about this from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit
[^6]: Also, most, if not all, of my memories seem to be in third person, even if they aren't trauma related. This may be why I don't have the first-person perspective of emotion attached to them.


In fact, one way I can differentiate between my parts is by 

it isn't clear if I could be experiencing something different.

so out of context for a part of me that cleans because it seems like a different section of my life.

I personally see myself as having three types of amnesia.

This memory will not be clear, and often has a "not me" feeling associated with it---it can feel like I'm indexing someone else's memories

I'm used to living with a constricted internal awareness that realizing I have amensia isn't surprising to me much anymore---it seems to be a normal part of my 

I'm only aware I'm in a different compartment when looking back in time. In the moment-to-moment, I always feel like _me_. That is; my sense of "I" does not change. This is why I like to conceptualize my experience as me switching between different compartments rather than 

Now that I know what switching feels like, I realize that I have day-to-day amnesia. 

When I look backat the 

I also often have the experience of 
Memory is tricky. When I think about my life, I am unaware I have amnesia

My whole life, I've had experiences where people claimed I had done things I had absolutely no memory of doing. These things seemed like things I would absolutely never do, and to be honest, I never thought too much about it.

In high school, I saw the same group of friends in class that I did outside of school. I clearly had different parts 

So now, looking back, of course I had amnesia. However, it's a lot more hidden than one would expect, because I simply do not remember what I do not remember. It's only when I have external sources notifying me that something happened that I didn't remember do I realize I must have had amnesia. 

It's honestly really scary know that I could potentially forget what I am doing right now in the future. How much of my life will I remember? Are these memories I'm making in my life encoding properly? I sure hope so---I don't want gaps in my memory.

With that being said, because I truly don't know what I don't know, I'm often not aware I'm missing anything.

My justification for these events was always that the other person was lying,

Is it amnesia proper, or is it just my awareness is so shuffled since I switch between many different compartments of memory in a day? 

At the end of the day, when my partner and I ask each other how our days were, I can typically give him a general impression of how the day went---I remember the major events 



One of the hardest parts of my DID discovery journey is coming to terms that I did, in fact, do those things. I had dissociated---putting me in a different compartment of awareness with a different mindset.

Who I thought I was is not who I actually was. Some parts 

I have difficulties tracking the passage of time. 
When I wake up in the morning, I have to orient myself to what day it 
Because I have so many different parts with varying levels of memory sharing between them, there are times where I won't know what I'm doing moment-to-moment.
the way I encoded and accessed memories was different from most others

In this case, it's not that I don't remember what happened when I was in a different compartment. 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Unless you catch me in a dissociative episode, which is very unlikely to happen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, I have never had a full dissociative fugue where I end up in an entirely different location than I was before. Most of my dissociative episodes occur at home, so the scariest thing might be I find myself hiding under the blanets of my bed when I thought I was in my kitchen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This, along with other symptoms, led to me receiving a dissociative disorder diagnosis as a pre-teen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/amnesia/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/amnesia/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 12:10:19 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative amnesia</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from days to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
This can affect my daily functioning significantly.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<!--

I'm only at the beginning of my journey to discovering how I operate, and I'm learning more about my system every day. 

At the very begining of my journey to discovering how I operate, I never could have imagined that I had this chaotic of a system. 

I am not a singular part, with other parts being "other" to me, which is how some people seem to conceptualize having DID.
Rather, I am all of my parts, and all of my parts are me. These parts seem to represent pieces of the whole me. My life is fragmented into many different compartments that I switch between. Depending on which compartment I am in, I will have a different internal experience. For the most part, externally, there is not much differentiation between my parts. You will likely not be able to tell when one part is out vs a different part is out.



Many of my parts share memory and are cooperative with one another.
Right now, as I write this, 
up until recently, I was just as dysfunctional, but I didn't know I was because I didn't know I had DID and daily amnesia. Now that I am much more aware of what is going on in my life, I have full confidence that I will become more functional again soon. I have been very functional living with this disorder in the recent past, so I have full faith I'll get there again, this time with much more awareness of how I operate.






I seem to use parts differently than the most-shared representations of DID portray. Because of this, it took me an incredibly long time to see in myself that I had DID. 






I'd like to note that while I use the word "dysfunctional" to describe myself, I'm actually very high-functioning in most areas of my life. 
I use the word dysfunctional to describe the fact that this disorder is impacting my day-to-day functioning, making it hard to do the things I want to do. This is because my internal awareness is so fragmented that I do not have continuity of memory, and I have clusters of parts with different interests trying to live life in different ways, causing internal division. However, in many aspects of life, I am living functionally.



I'm using my dissociative coping mecahanisms to protect me from what could be objectively considered a difficult time, just as I have in the past. For the most part, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview. Dissociation is an amazing coping mechanism. 


For what it's worth, the labels I use to describe how I function make it seem like my life is a lot worse than it actually is. Despite the internal chaos and amnesia, I, for the most part, enjoy how I operate. I realize 

Thus, when I am triggered in the present day, I have to switch between a series of parts in rapid succession before switching back to an untraumatized part.
I am also able to take care of myself well, but 


This is the most descriptive word I've found used in the literature and online communities that represents how I experience having DID.
Most of my parts share memory between them, so switching/shifting can almost be undetectable to me. However, I do experience amnesia between some parts that come out nearly daily.
I seem to split parts easily and in a complex manner. 

With these splitting patterns, this means I have a lot of parts.

When I was young, I likely would not qualify as polyframented---my rate of part creation has increased as I aged 

I seem to have parts created to do jobs for me. For example, I have a few different parts dedicated to cleaning, a part for brushing my showering, and even a sequence of parts dedicated to getting me from putting my VR headset on to in my VR game as quickly/without my awareness as possible. My definition of what constitutes part creation is so low that a game loading screen made me create parts.

[^1]: _[The phenomenology and treatment of extremely complex multiple personality disorder](https://scholarsbank.uoregon.edu/xmlui/bitstream/handle/1794/1396/Diss_1_4_8_OCR_rev.pdf)_. Richard Kluft, 1998. 

This is not a word I've seen in the academic literature, although Richard Kluft seems to describe similar phenomena in one of his papers[^1], so it's not concretely defined. To me, the word polyfragmented means a person who has many parts and/or splits them in a complex fashion. I believe I fall under the category of both. 
Because my understanding of DID was that of a more traditional presentation, I initially did not believe I had this disorder, despite having clear cases of amnesia. However, over time, I found that my presentation was simply different to the traditional presentation. It seems as though I 


rather than having a relatively few number of well-defined parts, 


Reading about experiences of people who self-identify as polyfragmented helped me to see that this label makes the most sense to me.

Because I switch so much, my relationship with time 

Rather than a few clearly defined parts, it seems as though my entire personality is split into multiple parts

My internal experience is extremely compartmentalized. When my symptoms are bad, I'm often living day-to-day, or even moment-to-moment, unaware of what I had previously been doing or what my next plans are. I feel like I'm in a state of survival---I just need to get through this moment onto the next day. This was a mindset I used as a child when I had to get through my current situation, but trusted there were good times ahead. I'd do whatever I could to pass time, to distract myself of the present moment so once the good times came, I could 

When times are good, 

However, in my adult life, this is a 
When I began graduate school, everything was stressful, and I was nearly constantly in this living moment-to-moment mindset, unable to take a step back and examine that 


I relied upon as a child to get me through times that were extremely stressful---I perceived the present moment as being bad, but I had faith that in the future. I used this when I had to get through a situation that took a long time

---the present moment is bad, but maybe the future will be better. I just need to get through this present moment to getas long as I could make it through the present moment, maybe the next. 

It took me several months of therapy with a dissociative disorders specialist in order for me to even consider that I had DID, despite having a pediatric dissociative disorder diagnosis. Like many others would in my generation, as soon as I realized I was being assessed for DID, I immediately went to sites like Reddit and YouTube to see how other people with this disorder conceptualize their experiences. Needless to say, I did not relate to others' experiences that I found online. Most people I had encountered seemed to have a relatively small number clearly defined parts with clear roles. I genuinely did not believe that I had DID, despite the fact that I was frequently dissociating in therapy sessions without realizing I was doing so. 

Why do I have so many parts? The threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals---things that would be considered traumatic to me may not have affected another child as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, along with the fact that I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there's a high correlation of those who are polyfragmented and have autism.

What does this mean? It is my understanding that typically, individuals with DID split a few to several well defined parts---they don't have too many different compartments they switch between.


used colloquially to mean a system with many parts, typically with complex splitting patterns. 

I do not seem to experience this. Instead, 

I've also learned that I have many different types of parts and mechanisms for part creation.
I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch[^6] between parts on a very regular basis.
Additionally, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to create many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event. 
I also do not only split parts due to trauma---I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged[^7]. 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I use <em>switch</em> to denote a hard, discrete change between parts, which usually occurs when I&rsquo;m triggered and can be disorienting. I use <em>shift</em> to denote a smooth change between parts, which occurs more often than switching for me and can internally feel like a gear shifting in my brain.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12, I stopped feeling anxiety. Prior to that, I was a child ravished by anxiety. Then, one day, it stopped <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. And I have never experienced anxiety in the same way since.</p>
<p>I now understand that anxiety is one of the experiences that I dissociated away&mdash;it&rsquo;s a state that I did not enjoy experiencing, so I learned how to compartmentalize it and push it out of my awareness.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean I do not <em>experience</em> anxiety; rather, it means that when I do, I am so detached from it that I do not experience all aspects of it.</p>
<p>My body trembles, lower lip quivers, and heart races, yet I don&rsquo;t know why I am experiencing these physical symptoms.
My mind races with irrational thought loops, yet I can&rsquo;t quite grasp onto them so they feel like meaningless noise to me.
I am disconnected and emotionally numb. Except for when I am not.</p>
<p>When I am able to connect with the feeling of anxiety, it is all-encompassing and feels everlasting. When something triggers anxiety to the forefront of my awareness, it is all I can concentrate on, and I will do whatever I need to do to alleviate the feeling. Then, all of a sudden, it goes away as quickly as it came, and after it&rsquo;s over I gradually forget that it ever happened.</p>
<p>Right now, as I write this, I do not know what anxiety feels like. Parts of me do, but I am not connected with those parts. For the most part, I feel like an emotionless machine, going through the motions of life. Despite the fact that I&rsquo;m unable to connect with anxiety, that doesn&rsquo;t mean it doesn&rsquo;t affect me. My behaviors are controlled by fear and anxiety that I cannot feel&mdash;I can only intellectually infer that I am being affected by anxiety by examining my behaviors. I avoid leaving my apartment, interacting with others, and doing things that may eventually lead to stressful situations. Yet I do not experience the associated emotions with these behaviors&mdash;I am numb.</p>
<p>When I was 12, I didn&rsquo;t become a less anxious person&mdash;I just became more detached from my anxiety. My crippling anxiety wasn&rsquo;t miraculously cured. Instead, it was like fixing a wound that needed stitches with a band-aid&mdash;an easy, temporary solution that left me worse-off in the long term.</p>
<p>In order to decrease my amnesia and regain control of my life, I need to connect back with my anxiety.
Although it allows me to avoid difficult feelings in the moment, my current method of dealing with anxiety&mdash;compartmentalizing it and shoving it from my awareness&mdash;leads to uncontrollable fear-based behavior, a lack of internal awareness, and amnesia. I need to connect with this destabilizing experience once again, this time working though it instead of shoving it from my awareness. Then, I can address its root causes and gain control of my life again.</p>
<!--

I have a very curated internal experience---emotionally, I feel 

The irrational thought loops 
At least not in a normal way anymore. 

DID shapes the way I experience emotions.

Different aspects of my life are compartmentalized 

When I was a child, I was filled with worry. 
-->
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My mom reports me having a discrete personality change when this occurred.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>http://www.lico.blog/posts/anxiety/</guid>
                    <link>http://www.lico.blog/posts/anxiety/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 19:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anxiety</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
