







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/reddit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>reddit</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/reddit/</link>
        
        
            <title>reddit</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>There seems to be a dominant representation of DID in online discourse. Mostly, it seems as though people represent themselves as having a handful of well-defined parts, each with distinct names, ages, and characteristics. Perhaps because I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented/">polyfragmented</a>, I experience something very different, and do not relate to the vast majority of the experiences that other people present themselves as having online. Last month, I posted to <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/DID/">the DID subreddit</a> to see if anyone related to my experiences:</p>





<div class="paige-quote">
    <blockquote class="blockquote"><p>I&rsquo;m wondering if anyone relates to my experiences, as I have not seen this representation of DID anywhere in the literature/online.</p>
<p>I have polyfragmented DID, with low identity alteration, day-to-day amnesia, and lots of switching (10-100+ times a day).</p>
<p>The last several years of my life have been a blur. However, I have been logging data about myself for the past ~2 years, and I have now accumulated enough to notice patterns. From this, it seems like my parts exhibit cyclical behavior. It seems like I have one part as my dominant part for anywhere from several hours to a few weeks. During this time, other task-based and trauma-holding parts seem to &ldquo;come out&rdquo; of that dominant part as needed. Eventually, a new dominant part takes over, and lasts a chunk of time before a different one takes over. After I have cycled through all of these dominant parts, they repeat in a similar order, with a period lasting ~3-5 months. Occasionally, new parts are added to this cycle. I have not yet gained enough internal awareness to know which &ldquo;part of the cycle&rdquo; I am in in a given moment, but if I look back at my data, it&rsquo;s clear that I have cyclical patterns across several different data points.</p>
<p>Does anyone here exhibit anything similar to this? Do you know of others that experience this system structure? Do you have any tips for the recovery process?</p>
<p>With this awareness, my life makes a whole lot more sense. I spend much of my time confused and out of date about where I am in life, as many of my parts are unaware of large aspects of my life. Because my dominant parts switch so readily, I&rsquo;m repeatedly having to re-update myself about my life circumstances (if I&rsquo;m even aware enough about my current life to do so!), and since these parts only repeat every few months, each part of me feels like they are losing large chunks of time. Life is so chaotic right now. I am in therapy 2x a week and am slowly making, and subsequently losing, progress. Any advice is appreciated.</p>
</blockquote>

    
</div>

<p>You can view the original Reddit post <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/DID/comments/166f8ui/polyfragmented_did_cycling_between_parts/">here</a>.
I received a lot of comments on this post, with many people relating to my experiences and sharing their own.</p>
<p>I feel like this is a very uncomfortable and unknown form of DID to have. My sense of self changes so rapidly, and internally things are very chaotic. It&rsquo;s hard to definitively describe what I&rsquo;m experiencing, as things change quickly enough that I often forget what I previously discovered. The only way I am able to confirm that this is actually what I am going through is because I have compiled enough data about myself to determine that I have clear cyclical patterns (see <a href="/posts/systemdata/">Learning about my system with data</a>).
Internally, things were too chaotic for me to discover this pattern independently, but now that I know that this is how I work I can confirm the pattern fits with my internal experiences as well.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s reassuring to know that other people are going through similar experiences to me. At least one person said they experienced this at earlier stages of their recovery and their system is more stable now. I&rsquo;ve been in therapy for just over 1.5 years, and I believe this system pattern began in late 2019 due to the stress caused by my PhD qualifying exams. Before taking my qualifying exams, I had two main handwritings that would show up in my academic notes, and were stable for at least the previous 5 years. After my qualifying exams, which went horribly and could be considered traumatic for me, I gradually gained more and more different handwritings as more parts were being created and added to the cycle. Now, I have an uncountable number of distinct handwritings that I switch between seemingly cyclically.</p>
<p>It seems like, depending on which part of the cycle I am in, I have very different understandings of my life. I talk about this in <a href="/posts/howdidaffectswork/">How DID affects my work</a>. I can go for weeks where I am hyperfocused on work and advancing in my research, followed by weeks where I am mostly unaware that I am even a graduate student who is supposed to be working. I am trying hard to break this cycle, but it seems to be going strong. There have been several occasions where I believed I was able to stop my cycle (for example, see <a href="/posts/wakingup/">Waking up to the present</a>), but I always end up losing my awareness and advancing in the cycle. I hope someday soon my system will stabilize more so I can live the life I want to live and remain grounded to the reality of the present.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/redditrelate/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/redditrelate/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 12:25:20 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Do other people experience DID in the same way as me?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from minutes to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
Additionally, <a href="/posts/shuffledawareness/">my internal awareness of my life is shuffled</a>, so I do not have a linear narrative history of my life or day-to-day activities.
This can affect my daily functioning significantly.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I use <em>switch</em> to denote a hard, discrete change between parts, which usually occurs when I&rsquo;m triggered and can be disorienting. I use <em>shift</em> to denote a smooth change between parts, which occurs more often than switching for me and can internally feel like a gear shifting in my brain.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
