







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/topics/discovery/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>Discovery</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/topics/discovery/</link>
        
        
            <title>Discovery</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>There seems to be a dominant representation of DID in online discourse. Mostly, it seems as though people represent themselves as having a handful of well-defined parts, each with distinct names, ages, and characteristics. Perhaps because I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented/">polyfragmented</a>, I experience something very different, and do not relate to the vast majority of the experiences that other people present themselves as having online. Last month, I posted to <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/DID/">the DID subreddit</a> to see if anyone related to my experiences:</p>





<div class="paige-quote">
    <blockquote class="blockquote"><p>I&rsquo;m wondering if anyone relates to my experiences, as I have not seen this representation of DID anywhere in the literature/online.</p>
<p>I have polyfragmented DID, with low identity alteration, day-to-day amnesia, and lots of switching (10-100+ times a day).</p>
<p>The last several years of my life have been a blur. However, I have been logging data about myself for the past ~2 years, and I have now accumulated enough to notice patterns. From this, it seems like my parts exhibit cyclical behavior. It seems like I have one part as my dominant part for anywhere from several hours to a few weeks. During this time, other task-based and trauma-holding parts seem to &ldquo;come out&rdquo; of that dominant part as needed. Eventually, a new dominant part takes over, and lasts a chunk of time before a different one takes over. After I have cycled through all of these dominant parts, they repeat in a similar order, with a period lasting ~3-5 months. Occasionally, new parts are added to this cycle. I have not yet gained enough internal awareness to know which &ldquo;part of the cycle&rdquo; I am in in a given moment, but if I look back at my data, it&rsquo;s clear that I have cyclical patterns across several different data points.</p>
<p>Does anyone here exhibit anything similar to this? Do you know of others that experience this system structure? Do you have any tips for the recovery process?</p>
<p>With this awareness, my life makes a whole lot more sense. I spend much of my time confused and out of date about where I am in life, as many of my parts are unaware of large aspects of my life. Because my dominant parts switch so readily, I&rsquo;m repeatedly having to re-update myself about my life circumstances (if I&rsquo;m even aware enough about my current life to do so!), and since these parts only repeat every few months, each part of me feels like they are losing large chunks of time. Life is so chaotic right now. I am in therapy 2x a week and am slowly making, and subsequently losing, progress. Any advice is appreciated.</p>
</blockquote>

    
</div>

<p>You can view the original Reddit post <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/DID/comments/166f8ui/polyfragmented_did_cycling_between_parts/">here</a>.
I received a lot of comments on this post, with many people relating to my experiences and sharing their own.</p>
<p>I feel like this is a very uncomfortable and unknown form of DID to have. My sense of self changes so rapidly, and internally things are very chaotic. It&rsquo;s hard to definitively describe what I&rsquo;m experiencing, as things change quickly enough that I often forget what I previously discovered. The only way I am able to confirm that this is actually what I am going through is because I have compiled enough data about myself to determine that I have clear cyclical patterns (see <a href="/posts/systemdata/">Learning about my system with data</a>).
Internally, things were too chaotic for me to discover this pattern independently, but now that I know that this is how I work I can confirm the pattern fits with my internal experiences as well.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s reassuring to know that other people are going through similar experiences to me. At least one person said they experienced this at earlier stages of their recovery and their system is more stable now. I&rsquo;ve been in therapy for just over 1.5 years, and I believe this system pattern began in late 2019 due to the stress caused by my PhD qualifying exams. Before taking my qualifying exams, I had two main handwritings that would show up in my academic notes, and were stable for at least the previous 5 years. After my qualifying exams, which went horribly and could be considered traumatic for me, I gradually gained more and more different handwritings as more parts were being created and added to the cycle. Now, I have an uncountable number of distinct handwritings that I switch between seemingly cyclically.</p>
<p>It seems like, depending on which part of the cycle I am in, I have very different understandings of my life. I talk about this in <a href="/posts/howdidaffectswork/">How DID affects my work</a>. I can go for weeks where I am hyperfocused on work and advancing in my research, followed by weeks where I am mostly unaware that I am even a graduate student who is supposed to be working. I am trying hard to break this cycle, but it seems to be going strong. There have been several occasions where I believed I was able to stop my cycle (for example, see <a href="/posts/wakingup/">Waking up to the present</a>), but I always end up losing my awareness and advancing in the cycle. I hope someday soon my system will stabilize more so I can live the life I want to live and remain grounded to the reality of the present.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/redditrelate/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/redditrelate/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 12:25:20 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Do other people experience DID in the same way as me?</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Have you thought about how you conceptualize your internal experience, or the language you use to describe it? I personally hadn&rsquo;t given either much thought until I learned I had DID. Since then, I&rsquo;ve had a long journey of learning to understand how I operate, which has required me to think deeply about how to convey my experiences to others who likely do not operate in the same way that I do.</p>
<p>How one chooses to explain how they operate is complex and deeply personal.
As such, different people with DID may choose to convey their experiences in many different ways.
While some people are extremely creative in their portrayals of how they operate, I am someone who is more reluctant to portray myself in a way that others may deem as being too imaginative.
Because of this, I&rsquo;m still trying to find the language that feels most appropriate to describe my experiences.</p>
<p>The language one chooses is influenced by the underlying model that they use to understand what they are experiencing.
My experiences with DID seem to vary greatly, and range in severity depending on if I&rsquo;m experiencing a trauma trigger or not.
On the severe end, when parts take over my body, it can feel like I&rsquo;m being possessed and another being is controlling me.
On the other end, most often switching and shifting between parts feels so natural to me that I wonder if my experiences are even different than the norm.
To me, it seems that both these mundane and extraordinary experiences can be explained by the model of me switching, shifting, and being influenced by different compartments of memory and experience, which I call parts.</p>
<p>With time, I have realized that I see the world with multiple different perspectives&mdash;while I have the perspective of me as a whole person, I also see the perspectives of me as my individual parts.
The perspective of me as a whole person is something I was acquainted with before my DID discovery journey began, as it is what most people experience and is thus the societal norm.
On this blog, and when I discuss with others about my experiences, I typically portray the perspective of myself as a singular unified person as it&rsquo;s likely how the vast majority of people see themselves, but this language can be limiting to describe my experiences.
Writing from the perspective of me as a whole, these &ldquo;parts&rdquo; seem to be compartments of many different aspects of my life, such as memory and  identity, that I switch between to navigate through life.
For the most part, I only have the perspective of one part at any given time<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, and due to my degree of compartmentalization between parts, including amnesia and severely changing understandings of the world, depending on which compartment I am in I may have very different perspectives and things to say.
If I only portray myself as one singular unified person, I am misrepresenting aspects of my experience.
Thinking and writing as if I am a system of parts can enable me to explain experiences that simply don&rsquo;t make sense from the more restrictive whole-self perspective, like changing views about a topic, lapses in memory, possession-like experiences, losing time, and even quirks like handwriting and gait changes between parts.</p>
<p>Since starting therapy, I&rsquo;ve gradually learned to internally reference myself as a system of parts, yet I still translate that to a singular-self language when talking with others as I am hesitant to externally display my internal perspective with others.
I like portraying having a unified, singular-self view of life, even though it doesn&rsquo;t fully reflect how I&rsquo;ve learned to perceive myself.
This is probably due to the fact that it makes me uncomfortable realizing others know that the way I internally refer to myself is different than the norm.
When I was young, I was more in-touch with my individual parts' perspectives&mdash;I would often refer to myself in third person in conversation with others<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I eventually learned that others did not experience themselves in this way, as I was occasionally ridiculed for it. I learned to hide using this language, even though it was the most accurate language for my experiences, since it was not well received by others.
Perhaps because of this, I feel the same way about using other unconventional language to describe my experiences&mdash;speaking from the perspective of individual parts, like I naturally did when I was younger, is tainted with shame due to my past experiences, and something I&rsquo;m working towards getting more comfortable with when appropriate in order to become more authentically me.</p>
<p>While I am used to thinking in third person<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, thinking about myself as multiple is new<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>, and I&rsquo;m still getting used to this conceptualization and the language used to describe it.
On this blog, I have decided to use whatever language is most appropriate for describing the particular experiences that I&rsquo;m trying to convey&mdash;I don&rsquo;t want to limit myself to a particular conceptualization or vocabulary set. So while I have mostly written from the perspective of a unified self thus far, this may change as I learn what language and conceptualization feels most comfortable for me.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Although, as I&rsquo;m creating connections between parts, this is thankfully changing!&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This is because I have many parts who perceive my life in third person, and when those compartments are active, I naturally refer to myself in third person.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This is useful for trauma survivors since it allows a detached view of self&mdash;one can perceive themselves as the observer of a situation rather than a participant in it.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I didn&rsquo;t know this was an option, and it didn&rsquo;t come organically to me like the third-person perspective did. Now that I am more aware this is how I operate, I see that it aligns very well with my experiences.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/language/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/language/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 12:22:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Finding my language</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
