







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/polyfragmented/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>polyfragmented</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/polyfragmented/</link>
        
        
            <title>polyfragmented</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>One impactful but not immediately obvious symptom of DID for me is that I do not seem to have a continuous internal sense of time&mdash;my awareness of my life is shuffled.
Because of this, I may have a hard time differentiating what happened yesterday versus what happened last week or last month,
or struggle with remembering if, for example, I have leftovers in my fridge now or if that was from weeks ago.
This has made things like tracking changes in my environment difficult.
For example, I have had spring-time allergies for much of my life, but I was unable to realize that until recently&mdash;every day in the spring, I&rsquo;d wake up with allergies, but to me that was just accepted as fact. I didn&rsquo;t remember that I had allergies yesterday or every day last week, or that I didn&rsquo;t have allergies last fall, or that I&rsquo;ve had allergies every spring since childhood. All I am aware of is that I have allergies in that moment. Only since concretely tracking my symptoms this year was I able to determine that I do have springtime allergies, despite having them for years.
Life really feels like a blur to me.</p>
<p>I believe these experiences can be explained by my system structure, which is heavily impacted by the fact that I am <a href="/posts/polyfragmented">polyfragmented</a>.
I seem to shift and switch between compartments a significant amount on a daily basis, and many of these compartments, or parts, only seem to come out every few days or weeks. Since what is at the forefront of my awareness depends on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, and many of these parts only come out once in a while, the end result seems to be that my understanding of my life is very shuffled.</p>
<p>Right now, I have a hard time differentiating between these parts, which makes it difficult to map how my understanding of my life is shuffled. I can vaguely tell when the last time I was in an active compartment was because I remember those memories most prominently, but I don&rsquo;t know <em>who</em> the part is. Many of them feel the same except for mild memory differences, seemingly because I have low identity alteration.
I have been told that differentiating between parts takes time, so I am hopeful that I&rsquo;ll soon be able to identify my parts.
I&rsquo;ve been operating like this for my entire life without awareness that most others do not have such a shuffled awareness.
I&rsquo;m glad that I finally understand that I have DID and that I operate in this way, as it provides me language to contextualize my experiences. With time, I hope to gain a more broad view of my life and form a more continuous relationship with time.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/shuffledawareness/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/shuffledawareness/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 21:19:32 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Shuffled sense of time</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The word I like best to describe my flavor of DID is polyfragmented.
Polyfragmented is most commonly referred to to mean someone who has a lot of parts and/or splits parts in a complex manner. I believe I exhibit both.</p>
<p>In a more traditional case of DID, it is my understanding that a person has a relatively small number parts that are more well defined. They only have a few compartments of memory, thus allowing them to spend more time in each compartment, so each compartment has more time to develop a distinct way of being. Their switches between these parts seem to be more pronounced since each part is more well defined.</p>
<p>I believe I experience something different. In addition to having several well-developed main parts, I also seem to have many fragments, or much less developed parts. It seems like, for the most part, these parts represent smaller fractions of my life than someone with a more traditional presenting form of DID. I have more parts, along with more fragmentation and less differentiation since each part had less time to develop a distinct identity.</p>
<p>Why do I have so many parts? I believe it&rsquo;s because the threshold for what constitutes part creation is lower for me than it is for other individuals&mdash;things that would be considered traumatic to me may not affect another person as much. I believe this is due to my innate temperament, life experiences, and, perhaps most importantly, because I am autistic. Anecdotally, it seems like there&rsquo;s a high correlation between those who are polyfragmented and are autistic <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also learned that I have many different splitting patterns.
One such splitting pattern is that, when I experience something traumatic, I seem to split many parts in a sequential manner, which leads to a lot of parts being created for a single event.
I also do not only split parts due to trauma&mdash;I seem to create parts to alleviate even mild discomfort from my awareness. This is something I developed over time, as my threshold for what constituted part creation lowered as I grew older and subconsciously realized how useful of a coping mechanism creating parts was. That is, I became increasingly more fragmented as the older I became, making me more and more dysfunctional in the real world as I aged<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Rather than working with one part at a time, I&rsquo;m working with clusters of parts at any given time<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.
I do not seem to have a &ldquo;host&rdquo;, or primary, personality. Instead, I have one of a few clusters of parts active at any given time, which seem to change from week-to-week and month-to-month in an approximate cyclical pattern.
My parts do not have names&mdash;they have labels<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.
I shift and switch<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> between these parts at least a few dozen times a day, even without being triggered, because I have parts I need to access as a normal part of every day living<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>.
Since my threshold for creating parts is so low, I believe I am still creating parts in the present-day.
My system isn&rsquo;t neatly organized and structured. It&rsquo;s chaotic, messy, and unknown.</p>
<p>Now, while this may sound like a difficult way to live&mdash;and in many aspects it certainly is&mdash;I believe the language used to describe this disorder makes it sound a lot more severe than it feels internally, at least to me.
I have had DID my entire life, and I have, for the most part, lived an enjoyable and conventionally successful life despite this. I know no other way of living&mdash;this is normal to me.
However, because of my system structure, I struggle with many aspects of time and memory<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, such as knowing what day, month, or sometimes year it is when I wake up in the morning, remembering what I did yesterday, or even 5 minutes ago, and losing anywhere from minutes to weeks of time due to a trauma trigger.
Additionally, <a href="/posts/shuffledawareness/">my internal awareness of my life is shuffled</a>, so I do not have a linear narrative history of my life or day-to-day activities.
This can affect my daily functioning significantly.
Only since learning that I have DID and gaining the language to describe my experiences did I know the way I experience the world is different from most others, and could be considered disordered. However, this is my normal, and always has been.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me just over a year of therapy to get to the awareness I have today, and I know there&rsquo;s so much more I&rsquo;m unaware of.
When I take a step back and look at the facts of my situation, I can objectively see that I should be having a difficult time right now. However, I feel emotionally detached and have an overall positive worldview.
My body is designed to deal with trauma, and learning about and working with my messy system could be considered just another trauma I&rsquo;m getting through.</p>
<p>Having polyfragmented DID makes my life very chaotic. I do not know how many parts I have, nor do I think I will ever know. I have to be okay with the unknown and be open minded about the information I learn about my system. I&rsquo;ve always lived this way&mdash;I just wasn&rsquo;t aware about it until now.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I came to this conclusion from r/DID and r/OSDD on Reddit&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>until I stop relying solely on dissociation as a coping mechanism, which I&rsquo;m actively working on doing in therapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Some people call these subsystems. I seem to have many layers of compartmentalization&mdash;my parts have their own parts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>They may have nicknames, but not many do. There are too many of them for it to make sense for them to have names. Plus, naming parts of myself with human names other than my own doesn&rsquo;t feel comfortable for me.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>I use <em>switch</em> to denote a hard, discrete change between parts, which usually occurs when I&rsquo;m triggered and can be disorienting. I use <em>shift</em> to denote a smooth change between parts, which occurs more often than switching for me and can internally feel like a gear shifting in my brain.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>I have many task-based parts, or parts that serve a specific job in my life, which leads to me needing to shift or switch between parts on a very regular basis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>My symptoms include more than just time and memory problems, but those aren&rsquo;t explicitly due to my system structure, and may be addressed in later posts.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/polyfragmented/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/polyfragmented/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 21:11:40 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Why do I call myself “polyfragmented”?</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
