







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/narrative/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>narrative</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/narrative/</link>
        
        
            <title>narrative</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I began therapy for DID in January 2022, I had no idea how much my life had already spiraled out of control. Over the course of several years, I had gone from being a high-achieving student at the top of my class to being effectively unable to work because I was so triggered by the world around me.
However, because of my severe internal compartmentalization, I was unaware of my dysfunction&mdash;I had no idea anything abnormal was happening, and, for the most part, thought I was still the successful student I previously was.
I went from being an over-achiever to effectively dysfunctional.
This is because work went from a source of fun and inspiration to a source of stress, so work became triggering to me. There are a variety of factors that affect why work became so triggering, but the end result is the same&mdash;just as in the past I learned to avoid traumatic or stressful things by dissociating away from them, I continued the pattern and subconsciously learned to dissociate away from work.</p>
<p>Within my system structure, I have separate compartments for work, which are differentiated enough from my other compartments such that when the work parts aren&rsquo;t out, I&rsquo;m practically unaware of my work life.
However, because my work parts are so compartmentalized, when my work parts are out, I&rsquo;m able to hyperfocus on work, undistracted by the happenings of the world around me.
This is something I developed as a child&mdash;I learned to separate my work and home lives because they were so different.
When my system is running smoothly, the right parts come out on queue, working together harmoniously. My internal compartmenalization of different facets of my life has always been severe, and since it had had worked well in the past, I had never questioned it before.</p>
<p>During graduate school, over the span of several years, as work gradually became more and more triggering for me, my work parts slowly started coming out less and less organically. I began a cycle of behavior: when work was not stressful, I&rsquo;d work as normal. Then, when something stressful would come up, it&rsquo;d become much more difficult to work. For a period of time spanning days to weeks, I&rsquo;d be effectively unable to work, but I&rsquo;d be unaware that I wasn&rsquo;t working as normal. Then, I&rsquo;d inevitably become aware that I was &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; at work, and force myself to start work again, which was always incredibly difficult as I was working through being triggered. Once the stressor was alleviated or sufficiently forgotten about, I&rsquo;d be back to working as normal again. And then when the next stressor came up, the cycle would repeat.</p>
<p>This cycle has repeated at least a dozen times during my PhD thus far, and each time it has repeated, new parts would be created to &ldquo;take control of my life again&rdquo; once I realized I was not working productively. Because of this, my awareness of my work life has become increasingly fragmented. For me, my handwriting is a great indicator to differentiate between parts.
For most of my undergraduate years, I had two main handwritings, indicating the two main work parts who were consistent through the entirety of undergrad. But in graduate school, my handwriting has become much more inconsistent. Because of the way I&rsquo;ve split work parts, I can see in my academic journal that, over the span of several months, I&rsquo;m writing the same concepts down over and over again, all in different handwritings. I have difficulty picking up where the previous part left off, so I practically have to start my work all over again once a new part is created. It&rsquo;s clear that I&rsquo;m trying really hard to advance in work, but because I&rsquo;m creating new compartments to work as opposed to utilizing the old ones, my awareness of my work life has become extremely fractured and inconsistent.</p>
<p>Why am I creating new parts instead of using already created work parts? I&rsquo;m not entirely sure, but I can speculate. I believe it&rsquo;s because <a href="/posts/polyfragmented/">I am polyfragmented</a>, so I create parts really easily. And because the previous parts I subconsciously create to take control of my life eventually become too stressed to come out, I create new parts who are unaware of the stress in order to advance.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s taken me an incredibly long time to gain the insight that I have now, and even now that I&rsquo;ve gained this insight, it&rsquo;s hard for me to break the cycle. Right now, I&rsquo;m at the stage that I&rsquo;m aware that this is how I operate, but I&rsquo;m not yet at the place where I&rsquo;m able to change it&mdash;I&rsquo;m stuck observing my cyclical parts.
I seem to have very little control over what goes on in my life, but it&rsquo;s starting to get better.
I am learning to become aware of what stage of the cycle I&rsquo;m in at any given time, which has allowed me to stay in the stage where work parts are out longer and the stage where I&rsquo;m dysfunctional shorter. I&rsquo;m making progress, but it&rsquo;s slow and incredibly difficult.</p>
<p>I truly hate that this is the way I operate. I do not enjoy being so stressed by my work that my dissociative defenses are constantly activated. There are large spans of time where I&rsquo;m totally unaware of work because I&rsquo;m so stressed by it, followed by times where I&rsquo;m hyperaware of how much I&rsquo;ve been &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; on work and have to pick up the pieces, over and over again.
To be clear, I do not believe I&rsquo;m &ldquo;slacking&rdquo; when I&rsquo;m in a stage of the cycle where I&rsquo;m unable to work. Rather, I consider myself to be in a triggered state that I have little to no control over. But from the outside looking in, if one is unaware that I have DID, it really looks like I do not care about my PhD and am intentionally slacking on my responsibilities.
This has been incredibly frustrating to come to terms with, as my behavior is still mostly out of my control as I am constantly responding to triggers in my environment, yet I have the strong desire to break the cycle.</p>
<p>What is the path forward? Ideally, I&rsquo;d like to stop this cyclical behavior so I can work as normal again. I want to stop creating new parts when I get too stressed. I want to have one or two dedicated work parts out like I did in my undergraduate years so my awareness of my work life isn&rsquo;t so fragmented. I want to stop being so triggered by work that my dissociate defenses are constantly activated. I truly just want to become productive at work again, and while I see the light at the end of the tunnel, I have a long way to go before I get there. For now, I&rsquo;ll take it one day at a time, as I slowly take back control of my life.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/howdidaffectswork/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/howdidaffectswork/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 04:18:25 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>How DID affects my work</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>DID is very much internal disorder. That is, unless I tell you that I have it, you wouldn&rsquo;t know<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. One of the ways DID affects my internal experience is that I have significant gaps in my memory, both of my past childhood, and of my present adulthood.
But amnesia is tricky&mdash;I don&rsquo;t know what I don&rsquo;t remember, so most of the time I don&rsquo;t realize I&rsquo;ve forgotten anything.</p>
<p>I believe I experience amnesia in a few ways.
The most innocuous type that I experience seems due to me having constricted awareness&mdash;each of my parts seems to act as a compartment of memory, so when I&rsquo;m in one compartment it may be difficult for me to index memories that occurred when I was in a different compartment of memory.
For example, if my partner talks about a hike we went on a few months ago when I&rsquo;m in a task-based compartment for cleaning, I may not remember the hike, but I may eventually get a very vague memory of it if they prompt me about it further. If I see a picture of us on the hike, it may help queue my memory of it more, but it still isn&rsquo;t a complete memory like it would be if I were in the compartment that was actually there on that hike.
I believe this is because hiking and cleaning occupy two entirely different compartments of my life; there&rsquo;s little in common between the two, and my constricted awareness makes it so that these memories aren&rsquo;t shared well between the two parts. This seems to be a version of state-dependent memory.</p>
<p>I also experience full amnesia between parts. That is, I will not have access to any of the memories of one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This typically seems to occur between compartments that hold trauma memories and ones that do not, but I also seem to experience this between non-trauma holding parts, and I&rsquo;m not yet sure why.</p>
<p>Within full amnesia, I seem to exhibit two types. The first is when I experience a discrete jump in my awareness when I switch between compartments where I have no idea what was happening just before the switch. This causes an obvious jump in my awareness, and may make it more noticeable that I have amnesia. I might find myself, all of a sudden, in a different room than I remember being in just a second ago, when in reality another part had moved me to that room outside of my awareness<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. I experienced this when I was younger<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, but not as much as I&rsquo;ve gotten older. Now, I more so seem to have a sliding-window type memory&mdash;rather than a discrete jump in awareness, my memory of what happened gradually disappears over several minutes after a switch. This leads to a perceived smoother transition between parts, making my memory loss less obvious to me.</p>
<p>Regardless of the type of amnesia I have, I experience shuffling of memories and time jumps&mdash;I do not have a continuous, linear understanding of my life. For example, it may be hard for me to differentiate what occurred last week vs what occurred years ago, and sometimes things that occurred months ago feel more current to me than things that occurred even yesterday. As always, this seems to be justified by my understanding of how I operate&mdash;if I&rsquo;m in a compartment of memory that was last active a few months ago, those memories are more at the forefront of my awareness than memories formed in a different compartment yesterday.
This leads to a lot of confusing experiences, like looking out of my window and expecting it to be winter but seeing that it&rsquo;s actually summer, or all of a sudden noticing that the furniture in my apartment has moved from what I last remember, or looking at my plants and being amazed by how much they had grown because I remembered them being much smaller.
These sorts of experiences occur on an a weekly to daily basis for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still early on in my DID discovery journey, so my understanding of my amnesia will likely change over time as I learn more about how I operate.
I hope this post serves as a snapshot in time of my awareness of how I operate a little over one year after starting therapy.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Unless you really know what to look for or you catch me in a dissociative episode, neither of which are likely.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, I have never had a full dissociative fugue where I end up in an entirely different location than I was before. Most of my dissociative episodes occur at home when I&rsquo;m alone or in when I&rsquo;m in threapy.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This, along with other symptoms, led to me receiving a dissociative disorder diagnosis as a pre-teen.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/amnesia/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/amnesia/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 12:10:19 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Dissociative amnesia</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Imagine if, without your awareness, your deepest, most repressed thoughts and feelings were displayed for the world to see. With how my DID presents, this is something that occurs quite frequently for me. Because much of my most difficult emotions are separated from the core me, I am usually unaware of them until they surface and they&rsquo;re in the forefront of my awareness. Then, after they are over, I may forget that these dissociative episodes ever happened. This has led to me into many scary and sometimes dangerous situations, which typically leave me puzzled by what is happening in the world around me.</p>
<p>As an example, I like to go on evening walks for exercise. I typically walk one of a few routes in the densely populated city I live in. One day this past summer, I walked by a person who had some of the same characteristics as someone who caused me harm in the past. I walked by this individual without awareness that I was at all triggered. Then, in a split second, they started yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;You&rsquo;re scared of me, huh? What do you have to be scared about?&rdquo;</p>
<p><em>What?</em> It was so out of context for me; I had no idea why they were yelling at me. I wasn&rsquo;t scared of them&mdash;up until they started yelling at me, I hadn&rsquo;t even noticed them. I ignored them and calmly kept walking in the direction I was going. Then, they started moving towards me<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, continually yelling at me.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Why are you scared of me? You think I&rsquo;m threatening? There&rsquo;s nothing to be scared about!&rdquo;</p>
<p>I sped up walking and continued ignoring them. I felt very calm while this was happening, although I was confused by what going on. I eventually made it to the next block over and lost sight of them. I calmly walked home, and went out of my way to reassure myself that I had done nothing wrong, and that the person was at fault, not me. But <em>why</em> did this person think I was scared of them? Was I scared of them?</p>
<p>As it turns out, a part of me <em>was</em> scared of them. When I saw that person, that part became so scared, that they momentarily took control of our face and made a scared microexpression, directed at that person. However, I had no awareness that I was scared of them or that I had made any facial expression. This is because the parts of me who were on my evening walk were not connected with the part of me that was scared of the person, so from the perspective of the part of me that was going on a walk, I had no idea that anything abnormal was happening, while the scared part was simultaneously terrified.</p>
<p>Over the next few days, I intentionally went on my evening walk, purposefully walking past the location of the event to ensure I didn&rsquo;t associate anything negative with it. The parts of me walking felt perfectly fine, and I didn&rsquo;t realize anything was off.
Then, within a week, without realizing it, I stopped going on my evening walks. A month went by, and I still avoided walking, but it didn&rsquo;t even occur to me that I stopped.
I went from walking every day for months to only leaving my apartment when absolutely necessary. I didn&rsquo;t feel any fear associated with walking or leaving my apartment, but it was clearly there, dictating my behavior. It took over a month for me to realize anything was wrong, and once I pondered why I was no longer walking the reason became obvious&mdash;a part of me was still clearly scared of what had happened on that walk.
In order to get back to my walking routine, I gradually had to show that part that we were safe, and that that wasn&rsquo;t going to happen again, and even if it did, there were other parts who could take care of the situation like we had done last time. With this awareness in mind, over time, I managed to get back to going on my evening walks.</p>
<p>This is one example of how having DID affects my life and functioning. Before I became aware that I have DID, I was unaware of how much influence my parts had over my life. My behaviors are influenced by fear I cannot even grasp onto or feel. Other people may be more aware of my own internal state than even I am, since my body language may be contradictory to how I feel on the inside.
Getting to know my parts is helping me to become more aware of my internal state, and, in turn, will allow me to live a more complete life.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Thankfully, they used a walker, so I was in little danger.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/partscontrol/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/partscontrol/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:30:21 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>The parts I don’t know about still have control</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was initially hesitant to write about anger, as it&rsquo;s an emotion I am not used to feeling<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
How could I write about something I know nothing about?
But I now realize that the absence of anger in my life is significant in itself, and is indicative of how I operate.</p>
<p>Anger is an emotion that I am simultaneously very sensitive to, yet not at all familar with&mdash;I am incredibly sensitive to the external display of anger in others, yet not at all familiar with how it feels internally.
I believe this is because when I was small, I grew up in an environment where my primary caregiver frequently displayed anger.
This is because they had unprocessed trauma of their own, which came out as fits of rage.
These bouts of anger were extremely terrifying for me as a young child, and ended in emotional and sometimes physical harm done to me.
Because of the repeated association of anger with terror, pain, and instability, I believe I learned to internally separate anger as a &ldquo;bad&rdquo; emotion, and shoved it away as an emotion that I did not want to experience.
My relationship with anger was tainted by my early childhood experiences, making a powerful emotion that should be utilized as part of an emotionally healthy life inaccessible to me as an adult.</p>
<p>I once naively believed that not feeling anger was an asset of mine&mdash;that anger was a disruptive emotion, and it was safer for me not to feel it. While it is beneficial to those around me for me to not ever display anger, I now believe that anger is an important emotion that should be part of my emotional repertoire.
Anger enables people to enact change. By my not being able to experience anger, I&rsquo;m more likely to stay involved in situations and environments which are not good for me, making me to be more likely to be repeatedly victimized.
Due to my upbringing, I learned to value other peoples' comfort over my own, and use dissociation to subconsciously withhold my sometimes justified anger.</p>
<p>I believe that because I have DID<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, my dynamic range of emotions is very shallow&mdash;most of the time, I feel mild contentment. I grew up in an environment where I didn&rsquo;t feel like I could take up any emotional space, as the emotional landscape in my family of origin was dominated by others' strong emotional displays. I enjoy my internal stability&mdash;I do not want to feel strong emotions. I am scared of the loss of control I was so used to seeing in others while growing up.
However, this separation of anger and other emotions leads to a less full life, including amnesia, behavior that feels out of my control when I&rsquo;m triggered, along with stunted &ldquo;good&rdquo; emotions, like happiness and excitement. By using dissociation, I&rsquo;ve traded experiencing a full range of emotions for internal stability. This served me well in the past, but in the future I&rsquo;d like to live a more full, complete life&mdash;one that does not rely on maladaptive dissociative coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>While I now see anger as a valuable emotion, my learned patterns of removing it from my awareness continue, so still I have difficulty accessing it.
My understanding of anger comes from a theoretical view&mdash;I can intellectually understand it, but I do not believe I have felt genuine anger before. With time, I hope that will change.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>And maybe I was right to be hesitant, as I don&rsquo;t have much to say since I&rsquo;m early in my awareness journey, but I want to document my understanding of things at various stages of healing.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>I believe I am this way due to how I responded to experiences in my childhood, which resulted in me forming maladaptive coping mechanisms which can be labeled DID.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/anger/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/anger/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 11:05:58 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anger</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was 12, I stopped feeling anxiety. Prior to that, I was a child ravished by anxiety. Then, one day, it stopped<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. And I have never experienced anxiety in the same way since.</p>
<p>I now understand that anxiety is one of the experiences that I dissociated away&mdash;it&rsquo;s a state that I did not enjoy experiencing, so I learned how to compartmentalize it and push it out of my awareness.
This doesn&rsquo;t mean I do not <em>experience</em> anxiety; rather, it means that when I do, I am so detached from it that I do not experience all aspects of it.</p>
<p>My body trembles, lower lip quivers, and heart races, yet I don&rsquo;t know why I am experiencing these physical symptoms.
My mind races with irrational thought loops, yet I can&rsquo;t quite grasp onto them so they feel like meaningless noise to me.
I am disconnected and emotionally numb. Except for when I am not.</p>
<p>When I am able to connect with the feeling of anxiety, it is all-encompassing and feels everlasting. When something triggers anxiety to the forefront of my awareness, it is all I can concentrate on, and I will do whatever I need to do to alleviate the feeling. Then, all of a sudden, it goes away as quickly as it came, and after it&rsquo;s over I gradually forget that it ever happened.</p>
<p>Right now, as I write this, I do not know what anxiety feels like. Parts of me do, but I am not connected with those parts. For the most part, I feel like an emotionless machine, going through the motions of life. Despite the fact that I&rsquo;m unable to connect with anxiety, that doesn&rsquo;t mean it doesn&rsquo;t affect me. My behaviors are controlled by fear and anxiety that I cannot feel&mdash;I can only intellectually infer that I am being affected by anxiety by examining my behaviors. I avoid leaving my apartment, interacting with others, and doing things that may eventually lead to stressful situations. Yet I do not experience the associated emotions with these behaviors&mdash;I am numb.</p>
<p>When I was 12, I didn&rsquo;t become a less anxious person&mdash;I just became more detached from my anxiety. My crippling anxiety wasn&rsquo;t miraculously cured. Instead, it was like fixing a wound that needed stitches with a band-aid&mdash;an easy, temporary solution that left me worse-off in the long term.</p>
<p>In order to decrease my amnesia and regain control of my life, I need to connect back with my anxiety.
Although it allows me to avoid difficult feelings in the moment, my current method of dealing with anxiety&mdash;compartmentalizing it and shoving it from my awareness&mdash;leads to uncontrollable fear-based behavior, a lack of internal awareness, and amnesia. I need to connect with this destabilizing experience once again, this time working though it instead of shoving it from my awareness. Then, I can address its root causes and gain control of my life again.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My mom reports me having a discrete personality change when this occurred.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/anxiety/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/anxiety/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 19:17:28 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Anxiety</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have always been nerdy. From a young age, I immersed myself in academic work, as I enjoyed learning and the strict routine that school provided for me. I also had an intense need to perform well&mdash;my perfectionistic tendencies dominated my life as a child. While I often did perform well academically, there were times where I performed markedly poorly on assessments, so far outside the norm of what would have ordinarily be expected of me, despite preparing and knowing the material. For example, on one occasion in high school, I was so prepared for an exam that I helped tutor my friends about the material leading up to it, only for me to fail while they performed well. I wasn&rsquo;t ordinarily a bad test taker&mdash;I genuinely didn&rsquo;t understand the material when exam time came. To put it simply, there were times when I was smart, and times when I was&hellip; not. I  now understand this to be as a result of having DID.</p>
<p>Some of my parts were formed when I was a small child. When I am in these compartments, although I may be aware that I am an adult, I typically have the mental ability of around the age in which those parts developed. These compartments are essentially snapshots of my mindset at the time they were created, with varying levels of awareness of the present day. One major implication of this is that my ability to understand information varies depending on which compartment of awareness I am in. For example, I have a younger, very timid part that sometimes comes out that has the mental ability of a 7-year-old. When this part is active, I am unable to grasp onto the complex topics required of me for my PhD that I can normally do with relative ease when the right part of me is active. I am not aware of what I do not know, believing what I know in that moment is all that I do know. This part of me often comes out around others while I&rsquo;m supposed to be having intellectual discussions. The results are humiliating&mdash;I am unable to discuss even my own research, which the right parts of me are very familiar with. Many a time I have left a meeting feeling absolutely defeated and frustrated that I was unable to discuss my research properly. However, there were other times, when the correct parts were out, that I was very much able to hold an academic discussion about my work. My fluctuating knowledge of my work has detrimentally impacted my academic career thus far.</p>
<p>Before I knew I had DID, I never questioned my fluctuating levels of intelligence. However, I did come up with a justification for my poor performance&mdash;when I was in compartments that weren&rsquo;t aware of my more academic parts, I truly believed that I was dumber than all of my peers. I believed that any time I had performed well I had cheated, and I had faked my way to where I am today as a PhD student. There are times where I&rsquo;d look at my academic papers, ones that I had written, and not only did I not understand what the material was about, but I didn&rsquo;t fully remember writing them. I developed extreme imposter syndrome as a result of this&mdash;I truly didn&rsquo;t feel like I belonged in my institution, and I believed that I had genuine reasons as to why.</p>
<p>It has only been within the last several months that I&rsquo;ve been able to identify when I&rsquo;m in a compartment of awareness that is not necessarily able to understand the material required of me in order to complete my degree, and I now see that the difference in ability is pronounced. When one of these parts of me are active, I now stop working and try to understand why it is out. What is preventing me from accessing the compartments of me that do work? Sometimes the answer is obvious; other times, I&rsquo;m not so sure. Most frequently, however, I don&rsquo;t realize that a non-academic part has been out until after it has already gone, when I relook at a problem that I was previously agonizing over and it becomes obvious. I&rsquo;m still trying to understand these parts of myself, but just knowing that my having DID explains much of my academic distress really helps me understand why I am the way that I am.</p>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/fluctuatingintelligence/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 21:52:50 -0400</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Fluctuating intelligence</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Pretty early on in my DID discovery journey, I realized that my handwriting was different depending on which part of me was writing. This was very useful information, as I had taken well-catalogued academic notes for years prior to starting therapy, so I had a solid bank of data of which I could look back on and see which parts of me were active at different times of my life.</p>
<p>One thing I quickly noticed was that any time I traveled to a conference, my handwriting changed. And then when I got back, my handwriting changed back to whatever was normal at that time of my life<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
Internally, this also made sense&mdash;I tend to index my life by location rather than time. In fact, in all of my notebooks' index sections, I had added a column for location, in addition to the standard page number and date. My mind likes segmenting my life based on location.</p>
<p>Why could this be the case? Why do I create parts when I travel? Looking back at my life story, it actually makes a lot of sense.
My first several years of life involved a lot of traveling. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad&rsquo;s job.
As a perk of being an expat, my dad&rsquo;s job paid for two vacations a year&mdash;one for rest and relaxation, and another to visit family.
Because of this, by my 5th birthday, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips.</p>
<p>This sounds like an incredibly fortunate childhood, and while it was, it was also very stressful for me.
As an autistic person, I regulate myself by following a strict routine. As an adult, changes in plans are very dysregulating, and usually leave me in a detached dissociated state with difficulty picking up the newly created plans.
I can only imagine how dysregulating it was for me as a small child to have my routine entirely upended every several months to travel to a new environment with an unknown routine.
I had no option&mdash;my family chose to travel, and since within my family structure the emotional landscape was already dominated by others, I had to be an easy child and submit to whatever they wanted. This led to me dissociating and creating parts to handle the traveling for me.</p>
<p>This past summer, I went to my first conference while aware that I create parts this way.
The night leading up to the event, I remember absolutely dreading the trip, wishing I could back out but knowing that I couldn&rsquo;t. Then, when the time came, I genuinely enjoyed the conference&mdash;the right part showed up for the job. I did seem to create a part for this trip, and this was the first part that I was self-aware I was creating. I had no control over it; instead, I observed its creation as I walked into the hotel lobby to check in. A new persona emerged, and was ready to take on whatever routine was required of me for my week-long conference that was just getting started. With that part as the dominant part, other parts came out periodically to do what was required of me, like networking, socializing, and presenting. But this newly created part was the star of the show, helping me create a solid routine I could stick to throughout the week to help keep me regulated. Then, on the last day, once again the dread came&mdash;this time, I, as the newly created part, didn&rsquo;t want to change my routine back again as I was only familiar with the one I had created. However, when I arrived in my apartment after a long journey back, a different part switched in and I was so glad to be home and back again in my standard routine.</p>
<p>We traveled to many beautiful locations in my early childhood, and I truly appreciate all the culturally enriching experiences I acquired, which I believe to this day have helped shaped my worldview. I do, however, wish that my parents were more aware of how stressful this was for me as a child. I did not understand the significance of the locations we would visit, and felt as though I was being dragged from place to place without understanding what was going on around me. In pictures of our family vacations, it&rsquo;s clear that I am dissociating&mdash;many of them show me with a blank expression with my eyes glazed over. I learned to regulate myself by dissociating, detaching from the world around me. And these repeated experiences of traveling = part creation have continued throughout my life, increasingly fragmenting my awareness when I take trips.</p>
<p>I believe this is a good example of how trauma, but not necessarily abuse, can lead to the formation of DID.
I would not consider traveling as much as we did abuse, but it was traumatic because it was too much for me to handle at the developmental stages it occurred in.
One could argue that this was neglect or negligence&mdash;that my parents weren&rsquo;t attuned to my emotional needs at the time.
However, it does not fit into the category of extreme abuse that is often attributed to the creation of DID.
While I do not believe this was the only trauma that caused me to form DID, and some of those traumas would be considered abuse,
traveling in the way that we did when I was small had a major impact on how I create parts, and is perhaps the most influential mechanism of part creation in my adult life.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My handwriting isn&rsquo;t usually discretely clear, and is often a blend of many different parts' handwritings. However, on several trips my handwriting made a clear enough change for me to notice this pattern.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/traveling/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/traveling/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 22:14:57 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Parts are created from trauma, not necessarily abuse</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
