







    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            <atom:link href="/tags/mechanism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        
        
        <description>mechanism</description>
        
            <language>en-us</language>
        
        
        <link>/tags/mechanism/</link>
        
        
            <title>mechanism</title>
        
        
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Pretty early on in my DID discovery journey, I realized that my handwriting was different depending on which part of me was writing. This was very useful information, as I had taken well-catalogued academic notes for years prior to starting therapy, so I had a solid bank of data of which I could look back on and see which parts of me were active at different times of my life.</p>
<p>One thing I quickly noticed was that any time I traveled to a conference, my handwriting changed. And then when I got back, my handwriting changed back to whatever was normal at that time of my life <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
Internally, this also made sense&mdash;I tend to index my life by location rather than time. In fact, in all of my notebooks' index sections, I had added a column for location, in addition to the standard page number and date. My mind likes segmenting my life based on location.</p>
<p>Why could this be the case? Why do I create parts when I travel? Looking back at my life story, it actually makes a lot of sense.
My first several years of life involved a lot of traveling. Although I was born in the US, when I was just over 2 months old, my family moved to the Middle East for my dad&rsquo;s job.
As a perk of being an expat, my dad&rsquo;s job paid for two vacations a year&mdash;one for rest and relaxation, and another to visit family.
Because of this, by my 5th birthday, I had been to 11 different countries between 4 continents, all on separate trips.</p>
<p>This sounds like an incredibly fortunate childhood, and while it was, it was also very stressful for me.
As an autistic person, I regulate myself by following a strict routine. As an adult, changes in plans are very dysregulating, and usually leave me in a detached dissociated state with difficulty picking up the newly created plans.
I can only imagine how dysregulating it was for me as a small child to have my routine entirely upended every several months to travel to a new environment with an unknown routine.
I had no option&mdash;my family chose to travel, and since within my family structure the emotional landscape was already dominated by others, I had to be an easy child and submit to whatever they wanted. This led to me dissociating and creating parts to handle the traveling for me.</p>
<p>This past summer, I went to my first conference while aware that I create parts this way.
The night leading up to the event, I remember absolutely dreading the trip, wishing I could back out but knowing that I couldn&rsquo;t. Then, when the time came, I genuinely enjoyed the conference&mdash;the right part showed up for the job. I did seem to create a part for this trip, and this was the first part that I was self-aware I was creating. I had no control over it; instead, I observed its creation as I walked into the hotel lobby to check in. A new persona emerged, and was ready to take on whatever routine was required of me for my week-long conference that was just getting started. With that part as the dominant part, other parts came out periodically to do what was required of me, like networking, socializing, and presenting. But this newly created part was the star of the show, helping me create a solid routine I could stick to throughout the week to help keep me regulated. Then, on the last day, once again the dread came&mdash;this time, I, as the newly created part, didn&rsquo;t want to change my routine back again as I was only familiar with the one I had created. However, when I arrived in my apartment after a long journey back, a different part switched in and I was so glad to be home and back again in my standard routine.</p>
<p>We traveled to many beautiful locations in my early childhood, and I truly appreciate all the culturally enriching experiences I acquired, which I believe to this day have helped shaped my worldview. I do, however, wish that my parents were more aware of how stressful this was for me as a child. I did not understand the significance of the locations we would visit, and felt as though I was being dragged from place to place without understanding what was going on around me. In pictures of our family vacations, it&rsquo;s clear that I am dissociating&mdash;many of them show me with a blank expression with my eyes glazed over. I learned to regulate myself by dissociating, detaching from the world around me. And these repeated experiences of traveling = part creation have continued throughout my life, increasingly fragmenting my awareness when I take trips.</p>
<p>I believe this is a good example of how trauma, but not necessarily abuse, can lead to the formation of DID.
I would not consider traveling as much as we did abuse, but it was traumatic because it was too much for me to handle at the developmental stages it occurred in.
One could argue that this was neglect or negligence&mdash;that my parents weren&rsquo;t attuned to my emotional needs at the time.
However, it does not fit into the category of extreme abuse that is often attributed to the creation of DID.
While I do not believe this was the only trauma that caused me to form DID, and some of those traumas would be considered abuse,
traveling in the way that we did when I was small had a major impact on how I create parts, and is perhaps the most influential mechanism of part creation in my adult life.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>My handwriting isn&rsquo;t usually discretely clear, and is often a blend of many different parts' handwritings. However, on several trips my handwriting made a clear enough change for me to notice this pattern.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/traveling/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/traveling/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 22:14:57 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>Parts are created from trauma, not necessarily abuse</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&hellip; it&rsquo;s about childhood trauma.</p>
<p>Dissociative Identity Disorder (DID) can be thought of as a coping mechanism one may develop when they experience repeated trauma in early childhood. It is arguably one of the most misunderstood and controversial mental health conditions, perhaps because it&rsquo;s been repeatedly sensationalized in the media. Or, maybe because the name and clinical description of the disorder implies that it&rsquo;s about having multiple identities or personality states. However, these personality states are often incredibly subtle and are instead indicative of a post-traumatic reaction involving severe internal compartmentalization.</p>
<p>DID is a highly individualized disorder which forms based off of one&rsquo;s reaction to their life experiences. As such, I can only speak for myself and how I personally experience this disorder. While DID can be difficult to understand, it can be thought of as being fundamentally about two psychological phenomena&mdash;<em>detachment</em> and <em>compartmentalization</em>. Using myself as an example, when I was small, there were times where I experienced severe repeated abuse<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, but at other times had a happy childhood. While I was being abused, I mentally <em>detached</em> myself from the situation&mdash;I disconnected from my body and the external world, choosing instead to escape into my mind to distract myself from a situation I knew no other way to get out of. Perhaps more importantly, I also internally <em>compartmentalized</em> the experience and shoved it from my awareness, effectively allowing me to forget that it even occurred after it was over as I lived an otherwise happy childhood<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. Because this abuse occurred repeatedly, I continually used this strategy of switching to the compartment that held the abuse when I experienced triggers that the abuse was going to happen again. Then, when the abuse was over, I would switch back to the compartment that had a happy childhood and was blissfully unaware of the abuse that was taking place. This repeated pattern of switching between compartments further increased my compartmentalization of memory, awareness, experience, and identity. However, this was incredibly protective, as it allowed some parts of me to learn and grow as a child while other parts of me held the difficult memories and feelings of being abused out of awareness. All of this was done on a subconscious level.</p>
<p>This strategy of compartmentalization can only develop when trauma occurs in early childhood, while the brain still is rapidly developing and has the capacity to use such defenses. And because I learned to use these defenses when I was very young and my brain wired based on my experiences of the world around me, I learned that this was a very effective strategy for minimizing psychological discomfort.
Because of this, over time my threshold for what constituted compartment creation lowered as I relied more and more on this coping mechanism.
Because I was able to compartmentalize my experience, I subconsciously learned to separate the good aspects of my life&mdash;like emotions of happiness, contentment, and good memories&mdash;from the bad aspects of my life&mdash;like anger, grief, and memories of trauma.
Additionally, I learned to use compartmentalization in areas of my life that weren&rsquo;t inherently traumatic.
While this started as a very effective coping mechanism in response to childhood trauma, it has rapidly turned maladaptive as I have continually created compartments to respond to adult stressors.</p>
<p>Rather than fluidly being able to access all aspects of my personality like a more integrated individual, I have to switch between discrete personality states as I move throughout life.
While many of these compartments share memory (i.e., when I am in one compartment of memory, I will likely remember at least most of what happened when I was in a different compartment of memory), when I switch between compartments it can feel like a RAM drop&mdash;my working memory, or what I was actively thinking about, gets wiped.
I also have compartments of memory with varying degrees of amnesia between them, so I genuinely may not remember what happened when I was in one compartment when I&rsquo;m in a different compartment. This lack of memory sharing typically happens between compartments who hold traumatic memories and emotions and ones who do not.
Additionally, depending on which memory compartment I&rsquo;m in, I will have different motivations and awareness of my current life. So while I may be an enthusiastic PhD student in several compartments, I also have compartments where I have no idea what my research is, or even that I am a student working towards my degree.
Sometimes, instead of fully taking over, these compartments intrude on my awareness, so I may have unexplained feelings of, say, fear that I have no idea where is coming from or what is triggering it.</p>
<p>For a long time, I was adamant that I did not experience identity alteration. I&rsquo;m now realizing that while I do have many compartments that all seem to identify as &ldquo;me&rdquo;, some compartments are so far removed from present time and context that, when I am in them, I do not perceive myself as being the adult me I actually am.
The identity alteration I do experience is incredibly subtle, and is much more an internal phenomena than an external one&mdash;an external observer will most likely not be able to tell apart my parts <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. These parts are just different versions of me, so even with the identity alteration I do have, I see these parts as all being <em>me</em>.</p>
<p>So DID is really not <em>about</em> identity, even if that&rsquo;s the most sensationalized part of the disorder. I personally see the identity alteration and switching/influence of multiple personality states as merely a side effect of a brilliant psychological defense mechanism in response to early childhood trauma. But while it&rsquo;s not about identity explicitly, the fact that one has several distinct identities<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> as opposed to a single unified one can be a major component to the disorder that may severely affect, both positively and negatively, how one experiences life with DID.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This example is an oversimplification, and this severe abuse occurred outside the home. However, I did experience less severe abuse and other traumas within my family which shaped my development of this disorder as well.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This was not fully the case, but I wanted to emphasize the differential between the good and bad parts of my childhood to provide a more concrete example of how parts in DID may split.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>For the most part, I still can&rsquo;t even tell apart my parts. This is something that I&rsquo;m sure I will get better at with time, as I get more acquainted with how I operate.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>These distinct indentities are not whole on their own. Rather, they represent different parts of my whole personality. Rather than having one unified identity, I have several fragmented identities/personality states that I switch between.&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></description>
                
                
                    <guid>/posts/notaboutidentity/</guid>
                    <link>/posts/notaboutidentity/</link>
                
                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 21:43:08 -0500</pubDate>
                
                
                    <title>It’s not about identity</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
